<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:17:51 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:17:51 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Natural daylight during office hours improves glucose control and whole-body substrate metabolism</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.006</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 793
Autoren: Jan-Frieder Harmsen, Ivo Habets, Andrew D. Biancolin, Agata Lesniewska, Nicholas E. Phillips, Loic Metz, Juan Sanchez-Avila, Marit Kotte, Merel Timmermans, Dzhansel Hashim, Soraya S. de Kam, Gert Schaart, Johanna A. Jörgensen, Anne Gemmink, Esther Moonen-Kornips, Daniel Doligkeit, Tineke van de Weijer, Mijke Buitinga, Florian Haans, Rebecca De Lorenzo, Hannah Pallubinsky, Marijke C.M. Gordijn, Tinh-Hai Collet, Achim Kramer, Patrick Schrauwen, Charna Dibner, Joris Hoeks
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.006
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.006-2026-01-18-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Aluminium adjuvants and childhood health: a call for science</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtemb.2025.127810</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 148
Autoren: Guillemette Crépeaux, Jeremy R. Hammond, Jonathan B. Handley, Brian Hooker, Karl Jablonowski, Lluís Luján, James Lyons-Weiler, Marika Nosten-Bertrand, Christopher A. Shaw, Yehuda Shoenfeld, Lucija Tomljenovic, Christopher Exley
Journal: Journal of Trace Elements in Medicine and Biology
Veröffentlicht: 2026-02-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jtemb.2025.127810
ISSN: 0946-672X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jtemb.2025.127810-2026-01-18-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cytoarchitectural multi-depot profiling reveals immune-metabolic crosstalk in human colon-associated adipose tissue</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.12.008</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 143
Autoren: Jutta Jalkanen, Jiawei Zhong, Pamela A. Nono Nankam, Nayanika Bhalla, Merve Elmastas, Jiaxin Luo, Sophie Weinbrenner, Scott Frendo-Cumbo, Benedek Pesti, William Gourash, Anita Courcoulas, Zinger Yang Loureiro, Arne Dietrich, Jesper Bäckdahl, Anders Thorell, Marcus Buggert, Joanna Kalucka, Margo P. Emont, Evan D. Rosen, Matthias Blüher, Peter Kovacs, Patrik L. Ståhl, Lucas Massier, Mikael Rydén, Niklas Mejhert
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.12.008
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.12.008-2026-01-18-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Enhanced non-enzymatic H2S generation extends lifespan and healthspan in male mice</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.012</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 136
Autoren: María Ángeles Cáliz-Molina, Raúl López-Fernández-Sobrino, Inmaculada Pino-Pérez, Concepción Panadero-Morón, María del Carmen Vilches-Pérez, María Camacho-Cabrera, Almudena García-Ruiz, Leopoldo Pérez-Rosendo, Isabel Espadas, Alejandro Sola-García, Mario Soriano-Navarro, Franz Martin, Mónica Venegas-Calerón, Joaquín Jesús Salas, Enrique Martínez-Force, Luis C. Romero, Ángeles Aroca, Román González-Prieto, Máximo Bernabeu-Wittel, Vivian Capilla-González, Christopher Hine, Alejandro Martín-Montalvo
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.012
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.012-2026-01-18-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Nutrition Strategies for Next‐Generation Incretin Therapies: A Systematic Scoping Review of the Current Evidence</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/obr.70079</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 122
Autoren: Marie Spreckley, Cara F. Ruggiero, Adrian Brown
Journal: Obesity Reviews
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-07
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  Next‐generation incretin therapies, including semaglutide and tirzepatide, have transformed obesity and Type 2 diabetes management. However, evidence‐based nutritional strategies to support safe and effective use of these agents remain limited. To address this gap, we conducted a systematic scoping review across five databases of studies published between January 2015 and April 2025 to map and appraise clinical trials incorporating nutritional interventions or dietary assessments during semaglutide or tirzepatide therapy in adults with obesity or Type 2 diabetes. Eligible studies included adults receiving semaglutide or tirzepatide with either an active dietary intervention or measured nutrition‐related outcomes. Study quality was assessed using established tools. Twelve studies were included: 10 randomized controlled trials, one non‐randomized comparative study, and one cross‐sectional observational study. Interventions ranged from structured very‐low‐energy or ketogenic diets to general lifestyle counseling and observational dietary assessments. Across studies, energy intake decreased by 24% to 39%, but lean tissue loss accounted for up to 40% of total weight reduction. Only three studies involved nutrition professionals, and systematic assessment of protein or micronutrient intake was rare. One observational study found widespread nutrient inadequacies and limited access to dietetic support. Despite the effectiveness of semaglutide and tirzepatide for weight loss, evidence on optimal dietary strategies is sparse. Early dietitian involvement, high‐protein, nutrient‐dense diets, and routine nutritional monitoring should be prioritized. Robust trials are needed to define best practice for integrating dietary care alongside pharmacotherapy.
DOI: 10.1111/obr.70079
ISSN: 1467-7881
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/obr.70079-2026-01-18-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>