<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:59:43 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Personalised gait retraining for medial compartment knee osteoarthritis: a randomised controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00151-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 942
Autoren: Scott D Uhlrich, Valentina Mazzoli, Amy Silder, Andrea K Finlay, Feliks Kogan, Garry E Gold, Scott L Delp, Gary S Beaupre, Julie A Kolesar
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00151-1
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00151-1-2025-09-17-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Knee crepitus and osteoarthritis features in young adults following traumatic knee injury</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25637</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 161
Autoren: Jamon L Couch, Brooke E Patterson, Kay M Crossley, Ali Guermazi, Matthew G King, Danilo De Oliveira Silva, Jackie L Whittaker, Michael A Girdwood, Adam G Culvenor
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-25
Abstract: ObjectiveThis study explored the association between knee crepitus and the presence, and worsening, of structural osteoarthritis features and self‐reported outcomes in young adults following traumatic knee injury.MethodsOne‐year following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction (ACLR), 112 participants (41 female participants; median age 28 years) self‐reported the presence/absence of knee crepitus using an item from the Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS). Patellofemoral and tibiofemoral osteoarthritis features (i.e. cartilage lesions, osteophytes, bone marrow lesions) were assessed from MRIs at 1‐ and 5‐years post‐ACLR. Self‐reported outcomes were assessed with two KOOS subscales (pain, quality of life [QoL]) and the International Knee Documentation Committee subjective evaluation form (i.e. self‐reported function). Poisson regression evaluated the relationship between self‐reported crepitus and the presence/worsening of structural osteoarthritis features. General linear models explored the relationship between crepitus and self‐reported outcomes.ResultsSelf‐reported crepitus was associated with full‐thickness patellofemoral cartilage lesions 1‐year post‐ACLR (prevalence ratio 2.70, 95%CI 1.41, 6.39) but not the risk of worsening structural osteoarthritis features between 1‐ and 5‐years post‐ACLR. Those with crepitus reported worse pain (β ‐6.42, 95%CI ‐10.47, ‐2.36), QoL (β ‐10.39, 95%CI ‐18.58, ‐2.20) and function (β ‐5.49, 95%CI ‐10.92, ‐0.06) 1‐year post‐ACLR, but greater improvement in pain and function between 1‐ and 5‐years.ConclusionSelf‐reported knee crepitus was associated with the presence of full‐thickness patellofemoral cartilage defects 1‐year post‐ACLR, but was not associated with a greater risk of worsening structural osteoarthritis features up to 5‐years post‐ACLR. One‐year post‐ACLR, those with crepitus reported worse pain, knee‐related QoL, and function.
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25637
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25637-2025-09-17-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Long-term effectiveness of non-surgical interventions for chronic low back pain: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00064-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 123
Autoren: Hazel J Jenkins, Leticia Corrêa, Benjamin T Brown, Giovanni E Ferreira, Casper Nim, Sasha L Aspinall, Deborah Wareham, Junghyun Choi, Christopher G Maher, Mark J Hancock
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00064-5
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00064-5-2025-09-17-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>American College of Rheumatology Guidance Statement for Diagnosis and Management of VEXAS Developed by the International VEXAS Working Group Expert Panel</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43287</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 61
Autoren: Arsene M. Mekinian, Sophie Georgin‐Lavaille, Marcela A. Ferrada, Sinisa Savic, Matthew J. Koster, Olivier Kosmider, Thibault Comont, Mael Heilblig, Juan I. Arostegui, Annmarie Bosco, Rim Bourguiba, Katherine R. Calvo, Catherine Cargo, Chiara Cattaneo, François Chasset, Henrique Coelho, Corrado Campochiaro, Francesca Crisafulli, Stephanie Ducharme‐Benard, Raquel Faria, Franco Franceschini, Micol Frassi, Emma M. Groarke, Carmelo Gurnari, Yervand Hakobyan, Yvan Jamilloux, Ciprian Jurcut, Yohei Kirino, Austin Kulasekararaj, Hiroyoshi Kunimoto, Lauren M. Madigan, Heřman F. Mann, Chiara Marvisi, Marcin Milchert, Sara Morais, Katja Sockel, Francesco Muratore, Hideaki Nakajima, Mrinal M. Patnaik, Luísa Regadas, Marie Robin, Abraham Rutgers, Carlo Salvarani, Anthony M. Sammel, Joerg Seebach, Pierre Sujobert, Alessandro Tomelleri, Geoffrey Urbanski, Frédéric Vandergheynst, Romana Vieira, David S. Viswanatha, Ewa Więsik‐Szewczyk, Elisa Diral, Benjamin Terrier, Bhavisha A. Patel, Pierre Fenaux, Peter C. Grayson, David B. Beck, the International VEXAS working group, and with endorsement of EuroBloodNet, the European Reference Network in Rare Hematological Diseases
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-11
Abstract: ObjectiveVacuoles E1 enzyme X‐linked autoinflammatory somatic syndrome (VEXAS) is a recently identified rare genetic disorder associated with somatic mutations in the UBA1 gene. VEXAS presents with a combination of inflammatory and hematologic manifestations, leading to increased morbidity and mortality.MethodsGiven the variability in disease presentation and the limited number of studies to date, no clinical documents currently exist to provide guidance to health care providers about the management of VEXAS. To address this gap, we formed an international multidisciplinary panel of VEXAS experts.ResultsThrough formalized meetings and a voting process, the group developed consensus clinical guidance considerations for the management of VEXAS. These considerations offer practical advice on several key topics: (1) clinical features of VEXAS, (2) UBA1 screening methods, (3) the diagnosis of myelodysplastic syndromes (MDSs) in patients with VEXAS, and (4) prognosis and management. The aim is to provide expert guidance on which patients to test, how to test for VEXAS, how to approach MDS in the context of VEXAS, and considerations for management.ConclusionThis work marks the first formal international consensus guidance for VEXAS and is intended to be used as a resource for clinicians seeking to understand the disease and its management.
DOI: 10.1002/art.43287
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43287-2025-09-17-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>EULAR recommendations for a core dataset to support clinical care and translational and observational research in systemic lupus erythematosus</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 38
Autoren: Johanna Mucke, George Bertsias, Martin Aringer, Laurent Arnaud, Carina Boström, Ricard Cervera, Gamal Chehab, László Czirják, Lene Wohlfahrt Dreyer, Luís Inês, Søren Jacobsen, Charite Kjaerside Nielsen, Emiliano Marasco, Marta Mosca, Kirsi Myllys, Cristina Pamfil, Jose M. Pego-Reigosa, Jutta G. Richter, Savino Sciascia, Farah Tamirou, Michel Tsang-A-Sjoe, Edward M. Vital, Ronald Van Vollenhoven, Chris Wincup, Matthias Schneider
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.001
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.001-2025-09-17-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>