<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 01:05:23 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 01:05:23 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Validity, reliability, and clinical usefulness of instruments for measuring thoracic kyphosis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101246</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 88
Autoren: Ana Paula Flôr Alves Nepomuceno, Ana Carolina Cury, Larissa Santos Pinto Pinheiro, George Schayer Sabino, Thales Rezende Souza, Sérgio Teixeira Fonseca, Juliana Melo Ocarino, Renan Alves Resende
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101246
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101246-2025-09-07-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scapular kinematics variability in individuals with and without rotator cuff-related shoulder pain: A systematic review with multilevel meta-regression</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 48
Autoren: Rubén Fernández-Matías, Jorge Ballesteros-Frutos, Pablo Gallardo-Zamora, Néstor Requejo-Salinas, Iván Caballero-Pozo, Paula Ludewig, Enrique Lluch-Girbés
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261-2025-09-07-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cervical flexion posture during smartphone use was not a risk factor for neck pain, but low sleep quality and insufficient levels of physical activity were. A longitudinal investigation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 28
Autoren: Igor Macedo Tavares Correia, Arthur de Sá Ferreira, Jessica Fernandez Mosqueira Gomes, Felipe José Jandre Reis, Leandro Alberto Calazans Nogueira, Ney Meziat-Filho
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258-2025-09-07-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and safety of allogeneic mesenchymal precursor cells with and without hyaluronic acid for treatment of chronic low back pain: a prospective, randomized, double blind, concurrent-controlled 36-month study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.spinee.2025.03.015</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 19
Autoren: Douglas P. Beall, Hyun W. Bae, Michael J. DePalma, Kasra Amirdelfan, Edward Tavel, Timothy T. Davis, James Scott Bainbridge, Arnold Weil, William Beckworth, Kee Kim, Philip Yuan, Pragya B. Gupta, Eugene Wang, Bradley S. Goodman, Ryan Reeves, Michael B. Furman, Nagy Mekhail, David Nunez, Michael DiMuro, Matthew C. Shonnard, Eric Rose, Roger D. Brown
Journal: The Spine Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.spinee.2025.03.015
ISSN: 1529-9430
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.spinee.2025.03.015-2025-09-07-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Medial Tibial Stress Syndrome Needs a New Name—Make No Bones About It</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13411</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 18
Autoren: Laura M. Anderson, Stuart J. Warden, Richard W. Willy, Daniel R. Bonanno, Hylton B. Menz
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-18
Abstract:  Pain near the posteromedial tibia is common in running and jumping athletes. This problem has had many names, with “shin splints” and “medial tibial stress syndrome” (MTSS) the most common. The term shin splints is nonspecific and nondescript, and has never gained clinical traction. Similarly, the clinical use of MTSS with athletes and coaches is often met with confusion as ‘tibial stress’ is frequently misinterpreted as indicating a bone stress injury. With no conclusive evidence regarding the pathophysiology of MTSS, we advocate renaming it “Load Induced Medial-Leg Pain” (LIMP). LIMP avoids the use of ‘tibial stress’ which is problematic due to the unknown pathology of the condition and its confusion with bone stress injury. Using the term LIMP instead of MTSS gives clinicians, researchers, and athletes a clearer, more accurate way to approach managing exercise-related lower leg pain. 
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13411
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13411-2025-09-07-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>