<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:18:22 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:18:22 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Clinical and cost-effectiveness of a cycling and education intervention versus usual physiotherapy care for the treatment of hip osteoarthritis in the UK (CLEAT): a pragmatic, randomised, controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00102-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 140
Autoren: Thomas W Wainwright, Tikki Immins, Sharon Docherty, Geoff Saunders, Annie Hawton, Elizabeth Goodwin, Tim Rees, Matthew Low, Jo Samways, Fran Webley, Nikki Howard, Paul H Lee, Robert G Middleton
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00102-x
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00102-x-2025-11-23-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>EULAR 2025 classification criteria for haemochromatosis arthropathy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 36
Autoren: Patrick DW Kiely, Stephanie Finzel, Bayram Farisogullari, Graeme J. Carroll, Geraldine McCarthy, John Stack, Simone Parisi, Graça Porto, Pascal Richette, Gyorgy Nagy, Marton Weidl, Ann Rosenthal, Pascal Guggenbuhl, Katarzyna J. Banaszkiewicz, Svenja Engelhardt, Jeremy D. Shearman, David Mitchell, Jane Barker, Valerie Brueton, Barbara Butzeck, Philip Coathup, Howard Don, Jacqueline Dowsett, Marie Duncan, Tracey Dunleavy, Ian Fish, Allin Hoggarth, Mark McKinnon, James Minter, Tim Osborne, Marguerite Smith, Christine Wright, Pedro M. Machado
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003-2025-11-23-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Group-based cycling and education for hip osteoarthritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00154-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 32
Autoren: Troels Kjeldsen, Inger Mechlenburg
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00154-7
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00154-7-2025-11-23-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Advances in the pathophysiology, diagnosis and treatment of Takayasu arteritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41584-025-01309-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 23
Autoren: Amr H. Sawalha, Durga P. Misra, Ruchika Goel, Fatma Alibaz-Oner, Kaitlin A. Quinn, Peter C. Grayson, Haner Direskeneli
Journal: Nature Reviews Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-06
DOI: 10.1038/s41584-025-01309-7
ISSN: 1759-4790
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41584-025-01309-7-2025-11-23-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Methotrexate use in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis associated-interstitial lung disease: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/rheumatology/keaf538</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 19
Autoren: Ines Mahmoud, Fatma Majdoub, Selma Bouden, Leila Rouached, Olfa Saidane, Raoudha Tekaya, Aicha Ben Tekaya, Leila Abdelmoula
Journal: Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-24
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Objectives
                    To assess the progression of the interstitial lung disease related to rheumatoid arthritis (RA-ILD) with Methotrexate (MTX) exposure, and to evaluate the lung involvement in RA non-ILD patients with MTX exposure.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    A systematic review was performed including studies of RA patients reporting the effect of MTX on ILD, as a primary or secondary end point.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Sixteen studies were included in the systematic review. The total number of patients was 36 444, of which 18 548 (50.8%) were declared on MTX. Patients on MTX were classified into two groups, based on whether they were experiencing ILD. Comparison with control groups was performed to assess the development and/or the progression of ILD in MTX users. Non exposed MTX subjects (N-MTX) were considered as the control group in 14 studies. To evaluate the pulmonary state, studies carried out different evaluation methods: High-Resolution Computed Tomography (10 studies), pulmonary function tests (8 studies), arterial blood gas analysis (one study) and survival (5 studies). MTX was not associated with a risk of developing ILD (9 studies). Five studies suggested that MTX was not associated with the progression of RA-ILD. An accelerated decline in lung function was observed with low-dose MTX (one study). Better survival was shown in MTX patients compared with the N-MTX group (one study). In one study, MTX use was significantly associated with the development of acute exacerbations.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    MTX appears to have no association with an increased risk of ILD and/or its progression in RA patients.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/rheumatology/keaf538
ISSN: 1462-0324
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/rheumatology/keaf538-2025-11-23-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>