<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:04:22 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:04:22 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of ultra-processed food consumption on male reproductive and metabolic health</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.08.004</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 1005
Autoren: Jessica M. Preston, Jo Iversen, Antonia Hufnagel, Line Hjort, Jodie Taylor, Clara Sanchez, Victoria George, Ann N. Hansen, Lars Ängquist, Susan Hermann, Jeffrey M. Craig, Signe Torekov, Christian Lindh, Karin S. Hougaard, Marcelo A. Nóbrega, Stephen J. Simpson, Romain Barrès
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.08.004
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.08.004-2025-11-04-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Handgrip Strength and Trajectories of Preclinical Obesity Progression: A Multistate Model Analysis Using the UK Biobank</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1210/clinem/dgaf521</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 475
Autoren: Manrong Xu, Menghan Li, Yawen Zhang, Lianxi Li, Yun Shen, Gang Hu
Journal: The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp;amp; Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-15
Abstract: Abstract
               
                  Purpose
                  Grip strength has been increasingly recognized as a predictor of chronic disease risk and mortality. The aim of our study was to investigate the association of grip strength and the trajectories of preclinical obesity progression.
               
               
                  Methods
                  Data were collected from 93 275 participants in the UK Biobank. Preclinical obesity was diagnosed based on an excess of anthropometric parameters, defined as elevated body mass index combined with at least 1 abnormal measure among waist circumference, waist-to-hip ratio, waist-to-height ratio, or percentage body fat, in the absence of obesity-induced dysfunctions. Three models captured different trajectories from baseline to dysfunctions and death, with or without intermediate progression. A multistate model was used to investigate the association between grip strength and the preclinical obesity progression and multiple-cause mortality risk. Sensitivity analyses were performed using free muscle volume, total lean mass, and muscle-to-weight ratio as exposures.
               
               
                  Results
                  Among 8163 death events over a mean follow-up of 13.4 years, each SD increase in grip strength was associated with a significantly reduced risk of preclinical obesity progression at each stage, with the strongest inverse association observed in baseline to first dysfunction [fully adjusted hazard ratio (HR): 0.86, 95% confidence interval (CI): 0.85-0.88]. Compared to the lowest tertile, the highest grip strength significantly showed protective effects across all trajectory models, with double dysfunctions to all-cause death yielding the most pronounced associations (fully adjusted HR: 0.77, 95% CI: 0.70-0.84). Further subgroup and sensitivity analysis showed consistent results.
               
               
                  Conclusion
                  Increased grip strength was significantly associated with a decreased risk of obesity-induced dysfunctions progression and multiple-cause mortality. These findings underscore the importance of improving muscle mass and strength in preclinical obesity.
               
DOI: 10.1210/clinem/dgaf521
ISSN: 0021-972X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1210/clinem/dgaf521-2025-11-04-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Paternal exercise confers endurance capacity to offspring through sperm microRNAs</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.003</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 427
Autoren: Xin Yin, Azhar Anwar, Linbo Yan, Ranran Yu, Yang Luo, Liang Shi, Botao Li, Jiehao Chen, Gaoli Liang, Yongci Chen, Jie Tang, Jie Liang, Yansheng Kan, Zhihao Zhang, Xiahuan Zhou, Jizheng Ma, Chenbo Ji, Yanbo Wang, Qipeng Zhang, Jing Li, Liang Li, Xiaozhi Zhao, Feng Yin, Liyuan Sheng, Dijun Chen, Tao Zhang, Chen-Yu Zhang, Xi Chen
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.003
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.003-2025-11-04-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of sweeteners and sweetness enhancers on weight management and gut microbiota composition in individuals with overweight or obesity: the SWEET study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s42255-025-01381-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 387
Autoren: Michelle D. Pang, Louise Kjølbæk, Jacco J. A. J. Bastings, Sabina Stoffer Hjorth Andersen, Alexander Umanets, Mônica Maurer Sost, Santiago Navas-Carretero, Kyriakos Reppas, Graham Finlayson, Charo E. Hodgkins, Marta del Álamo, Tony Lam, Hariklia Moshoyiannis, Edith J. M. Feskens, Tanja C. M. Adam, Gijs H. Goossens, Jason C. G. Halford, Joanne A. Harrold, Yannis Manios, J. Alfredo Martinez, Ellen E. Blaak, Anne Raben
Journal: Nature Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-07
DOI: 10.1038/s42255-025-01381-z
ISSN: 2522-5812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s42255-025-01381-z-2025-11-04-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Adipocyte lipolysis activates epithelial stem cells for hair regeneration through fatty acid metabolic signaling</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.012</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 270
Autoren: Kang-Yu Tai, Chih-Lung Chen, Sabrina Mai-Yi Fan, Chen-Hsiang Kuan, Chun-Kai Lin, Hsin-Wen Huang, Hao-Wei Lee, Shiou-Han Wang, Nai-Wen Chang, Jian-Da Lin, Che-Feng Chang, Kai-Chien Yang, Maksim V. Plikus, Sung-Jan Lin
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.012
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.012-2025-11-04-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>