<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 01:09:40 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 01:09:40 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Perineuromal Botulinum Toxin Injection for War-Related Postamputation Pain: A Pragmatic, Multicenter, Comparative Effectiveness Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 352
Autoren: Nadiya Segin, Roman Smolynets, Joana Barroso, Natalia Matolinets, Paul F. Pasquina, Steven P. Cohen
Journal: Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026
ISSN: 0003-9993
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026-2025-11-24-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Natural Speech Analysis Can Reveal Individual Differences in Executive Function Across the Adult Lifespan</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00268</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 131
Autoren: Hsi T. Wei, Dana Kulzhabayeva, Lella Erceg, Mira Kates Rose, Kiah A. Spencer, Jessica Robin, Ellen Bialystok, Jed A. Meltzer
Journal: Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-07
Abstract: 
                    Purpose:
                    Automated analysis of naturalistic speech has emerged as an effective tool for detecting cognitive decline in dementia but has seldom been used to examine the ordinary cognitive decline occurring in normal aging. Executive function (EF) declines throughout the adult lifespan but is difficult to track longitudinally due to practice effects, making speech-based assessments particularly attractive. This study examined relationships between EF and speech characteristics.
                  
                  
                    Method:
                    We collected two audio picture descriptions from participants in two experiments that also included EF assessments, with 67 healthy older adults (aged 65–75 years) in Study 1 and 174 healthy adults (aged 18–90 years) in Study 2. Language composite scores were computed by aggregating relevant speech features indexing aspects of speech that have been reported to show changes in pathological aging. Principal components reflecting common covariation in speech features were extracted from a large training data set to compute speech domain scores. The relationships between language composites/speech principal components and EF were assessed while controlling for age, gender, and education.
                  
                  
                    Results:
                    In Study 1, older adults' word-finding difficulties, measured as speech disfluencies, showed significant associations with EF. Study 2 confirms that speech disfluencies can explain individual differences in EF not only for adults above the age of 65 years but also across the adult lifespan. Information units and coherence in speech showed weaker associations with EF and Montreal Cognitive Assessment scores that were not significant after correction for multiple comparisons.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion:
                    The findings revealed associations between word-finding ability in natural speech and general EF across the adult lifespan, supporting natural speech analysis as a convenient and sensitive assessment of general cognitive ability.
                  
DOI: 10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00268
ISSN: 1092-4388
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00268-2025-11-24-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>(Not so) universal literacy screening: a survey of educators reveals variability in implementation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11881-025-00342-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 51
Autoren: Ola Ozernov-Palchik, Zoe Elizee, Fabio Catania, Meral Hacikamiloglu, Stefanie Shattuck-Hufnagel, Yaacov Petscher, Satrajit Ghosh, John D. E. Gabrieli
Journal: Annals of Dyslexia
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-29
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Currently, most states in the United States have enacted legislation mandating universal screening for literacy risk in kindergarten through 3rd grade. However, the degree to which these policies translate into consistent, high-quality screening practices remains unclear. In this survey study, we collected responses from a diverse sample of K–3 educators (
                    N
                     = 251) across 39 states, representing varied school types, professional roles, and experience levels, to examine the real-world implementation of universal screening. Guided by the Exploration, Preparation, Implementation, and Sustainment (EPIS) framework, we analyzed quantitative and qualitative data to identify real-world factors that could impede the fidelity and effectiveness of screening implementation. We found substantial variability across multiple dimensions of literacy screening implementation. Educators described considerable variation in screener selection, administration practices, testing environments, training quality, scoring accuracy, and the use of results to guide intervention. Notably, many indicated insufficient training and professional development, expressing uncertainty about administering and interpreting screeners, particularly for English language learners. Nearly half also reported the absence of systematic procedures for developing intervention plans, suggesting that many students identified as at risk do not receive appropriate follow-up support. These implementation challenges occurred despite widespread recognition among educators of screening’s importance for early literacy intervention. Educators from lower-socioeconomic status schools reported significantly greater time burdens in conducting screenings and more technology-related challenges compared to their higher-SES counterparts. Without systematic improvements to implementation support and training, current screening initiatives may fail to achieve their intended goal of early identification and intervention for struggling readers.
                  
DOI: 10.1007/s11881-025-00342-1
ISSN: 0736-9387
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s11881-025-00342-1-2025-11-24-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Episode of Care Characteristics Following Implementation of a No Co-pay Physical Therapy Program for Musculoskeletal Conditions</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/ptj/pzaf129</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 43
Autoren: Trevor Lentz, Adam Lutz, Uchechukwu Ikeaba, Brooke Alhanti, Steven Z George, Chad Cook, Charles Thigpen
Journal: Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-24
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Importance
                    New care models promoting early access to physical therapy by reducing or eliminating co-pays are emerging. Few studies have compared health care use in these programs to other care pathways across musculoskeletal conditions.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    The objective of this study was to describe episode-level musculoskeletal health care use across different care pathway options, including a no-copay physical therapy program.
                  
                  
                    Design
                    This study was a descriptive retrospective analysis of claims data.
                  
                  
                    Setting and Participants
                    This study included health care beneficiaries of a self-insured employer with approximately 52,000 covered lives.
                  
                  
                    Interventions or Exposures
                    The study included musculoskeletal care episodes from October 2019 to September 2020 categorized as no copay physical therapy, traditional physical therapy, or other management.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcomes
                    Rates of surgery/injection, imaging, inpatient services, physician services, emergency services, physical therapy, and other services by episode type, overall and stratified by body region: upper extremity, lower extremity, and spine.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Of 9696 total episodes, 886 (9.1%) were no copay physical therapy, 1261 (13%) were traditional physical therapy, and 7549 (77.9%) were other management. No copay physical therapy episodes had lower imaging rates (38%) compared to traditional physical therapy (47%) and other management (45%) episodes. Inpatient services were similar for no copay (16%) and traditional (12%) physical therapy, both lower than other management episodes (23%). Physician services were higher in other management (100%) and traditional physical therapy (81%) episodes compared to no copay physical therapy episodes (43%). Surgery/injection rates were similar for no copay (11%) and traditional (8%) physical therapy, both lower than other management episodes (27%). Differences by pathway were more pronounced for extremity conditions than for spine conditions.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    Rates of no copay program use were modest with those who used the program having lower rates of advanced imaging, injection, and surgery.
                  
                  
                    Relevance
                    Findings may be most relevant for employers, health systems, and payors planning resource allocation and benefit design for similar programs.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/ptj/pzaf129
ISSN: 0031-9023
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/ptj/pzaf129-2025-11-24-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Genomic Investigations of Spoken and Written Language Abilities: A Guide to Advances in Approaches, Technologies, and Discovery</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00152</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 42
Autoren: Simon E. Fisher
Journal: Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-11
Abstract: 
                    Purpose:
                    The aim of this tutorial is to show how the rise of molecular technologies and analytical methods in human genetics yields exciting new ways to understand the biological foundations of spoken and written language. The focus is on complementary strategies capturing genetic variation of different kinds (rare gene disruptions and common DNA polymorphisms), discussing how these can be associated with developmental speech, language, and reading disorders as well as with interindividual differences in the general population.
                  
                  
                    Results:
                    
                      The first half of the tutorial discusses rare variants that are sufficient themselves to cause a severe speech and/or language disorder. This begins with lessons learned from studying
                      FOXP2
                      disruptions that cause childhood apraxia of speech, accompanied by impaired language production and comprehension, before considering how genome or exome sequencing has uncovered pathogenic variants in an array of additional neurodevelopmental genes, including
                      CHD3
                      ,
                      DDX3X
                      ,
                      KAT6A
                      ,
                      SETBP1
                      ,
                      SETD1A
                      ,
                      WDR5
                      , and
                      ZFHX4
                      . The second half of the tutorial covers the study of common DNA variants with individually tiny effect sizes, highlighting the challenges of robustly associating them with variability in language-related skills. Against this background, a shift from small candidate gene studies to large-scale genome-wide association study designs is transforming the landscape of the field, gaining leverage from team science approaches and personal genomics. The shift is illustrated with selected examples of recent studies of relevant quantitative measures and diagnostic status in many thousands of participants.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusions:
                    This work demonstrates the dramatic impact genomic innovations are having on the language sciences and how molecular genetic approaches can address long-standing questions about neurobiology and the evolution of distinctive human traits. Potential translational consequences for speech or language pathology vary according to the types of DNA variation and will benefit from enhanced communication about the roles of genomics in clinical contexts.
                  
DOI: 10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00152
ISSN: 1092-4388
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00152-2025-11-24-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>