<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:17:45 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:17:45 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and Safety of Subcutaneous Anifrolumab in Systemic Lupus Erythematosus: the Randomized, Phase 3, TULIP‐SC Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.70041</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 69
Autoren: Susan Manzi, Ian N. Bruce, Eric F. Morand, Richard Furie, Yoshiya Tanaka, Kenneth C. Kalunian, Anca Askanase, Patricia Puzio, Emon Khan, Jenny Wissmar, Michael Song, Catharina Lindholm, The TULIP‐SC investigators
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-29
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    The multinational, phase 3, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled TULIP‐SC trial evaluated the efficacy and safety of subcutaneous anifrolumab in adults who have moderate‐to‐severe SLE activity, despite receiving standard therapy.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Adults with SLE received subcutaneous anifrolumab 120 mg or placebo once weekly for 52 weeks (1:1 randomization). Only the primary endpoint (treatment difference in BILAG‐based Composite Lupus Assessment [BICLA] response at 52 weeks) was formally tested in a pre‐planned interim analysis; key secondary and other endpoints were tested in the full analysis.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      At the interim analysis (220 patients, anifrolumab: n=109; placebo: n=111), the primary endpoint was met (anifrolumab vs placebo: 59.4% vs 43.9%; BICLA response difference [95% confidence interval]=15.5% [2.3–28.6%],
                      p
                      =0.0211).
                    
                    
                      The full analysis included 367 patients (anifrolumab: n=184; placebo: n=183). Versus placebo, more patients treated with anifrolumab attained a BICLA response whilst maintaining low/reduced oral glucocorticoid doses through Week 52 (56.2% vs 34.0%; difference=22.3% [12.3−32.2]
                      p
                      &amp;lt;0.0001), and the time to first sustained BICLA response was reduced (Hazard ratio=2.2 [1.5−3.2];
                      p
                      &amp;lt;0.0001). Treatment differences in Week 52 DORIS remission and Low Lupus Disease Activity State attainment rates favored anifrolumab over placebo (14.2% [5.6−22.8%],
                      p
                      =0.0012, and 14.1% [4.6−23.6%],
                      p
                      =0.0038). The frequencies of serious adverse events were 11.9% with anifrolumab and 10.4% with placebo; the frequencies of herpes zoster were 3.8% and 1.1%, respectively.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Consistent with the well‐established profile of intravenous anifrolumab, subcutaneous anifrolumab demonstrated significant, clinically meaningful treatment benefits when added to standard therapy, and an acceptable safety profile in patients with moderate to severe SLE.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/art.70041
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.70041-2026-01-18-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Genome‐Wide
                    DNA
                    Methylation Study Reveals Specific Signatures in the Affected Arterial Tissue of Patients With Giant Cell Arteritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43358</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 38
Autoren: Gonzalo Borrego‐Yaniz, Ana Márquez, Elkyn Estupiñán‐Moreno, Laura C. Terrón‐Camero, Miguel A. González‐Gay, Santos Castañeda, Giuliana Guggino, David Saadoun, Pietro Lio, Simona Fontana, Martina Bonacini, Alessandro Rossi, Alberto Cavazza, Francesco Muratore, Carlo Salvarani, Nicolo Pipitone, Javier Martin, Stefania Croci, Lourdes Ortiz‐Fernández
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-11
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    Giant cell arteritis (GCA) is a large‐vessel vasculitis, potentially causing complications such as blindness and strokes. This study aims to gain insights into the pathogenesis of GCA by identifying specific DNA methylation signatures in the arterial tissue of patients with this vasculitis.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    DNA methylation profiling was analyzed in 79 temporal artery biopsy samples (69 patients with GCA and 10 controls) by performing an epigenome‐wide association study (EWAS). Differential analysis was performed to identify differentially methylated positions (DMPs) and differentially methylated regions (DMRs). Lastly, we compared our findings with previous transcriptomics and epigenomics studies on GCA‐affected arteries.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      EWAS identified 3,644 DMPs (
                      P
                      
                        adj
                      
                      &amp;lt; 0.05, |Δβ| &amp;gt; 0.3), indicating a profound alteration within GCA‐affected arterial tissue. These DMPs were annotated to 1,517 potentially dysregulated genes. A total of 282 additional genes were identified by annotation of significant DMRs. Pathway enrichment analysis revealed a significant alteration of inflammatory mechanisms, such as interleukin‐2 and interleukin‐7, as well as pathways related to vascular remodeling. Omics study comparison revealed 37 genes consistently affected across datasets, many of them linked to immune signaling and T cell regulation. Notably, markers of exhausted T cells, including
                      SLAMF6
                      and
                      HAVCR2
                      , were present among them.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Our study identified GCA‐specific DNA methylation signatures in arterial tissue, revealing disrupted inflammatory and vascular pathways and suggesting the involvement of exhausted T cells in this condition. These findings offer new insights into GCA pathogenesis and provide new potential targets for the treatment of this debilitating disease.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/art.43358
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43358-2026-01-18-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Impact of Positive Lifestyle Behaviors on Direct Health Care Cost Savings for Low Back Pain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25653</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 26
Autoren: Ye Tian, Katharine E. Roberts, Michelle Hall, Paula R. Beckenkamp, Angelo Sabag, Karoline Moe, Ana Paula Carvalho‐e‐Silva, Emily J. Callander, Paulo H. Ferreira
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-14
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    This study aimed to investigate the relationship between a previously purpose‐developed lifestyle behavior scale and health care cost savings related to low back pain (LBP).
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    This longitudinal study used data from the Australian Twin Back (AUTBACK) study. LBP and lifestyle behavior measures were collected at baseline. Physical activity (PA) was objectively quantified via an accelerometer. A lifestyle behavior scale was created using variables of body mass index, PA, smoking status, and sleep quality. Weekly health care use for LBP was collected over one year. Health care costs were calculated by aggregating expenses for health care visits and medications, encompassing personal and Australia Medicare costs, and analyzed by two‐part models.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Individuals with lower lifestyle behavior scores, women, and those with a baseline episode of LBP were more likely to incur health care use costs (n = 307). A total of 2.6% of participants accounted for over 56% of the total expenditures. A one‐point improvement in the lifestyle behavior scale was significantly associated with 23% decrease in overall health care costs for LBP (95% confidence interval [CI] 7%−36%;
                      P
                      = 0.006), 25% decrease in medication costs for LBP (95% CI 13%−35%;
                      P
                      &amp;lt; 0.001), and 27% decrease in health care visit costs for LBP (95% CI 14%−39%;
                      P
                      &amp;lt; 0.001). The predicted difference in yearly health care use costs between individuals with the lowest and highest lifestyle scores was AU$873.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    This study demonstrated the association between greater adherence to positive lifestyle behaviors and reduced health care costs related to LBP. Interventions aimed at improving lifestyle behaviors could yield substantial cost savings for individuals and the health care system, mitigating the burden of LBP.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25653
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25653-2026-01-18-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Reactive Oxygen Species–Induced Modifications of Fibrin Clots as a Link Between Immune Responses and Atherothrombosis in Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43371</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 24
Autoren: Matteo Becatti, Giacomo Emmi, Alessandra Bettiol, Amanda Mannucci, Flavia Rita Argento, Eleonora Fini, Serena Borghi, Francesca Nencini, Maria Nicastro, Irene Mattioli, Elena Silvestri, Augusto Vaglio, Domenico Prisco, Claudia Fiorillo
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-28
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    Cardiovascular events are major determinants of morbidity and mortality in systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), particularly in patients with renal involvement. Although oxidative stress has been implicated in driving vascular and renal damage in SLE, the specific mechanisms remain unclear. This study investigated the potential role of oxidative stress‐induced alterations in fibrinogen structure and function in the pathogenesis of atherothrombosis in SLE.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    In this cross‐sectional study, we enrolled 144 adult patients with SLE and 90 matched controls. We measured blood leukocyte reactive oxygen species (ROS) production, systemic redox status, and the structural and functional features of purified fibrinogen. Correlations between these parameters and disease activity were also investigated. In vitro experiments to clarify the causal relationships among ROS levels, protein oxidation, and fibrin abnormalities provided mechanistic insights of the observed alterations.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Patients with SLE showed increased leukocyte ROS production, mainly due to neutrophil NADPH oxidase activation. Interestingly, renal biopsies from patients with SLE with active proliferative lupus nephritis exhibited overexpression of the NADPH oxidase enzyme complex p22phox. This was accompanied by plasma oxidative stress as indicated by elevated plasma lipid peroxidation and reduced antioxidant defenses. Fibrinogen oxidation was associated with structural and functional changes, leading to the formation of denser fibrin networks with lower clot porosity and reduced susceptibility to plasmin‐mediated fibrin lysis. Interestingly, these fibrinogen modifications correlated with alterations in redox status and disease activity.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Oxidative stress may drive structural and functional modifications of fibrinogen in SLE, potentially acting as a novel pathogenetic mechanism in atherothrombosis among these patients.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/art.43371
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43371-2026-01-18-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Metformin and incident osteoarthritis: Causal insights from a co-twin control study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joca.2025.12.014</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 21
Autoren: Karin Magnusson, Aleksandra Turkiewicz, Andrea Dell’Isola, Ali Kiadaliri, Martin Englund
Journal: Osteoarthritis and Cartilage
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.joca.2025.12.014
ISSN: 1063-4584
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.joca.2025.12.014-2026-01-18-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>