<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 01:01:14 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 01:01:14 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Trends in US Children’s Mortality, Chronic Conditions, Obesity, Functional Status, and Symptoms</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2025.9855</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 3563
Autoren: Christopher B. Forrest, Lauren J. Koenigsberg, Francis Eddy Harvey, Mitchell G. Maltenfort, Neal Halfon
Journal: JAMA
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-12
Abstract: ImportanceRecent scientific and policy statements suggest that child health may be worsening in the US.ObjectiveTo determine how US children’s health has been changing from 2007 to 2023 using multiple data collection methods and a comprehensive set of health indicators.Design, Setting, and ParticipantsRepeated, cross-sectional analyses using mortality statistics from the US and 18 comparator high-income nations from the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD18), 5 nationally representative surveys, and electronic health records from 10 pediatric health systems (PEDSnet). The populations included individuals younger than 20 years old. Unweighted denominator sample size ranges were 1623 to 95 677 across the surveys, 1 026 926 to 2 114 638 for PEDSnet, 81.9 million to 83.2 million in the US, and 118.4 million to 121.1 million in the OECD18 for mortality statistics.ExposureCalendar time.Main Outcomes and MeasuresRate ratios (RRs) and annual incidence for mortality and prevalence for chronic physical, developmental, and mental health conditions, functional status, and symptoms.ResultsFrom 2007 to 2022, infants (&amp;amp;amp;lt;1 year old) were 1.78 (95% CI, 1.78-1.79) and 1- to 19-year-old individuals were 1.80 (95% CI, 1.80-1.80) times more likely to die in the US than in the OECD18. The 2 causes of death with the largest net difference between the US and OECD18 were prematurity (RR, 2.22 [95% CI, 2.20-2.24]) and sudden unexpected infant death (RR, 2.39 [95% CI, 2.35-2.43]) for infants 12 months or younger, and firearm-related incidents (RR, 15.34 [95% CI, 14.89-15.80]) and motor vehicle crashes (RR, 2.45 [95% CI, 2.42-2.48]) for 1- to 19-year-old individuals. From 2011 to 2023, the prevalence of 3- to 17-year-old individuals with a chronic condition rose from 39.9% to 45.7% (RR, 1.15 [95% CI, 1.14-1.15]) within PEDSnet, and from 25.8% to 31.0% (RR, 1.20 [95% CI, 1.20-1.20]) within the general population. Rates of obesity, early onset of menstruation, trouble sleeping, limitations in activity, physical symptoms, depressive symptoms, and loneliness all increased during the study period.Conclusions and RelevanceThe health of US children has worsened across a wide range of health indicator domains over the past 17 years. The broad scope of this deterioration highlights the need to identify and address the root causes of this fundamental decline in the nation’s health.
DOI: 10.1001/jama.2025.9855
ISSN: 0098-7484
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jama.2025.9855-2025-09-09-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices at a Crossroads</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2025.10776</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2599
Autoren: Edwin J. Asturias, Noel T. Brewer, Oliver Brooks, Lin H. Chen, Helen Y. Chu, Sybil Cineas, Jamie Loehr, Denise J. Jamieson, Mini Kamboj, George A. Kuchel, Karyn Lyons, Yvonne A. Maldonado, Charlotte A. Moser, Robert Schechter, Albert C. Shaw, Keipp Talbot, Jane R. Zucker
Journal: JAMA
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-26
Abstract: In this Viewpoint, former members of the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) caution that the sudden change in the ACIP may reverse the achievements of US immunization policy, including impeding access to lifesaving vaccines and putting US families at risk of dangerous and preventable illnesses.
DOI: 10.1001/jama.2025.10776
ISSN: 0098-7484
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jama.2025.10776-2025-09-09-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mitochondrial Donation and Preimplantation Genetic Testing for mtDNA Disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2415539</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2442
Autoren: Louise A. Hyslop, Emma L. Blakely, Magomet Aushev, Jordan Marley, Yuko Takeda, Angela Pyle, Eilis Moody, Catherine Feeney, Jan Dutton, Carol Shaw, Sarah J. Smith, Kate Craig, Charlotte L. Alston, Lisa Lister, Karina Endacott, Samantha Byerley, Helen McDermott, Kathryn Wilson, Lynne Botham, Beth Matthew, Nilendran Prathalingam, Matthew Prior, Alison Murdoch, Douglass M. Turnbull, Gavin Hudson, Meenakshi Choudhary, Robert W. Taylor, Rekha N. Pillai, Jane A. Stewart, Robert McFarland, Mary Herbert
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-31
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2415539
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2415539-2025-09-09-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why scientists are rethinking the immune effects of SARS-CoV-2</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.r1733</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2441
Autoren: Nick Tsergas
Journal: BMJ
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-19
DOI: 10.1136/bmj.r1733
ISSN: 1756-1833
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bmj.r1733-2025-09-09-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and Safety of Baxdrostat in Uncontrolled and Resistant Hypertension</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2507109</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2344
Autoren: John M. Flack, Michel Azizi, Jenifer M. Brown, Jamie P. Dwyer, Jakub Fronczek, Erika S.W. Jones, Daniel S. Olsson, Shira Perl, Hirotaka Shibata, Ji-Guang Wang, Ulrica Wilderäng, Janet Wittes, Bryan Williams
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-30
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2507109
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2507109-2025-09-09-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>