<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 00:58:40 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 00:58:40 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Cyclodextrin-mediated Enhancement of Haloperidol Solubility: Physicochemical Studies and In Vivo Investigation Using Planaria Worms</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11095-025-03909-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 143
Autoren: Yuehuai Xiong, Kenneth Shankland, Vitaliy V. Khutoryanskiy
Journal: Pharmaceutical Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Purpose
            This study aims to evaluate the ability of various cyclodextrins (CDs) to enhance the aqueous solubility of haloperidol (HAL), through the formation of inclusion complexes. It also investigates the pharmacological activity of CD/HAL complexes using a planaria model.
          
          
            Methods
            Inclusion complexes were prepared using α-CD, β-CD, methyl-β-CD, hydroxypropyl-β-CD and γ-CD. The solubility of HAL in the presence of CDs was assessed, and the stoichiometry of the complexes was determined using Job’s method. Physicochemical interactions between HAL and CDs were characterized by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), differential scanning calorimetry (DSC), and powder X-ray diffraction (PXRD). The in vivo pharmacological activity was tested in planaria worms following exposure to HAL in the presence or absence of CDs.
          
          
            Results
            HAL’s aqueous solubility was significantly enhanced in the presence of α-CD, methyl-β-CD, and hydroxypropyl-β-CD, while γ-CD showed no effect. Only modest solubility improvements were observed with increasing β-CD concentrations up to 8 mg/mL. Stoichiometric analysis confirmed a 1:1 ratio of HAL to CD in the inclusion complexes. In vivo studies demonstrated that HAL reduced planaria mobility, mimicking cataleptic effects seen in mammals, whereas the presence of CDs reduced this pharmacological effect.
          
          
            Conclusion
            Cyclodextrins, particularly α-CD, methyl-β-CD, and hydroxypropyl-β-CD, effectively enhance the solubility of haloperidol by forming 1:1 inclusion complexes. The reduction in haloperidol-induced behavioral changes in planaria by CDs suggests a potential impact on drug bioavailability and supports the use of planaria as a simple in vivo model for screening neuroactive compounds and formulations.
          
DOI: 10.1007/s11095-025-03909-0
ISSN: 0724-8741
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s11095-025-03909-0-2025-09-20-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>PEPITEM and its tripeptide pharmacophores: Mechanisms of bone regulation and therapeutic potential in health and disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118489</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 117
Autoren: Kathryn Frost, Alyssa Urbanowski, Georgiana Neag, Jonathan W. Lewis, Ellie Northall, Samuel Kemble, Emily Powell, Adam P. Croft, Asif J. Iqbal, G. Ed Rainger, James R. Edwards, Amy J. Naylor, Helen M. McGettrick
Journal: Biomedicine &amp;amp; Pharmacotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118489
ISSN: 0753-3322
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118489-2025-09-20-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Investigating the safety and tolerability of single-dose psilocybin for post-traumatic stress disorder: A nonrandomized open-label clinical trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/02698811251362390</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 79
Autoren: Niall M. McGowan, James J. Rucker, Rachel Yehuda, Manish Agrawal, Nadav Liam Modlin, Hollie Simmons, Agata Tofil-Kaluza, Shriya Das, Guy M. Goodwin
Journal: Journal of Psychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-29
Abstract: 
            Background:
            Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is a debilitating condition for which there are few efficacious treatments. Psilocybin is being studied for use in treatment-resistant depression but has not yet been investigated in PTSD.
          
          
            Aims:
            The trial’s primary outcome was to investigate the safety and tolerability of single-dose psilocybin in participants with PTSD.
          
          
            Methods:
            This was a Phase 2, nonrandomized, open-label, multicenter trial. Secondary outcomes were changes in PTSD symptoms (Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale for DSM-5 (CAPS-5); PTSD Checklist for DSM-5 (PCL-5)), functional impairment (Sheehan Disability Scale; SDS) and quality of life (EQ-5D-5L index score).
          
          
            Results:
            
              Amongst the 22 participants enrolled (63.6% female; mean (SD) age, 39.0 (7.91) years), there was a total of 117 treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs); 70 (59.8%) were reported on administration day, of which 64/70 (91.4%) resolved by the end of the next day. TEAEs commonly included headache (
              n
               = 11; 50.0%), nausea (
              n
               = 8; 36.4%), crying (
              n
               = 6; 27.3%) and fatigue (
              n
               = 6; 27.3%). There were no serious TEAEs or TEAEs leading to study withdrawal. Pre-post comparisons indicated a clinically meaningful change from Baseline in mean CAPS-5 total score at Week 4 (−29.9 (14.06)) and Week 12 (−29.5 (15.43)), which was associated with the intensity of psychedelic experience on Day 1. PCL-5 scores showed symptom reduction was rapid and sustained until Week 12. SDS total score and EQ-5D-5L index score showed similar improvements.
            
          
          
            Conclusions:
            Psilocybin at a dose of 25 mg, administered with psychological support, may be safe, well-tolerated and associated with symptomatic improvement in adults with PTSD. Further investigation is warranted.
          
          
            Clinical trial registration:
            ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT05312151
            (https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT05312151)
          
DOI: 10.1177/02698811251362390
ISSN: 0269-8811
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/02698811251362390-2025-09-20-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Exploiting PP2A dependent and independent effects of forskolin for therapeutic targeting of KMT2A (MLL)‐rearranged acute leukaemia</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/bph.70158</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 78
Autoren: Yoana Arroyo‐Berdugo, Antonella Di Mambro, Volker Behrends, Michelle A. Sahai, Luca Cozzuto, Immacolata Zollo, Julia Ponomarenko, Owen Williams, John Gribben, Yolanda Calle, Bela Patel, Maria Teresa Esposito
Journal: British Journal of Pharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-20
Abstract: Background and PurposeActivation of Protein Phosphatase 2A (PP2A), via genetic and pharmacologic modulation of SET, has recently being identified as a promising strategy to therapeutically target acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) carrying KMT2A (MLL) chromosomal translocations (KMT2A‐r AML).Experimental ApproachIn this study, we investigated the expression of PP2A subunits and the therapeutic potential of forskolin, a cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) elevating natural compound that has been reported as a PP2A activator.Key ResultsOur data show that PPP2CA encoding protein phosphatase 2 catalytic subunit α is abundantly expressed in KMT2A‐r AML cells. Treatment with forskolin arrests proliferation; induces cell death; represses the expression of MYC, HOXA9 and HOXA10; stimulates PP2A activity; and attenuates the activity of ERK1/2 in KMT2A‐r AML cells. Forskolin increases sensitivity to standard‐of‐care daunorubicin in KMT2A‐AML cell lines and PDX. Silencing PPP2CA partially rescues the cytotoxic effect of forskolin, stimulates ERK1/2, inhibits GSK3β, and abolishes the forskolin‐mediated repression of c‐MYC and HOXA10, but it did not affect the potentiation of response to daunorubicin. This effect was also not dependent on increase of cAMP, but it was because of increase in the intracellular accumulation of daunorubicin, through inhibition of drug efflux pump P‐glycoprotein 1 (multidrug resistance protein).Conclusions and ImplicationsIn conclusion, our findings highlight a novel mechanism of action for forskolin and support a potential role of this natural compound in combination with current conventional agent daunorubicin in the treatment of KMT2A‐r AML.
DOI: 10.1111/bph.70158
ISSN: 0007-1188
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/bph.70158-2025-09-20-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A New Ashwagandha Formulation (Zenroot™) Alleviates Stress and Anxiety Symptoms While Improving Mood and Sleep Quality: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12325-025-03327-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 65
Autoren: Manasvi Mahadevan, Kumarpillai Gopukumar, Ruchi Gupta, Abhijeet Morde, Paras Patni, Sahitya Sarvamangala Srinivas, Arun Bhuvanendran, Abhijith Phanindra
Journal: Advances in Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-28
DOI: 10.1007/s12325-025-03327-z
ISSN: 0741-238X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s12325-025-03327-z-2025-09-20-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>