<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 01:01:12 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 01:01:12 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Knee crepitus and osteoarthritis features in young adults following traumatic knee injury</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25637</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 168
Autoren: Jamon L Couch, Brooke E Patterson, Kay M Crossley, Ali Guermazi, Matthew G King, Danilo De Oliveira Silva, Jackie L Whittaker, Michael A Girdwood, Adam G Culvenor
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-25
Abstract: ObjectiveThis study explored the association between knee crepitus and the presence, and worsening, of structural osteoarthritis features and self‐reported outcomes in young adults following traumatic knee injury.MethodsOne‐year following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction (ACLR), 112 participants (41 female participants; median age 28 years) self‐reported the presence/absence of knee crepitus using an item from the Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS). Patellofemoral and tibiofemoral osteoarthritis features (i.e. cartilage lesions, osteophytes, bone marrow lesions) were assessed from MRIs at 1‐ and 5‐years post‐ACLR. Self‐reported outcomes were assessed with two KOOS subscales (pain, quality of life [QoL]) and the International Knee Documentation Committee subjective evaluation form (i.e. self‐reported function). Poisson regression evaluated the relationship between self‐reported crepitus and the presence/worsening of structural osteoarthritis features. General linear models explored the relationship between crepitus and self‐reported outcomes.ResultsSelf‐reported crepitus was associated with full‐thickness patellofemoral cartilage lesions 1‐year post‐ACLR (prevalence ratio 2.70, 95%CI 1.41, 6.39) but not the risk of worsening structural osteoarthritis features between 1‐ and 5‐years post‐ACLR. Those with crepitus reported worse pain (β ‐6.42, 95%CI ‐10.47, ‐2.36), QoL (β ‐10.39, 95%CI ‐18.58, ‐2.20) and function (β ‐5.49, 95%CI ‐10.92, ‐0.06) 1‐year post‐ACLR, but greater improvement in pain and function between 1‐ and 5‐years.ConclusionSelf‐reported knee crepitus was associated with the presence of full‐thickness patellofemoral cartilage defects 1‐year post‐ACLR, but was not associated with a greater risk of worsening structural osteoarthritis features up to 5‐years post‐ACLR. One‐year post‐ACLR, those with crepitus reported worse pain, knee‐related QoL, and function.
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25637
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25637-2025-09-24-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The impact of population ageing on musculoskeletal disorders in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2021: global burden and healthcare costs</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.002</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 119
Autoren: Shi-Yang Guan, Jin-Xin Zheng, Xin-Yu Feng, Shun-Xian Zhang, Shu-Zhen Xu, Peng Wang, Hong-Yan Cai, Hai-Feng Pan
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.002
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.002-2025-09-24-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Risk factors for the development of knee osteoarthritis across the lifespan: A systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joca.2025.03.003</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 30
Autoren: Vicky Duong, Christina Abdel Shaheed, Manuela L. Ferreira, Sujita W. Narayan, Venkatesha Venkatesha, David J. Hunter, Jimmy Zhu, Inoshi Atukorala, Sarah Kobayashi, Siew Li Goh, Andrew M. Briggs, Marita Cross, Rolando Espinosa-Morales, Kai Fu, Francis Guillemin, Francis Keefe, L. Stefan Lohmander, Lyn March, George J. Milne, Yifang Mei, Ali Mobasheri, Mosedi Namane, George Peat, May Arna Risberg, Saurab Sharma, Regina Sit, Rosa Weiss Telles, Yuqing Zhang, Cyrus Cooper
Journal: Osteoarthritis and Cartilage
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.joca.2025.03.003
ISSN: 1063-4584
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.joca.2025.03.003-2025-09-24-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of Nonsteroidal Anti‐Inflammatory Drugs on Sacroiliac Joint Inflammation, as Seen on Magnetic Resonance Imaging, in Axial Spondyloarthritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25581</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 27
Autoren: Gareth T. Jones, Alexander N. Bennett, Raj Sengupta, Pedro M. Machado, Helena Marzo‐Ortega, Lorna Aucott, Margaret A. Hall‐Craggs, Timothy J. P. Bray, Alan Bainbridge, Ruaridh M. Gollifer, Gary J. Macfarlane
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-10
Abstract: ObjectiveImaging evidence of active sacroiliitis is important for diagnosis, classification, and monitoring of axial spondyloarthritis (axSpA). However, there is no consistent guidance on whether patients should temporarily stop nonsteroidal anti‐inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) before magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). The aim of this study was to determine whether NSAIDs lead to an underestimation of active sacroiliitis, as observed using MRI.MethodsAdults with axSpA were recruited from rheumatology clinics and undertook NSAID washout for one to two weeks before a sacroiliac joint MRI scan. Images were read by two independent readers and adjudicated by a third if required. Those who had a positive result for active sacroiliitis, as per internationally recognized criteria, underwent a second scan six weeks after recommencing daily NSAIDs. We determined the proportion of participants who had a negative scanning result while taking NSAIDs after a previous positive result when NSAID‐free. Images were also scored using semiquantitative methods comprising lesion size and intensity, and a subset of participants underwent quantitative MRI (qMRI) to provide an objective evaluation of any inflammatory changes.ResultsFrom 34 centers across the United Kingdom, 311 participants (median age 42 years; 62% male) were recruited; 286 (92%) completed the NSAID washout and underwent the first MRI scan. From 146 participants with active sacroiliitis, follow‐up scans (while taking NSAIDs) were obtained from 124 (85%), at which point 25 participants had a negative result (20.2%; 95% confidence interval 13.5%–28.3%). Semiquantitative and qMRI methods supported these findings.ConclusionOne‐fifth of patients showed full resolution of active sacroiliitis lesions when NSAIDs were present. In clinical practice, if patients with axSpA are willing to attempt a one‐ to two‐week NSAID washout before MRI, this should be considered.
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25581
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25581-2025-09-24-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>ERS/EULAR clinical practice guidelines for connective tissue disease-associated interstitial lung disease developed by the task force for connective tissue disease-associated interstitial lung disease of the European Respiratory Society (ERS) and the European Alliance of Associations for Rheumatology (EULAR) Endorsed by the European Reference Network on rare respiratory diseases (ERN-LUNG)</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.021</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 27
Autoren: Katerina M. Antoniou, Oliver Distler, Ana-Maria Gheorghiu, Catharina C. Moor, Jens Vikse, Nikoleta Bizymi, Ilaria Galetti, Graham Brown, Elena Bargagli, Yannick Allanore, Tamera J. Corte, Philippe Dieudé, Vincent Cottin, Benjamin A. Fisher, Aurelie Fabre, Jon T. Giles, Michael Kreuter, Ingrid E. Lundberg, Venerino Poletti, Britta Maurer, Elisabetta A. Renzoni, Ulf Müller-Ladner, Mary E. Strek, Nicola Sverzellati, Paul Studenic, Jibril Mohammed, Blin Nagavci, Tanja Stamm, Thomy Tonia, Bruno Crestani, Anna-Maria Hoffmann-Vold
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.021
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.021-2025-09-24-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>