<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 01:12:27 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 01:12:27 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>A Flexible Multi-Sensor Device Enabling Handheld Sensing of Heart Sounds by Untrained Users</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1109/jbhi.2025.3551882</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 311
Autoren: Andrew McDonald, Maximilian Nussbaumer, Nirmani Rathnayake, Richard Steeds, Anurag Agarwal
Journal: IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1109/jbhi.2025.3551882
ISSN: 2168-2194
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1109/jbhi.2025.3551882-2025-08-18-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Evaluating gender bias in large language models in long-term care</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 96
Autoren: Sam Rickman
Journal: BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-11
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Large language models (LLMs) are being used to reduce the administrative burden in long-term care by automatically generating and summarising case notes. However, LLMs can reproduce bias in their training data. This study evaluates gender bias in summaries of long-term care records generated with two state-of-the-art, open-source LLMs released in 2024: Meta’s Llama 3 and Google Gemma.
          
          
            Methods
            Gender-swapped versions were created of long-term care records for 617 older people from a London local authority. Summaries of male and female versions were generated with Llama 3 and Gemma, as well as benchmark models from Meta and Google released in 2019: T5 and BART. Counterfactual bias was quantified through sentiment analysis alongside an evaluation of word frequency and thematic patterns.
          
          
            Results
            The benchmark models exhibited some variation in output on the basis of gender. Llama 3 showed no gender-based differences across any metrics. Gemma displayed the most significant gender-based differences. Male summaries focus more on physical and mental health issues. Language used for men was more direct, with women’s needs downplayed more often than men’s.
          
          
            Conclusion
            Care services are allocated on the basis of need. If women’s health issues are underemphasised, this may lead to gender-based disparities in service receipt. LLMs may offer substantial benefits in easing administrative burden. However, the findings highlight the variation in state-of-the-art LLMs, and the need for evaluation of bias. The methods in this paper provide a practical framework for quantitative evaluation of gender bias in LLMs. The code is available on GitHub.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0
ISSN: 1472-6947
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0-2025-08-18-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Pitfalls of large language models in medical ethics reasoning</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01792-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 96
Autoren: Shelly Soffer, Vera Sorin, Girish N. Nadkarni, Eyal Klang
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01792-y
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01792-y-2025-08-18-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Personalized home based neurostimulation via AI optimization augments sustained attention</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01744-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 80
Autoren: Roi Cohen Kadosh, Delia Ciobotaru, Malin I. Karstens, Vu Nguyen
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-29
Abstract: Abstract
          Brain-based technologies for human augmentation face challenges in personalization and real-world translation. We present an AI-driven personalized Bayesian optimization algorithm that remotely adjusts neurostimulation parameters based on baseline ability and head anatomy to enhance sustained attention at home. Validated through in silico modeling and a double-blind, sham-controlled study, our approach aligns with MRI-based models and neurobiological theories, maximizing efficacy and enabling scalable, personalized cognitive enhancement and therapy in real-world settings.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01744-6
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01744-6-2025-08-18-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Evaluation of the NHS active 10 walking app intervention through time-series analysis in 201,688 individuals</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01785-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 62
Autoren: Dharani Yerrakalva, Samantha Hajna, Soren Brage, Simon J. Griffin
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-06
Abstract: Abstract
          Despite widespread interest in integrating mobile health apps into primary care to prevent and manage physical inactivity-related health conditions, the effectiveness of these apps remains unclear. We quantified the effects of Active 10 (a goal setting and self-monitoring app developed by Public Health England) on brisk and non-brisk walking using a single-group interrupted time-series analysis of individual-level data collected between July 2021 and January 2024. Among Active 10 users (n = 201,668 l; 51.4 ± 14.4 years; 75.4% women) brisk and non-brisk walking increased by 9.0 (95% confidence interval (CI) 8.9, 9.1; 73% above baseline) and 2.6 min/day (95% CI 2.4, 2.8; 9% above baseline), respectively, on the day of app download. Post-download, brisk and non-brisk walking decreased by 0.15 (95% CI −0.17, −0.13) and 0.06 (95% CI −0.08, −0.03) min/day/month, respectively, but remained above baseline. Our findings suggest that Active 10 may be effective in facilitating increases in brisk and non-brisk walking.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01785-x
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01785-x-2025-08-18-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>