<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 01:00:46 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 01:00:46 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Pig-to-human lung xenotransplantation into a brain-dead recipient</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03861-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 1510
Autoren: Jianxing He, Jiang Shi, Chao Yang, Guilin Peng, Chunrong Ju, Yi Zhao, Hui Liu, Ping He, Xiaoqing Liu, Zuopeng Zhang, Chuanbao Chen, Dengke Pan, Zifeng Yang, Wenda Guang, Hongtao Li, Zhonghua Chen, Menyang Liu, Hengrui Liang, Weiqing Huang, Kyeongman Jeon, Toyofumi F. Chen-Yoshikawa, A. Justin Rucker, Amos Lal, Nanshan Zhong, Kang Zhang, Xiaoyou Liu, Xin Xu
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-25
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03861-x
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03861-x-2025-09-24-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Interplay of genetic predisposition, plasma metabolome and Mediterranean diet in dementia risk and cognitive function</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03891-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 1005
Autoren: Yuxi Liu, Xiao Gu, Yanping Li, Fenglei Wang, Chirag M. Vyas, Cheng Peng, Danyue Dong, Yuhan Li, Yu Zhang, Yin Zhang, Oana A. Zeleznik, Jae H. Kang, Molin Wang, Frank B. Hu, Walter C. Willett, Olivia I. Okereke, A. Heather Eliassen, Peter Kraft, Meir J. Stampfer, Dong D. Wang
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-25
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03891-5
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03891-5-2025-09-24-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Dietary saturated fatty acids promote lung myeloid cell inflammasome activation and IL-1β–mediated inflammation in mice and humans</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 447
Autoren: Sam J. McCright, Olivia Harding, Julia Chini, Nicole DeMarco, Li-Yin Hung, Christopher F. Pastore, Wenyun Lu, Joshua Rabinowitz, Jorge Henao-Mejia, De’Broski R. Herbert, Lisa R. Young, David A. Hill
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-27
Abstract: Resident tissue macrophages and monocytes (RTMs) integrate local and systemic signals to coordinate immune cell function at homeostasis and in response to inflammatory stimuli. Obesity-associated metabolic dysfunction drives the development of RTM populations that contribute to disease states in multiple tissues. However, the contribution of specific dietary components to innate immune cell activation and function, as opposed to the direct effects of obesity, is largely unknown. Here, we studied the mechanisms by which high-fat (HF) diets shape lung RTM phenotype and function at steady state and influence responses to inflammatory insults. We found that, during HF diet feeding, lung RTMs accumulate saturated long-chain fatty acids, specifically stearic acid (SA), and demonstrate features of NLRP3 inflammasome priming and activation. In vivo, increased dietary SA was sufficient to cause neutrophil-predominant lung inflammation in the steady state and exacerbate a model of innate airway inflammation, whereas increased dietary oleic acid, the monounsaturated counterpart of SA, was sufficient to reduce inflammasome activation in the steady state and attenuate airway inflammation. Depletion of interleukin-1β (IL-1β) or pharmacologic inhibition of the endonuclease inositol requiring enzyme 1α (IRE1α) protected against SA-induced exacerbated lung inflammation. Last, we identified a population of lung monocytes with hallmarks of HF diet–induced RTM activation that were present in samples from obese humans with asthma. Together, these results identify a class of dietary lipids that regulate lung RTM phenotype and function in the steady state and modulate the severity of inflammation in the lung.
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653-2025-09-24-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Targeting dormant tumor cells to prevent recurrent breast cancer: a randomized phase 2 trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03877-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 370
Autoren: Angela DeMichele, Amy S. Clark, Emily Shea, Lauren J. Bayne, Christopher J. Sterner, Killian Rohn, Samantha Dwyer, Tien-chi Pan, Isoris Nivar, Yan Chen, Paul Wileyto, Lindsay R. Berry, Shannon Deluca, Jessica Savage, Igor Makhlin, Dhruv K. Pant, Heather Martin, Adetutu Egunsola, Nathan Mears, Brooke L. Goodspeed, Elizabeth M. Chislock, Jewell Graves, Jianping Wang, Natalie Shih, George K. Belka, Don Berry, Anupma Nayak, Michael Feldman, Lewis A. Chodosh
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-02
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03877-3
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03877-3-2025-09-24-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Macrovascular and microvascular outcomes of metabolic surgery versus GLP-1 receptor agonists in patients with diabetes and obesity</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03893-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 349
Autoren: Hamlet Gasoyan, Mohammad Hesam Alavi, Alexander Zajichek, Nicholas J. Casacchia, Abdullah Al Jabri, James Bena, Xiaoxi Feng, Rickesha Wilson, Ricard Corcelles, W. Scott Butsch, Rishi P. Singh, Nikhil Das, Hejin Jeong, Amgad Mentias, W. H. Wilson Tang, Bartolome Burguera, Raul J. Rosenthal, Steven E. Nissen, Michael B. Rothberg, Ali Aminian
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-16
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03893-3
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-24</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03893-3-2025-09-24-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>