<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 01:00:13 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 01:00:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>All the Colors of the Rainbow: Synthetic Dyes in US Packaged Foods and Beverages in 2020</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 942
Autoren: Elizabeth K. Dunford, Thomas M. Galligan, Lindsey Smith Taillie, Aviva A. Musicus
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007-2025-09-23-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Day/night fluctuations of breast milk bioactive factors and microbiome</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1618784</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 410
Autoren: Melissa A. Woortman, Haipeng Sun, Jincheng Wang, Filipa Godoy-Vitorino, Angeliz J. Rivera Meléndez, Maribel Campos Rivera, Edna E. Aquino Piñero, Krystin Engelhardt, Lawrence C. Kleinman, Maria G. Dominguez-Bello
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-05
Abstract: IntroductionHuman breast milk is a sophisticated and complex biological fluid that provides crucial nutritional, immunological, and microbial benefits to infants. Hormones exhibit circadian variations in maternal serum, and understanding these fluctuations in breast milk is crucial for assessing infant maturation. This is particularly relevant when expressed breast milk is fed at a different time from when it was originally produced.MethodsThis study examined 24-h variations in breast milk composition by analyzing samples from 38 lactating mothers at four distinct times of the day. Levels of cortisol, melatonin, immunoglobulin A (IgA), lactoferrin, and oxytocin were quantified using ELISA, and microbiome composition was assessed through 16S rRNA sequencing.ResultsSignificant 24-h fluctuations in melatonin and cortisol concentrations were noted, whereas lactoferrin and IgA levels only varied when separating by infant age, maternal BMI, or infant sex. Breast milk microbial composition shifted, with a nocturnal increase in skin-associated bacteria and a diurnal increase in environmental bacteria depending on maternal BMI and infant age. Additionally, milk microbiota alpha diversity increased due to age, but not consistently over all the time points.DiscussionThese differences in 24-h breast milk composition underscore the physiological relevance of maintaining the natural temporal dynamics of breast milk, which may be disrupted when expressed breast milk is fed asynchronously from its time of expression.
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1618784
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1618784-2025-09-23-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Blueberry Consumption in Early Life and Its Effects on Allergy, Immune Biomarkers, and Their Association with the Gut Microbiome</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17172795</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 390
Autoren: Carina Venter, Stina Boden, Kaci Pickett-Nairne, Liam O’Mahony, Gabrielle N. E. Glime, Kinzie L. Matzeller, Daniel N. Frank, Cassandra Kotter, Jennifer M. Kofonow, Charles E. Robertson, Wayne W. Campbell, Nancy F. Krebs, Minghua Tang
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-28
Abstract: Background/Objectives: The complementary feeding period is a critical window for shaping infant diet, gut microbiota, and immune development. While allergic symptoms often emerge in the first year of life, the effects of specific foods, such fruits, on infant allergy symptoms, inflammation, immunity and associated microbiota remain unclear. This study aimed to assess the impact of daily blueberry consumption during the complementary feeding period on allergy-related symptoms, immune biomarkers, and gut microbiota in breastfed U.S. infants. Methods: In a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trial, infants from the Denver metro area were assigned to receive up to 10 g/day of freeze-dried blueberry powder or an isocaloric placebo from 5 to 12 months of age. Stool, blood, and caregiver-reported allergy-related symptom data were collected at baseline and study end. Results: Of the 76 infants enrolled, 61 completed the study (Blueberry: n = 30; Placebo: n = 31). While more infants in the blueberry group had allergy-related symptoms at baseline, they had significantly different longitudinal symptom trajectories than the placebo (p = 0.05), showing a greater resolution rate of symptoms by study end. Pro-inflammatory serum IL-13 levels were significantly reduced (p = 0.035) and anti-inflammatory IL-10 levels borderline increased (p = 0.052) in the blueberry group. However, changes in allergy symptoms were not significantly associated with IL-10 or IL-13. The relative abundances of Lacticaseibacillus, Blautia, and Peptostreptococcaceae at 12 months were negatively correlated with IL-10, while Lactobacillus, Clostridiaceae, and Megasphaera were positively associated. IL-13 was positively associated with Citrobacter and negatively associated with Anaerostipes and Blautia. Conclusions: The consumptio9n of blueberries as an early complementary food may improve resolution of allergy symptoms, modulate immune biomarkers, and promote beneficial shifts in gut microbiota during infancy. Future research should aim to identify the specific bioactive components of blueberries responsible for these effects and explore the potential of other complementary foods to favorably influence developing biological systems involved in microbiota and immune development.
DOI: 10.3390/nu17172795
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu17172795-2025-09-23-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Exploring the role of diet quality and adiposity in the pain experience: a mediation analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00394-025-03772-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 229
Autoren: Susan J. Ward, Alison M. Coates, Sharayah Carter, Katherine L. Baldock, Ty E. Stanford, Carolyn Berryman, Tasha R. Stanton, Jonathan D. Buckley, Alison M. Hill
Journal: European Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-23
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Purpose
            Improving diet quality may lower chronic musculoskeletal pain (CMP) directly or through weight loss. This study examined whether a dietary intervention for weight-loss improved diet quality and CMP in adults with elevated adiposity. It also investigated whether adiposity mediated a relationship between diet quality and pain.
          
          
            Methods
            This secondary analysis of data from another study included 104 Australian adults (25–65 years) with overweight/obesity (BMI, 27.5–34.9 kg/m2) who completed a 3-month dietary intervention targeting 30% energy restriction. Baseline and 3-month measures included diet quality (Dietary Guideline Index (DGI)), presence of CMP, pain related quality-of-life (Short-Form-36 bodily pain scale (SF36-BPS)), pain severity (McGill Pain Questionnaire (MPQ)) and adiposity (weight, waist circumference (WC), percent body fat (BF)). Linear mixed models estimated the effect of the dietary intervention on these outcomes. Structural equation modelling estimated the direct effects of changes in diet quality on CMP, and proportion mediated by changes in adiposity.
          
          
            Results
            Participants improved diet quality (DGI total score) by 22% (p &amp;lt; 0.001) and achieved weight loss (− 7.1 ± 0.3 kg, 95% CI − 7.7, − 6.4). Presence of CMP reduced from 50 to 24% (p &amp;lt; 0.001). Pain-related quality of life improved, and pain severity lessened. Reductions in weight, WC, or BF did not mediate improvements in pain characteristics. Improved diet quality (∆DGI) was directly associated with lower pain severity (∆MPQ), accounting for reductions in the mediator, WC (β = − 0.085, 95% CI − 0.151, − 0.019) and BF (β = − 0.073, 95% CI − 0.135, − 0.012).
          
          
            Conclusion
            On average, diet quality improved and pain lessened following a 3-month dietary intervention for weight-loss. Changes in adiposity did not mediate this relationship.
          
DOI: 10.1007/s00394-025-03772-0
ISSN: 1436-6207
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00394-025-03772-0-2025-09-23-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cluttered with claims: Composition, nutrition, health and marketing claims on commercial infant and toddler foods in New Zealand</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/1747-0080.70042</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 171
Autoren: Sally Mackay, Berit Follong, Baylee Wilde, Maria Ferreria, Maree Scully
Journal: Nutrition &amp;amp; Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-26
Abstract: AbstractAimThe World Health Organization Regional Office for Europe's Nutrient and Promotion Profile Model recommends that commercial infant and toddler foods do not carry compositional, nutrition, health, or marketing claims. Our objective was to identify on‐pack claims displayed on commercial foods for infants and toddlers in New Zealand.MethodThe packaging of products intended for infants (aged up to 11 months) and toddlers (ages 12 months to &amp;lt;36 months) was analyzed for the presence of claims using a coding structure based on categories outlined by the World Health Organization Europe Nutrient and Promotion Profile Model. Descriptive statistics were conducted to analyze the frequency of types of claims. Relevant infant and toddler products available in New Zealand supermarkets were identified through a packaged food database of products collected in 2023.ResultsTwo hundred and ten products were identified: 167 infant and 43 toddler products. On average, there were 7.5 unique claims per product (range 3–15), with composition and nutrition claims being the most common (mean 4.0 per product), followed by marketing (3.3) and health claims (0.2). Composition and nutrition claims relating to the absence of ingredients generally perceived to be harmful (i.e. ‘free from’ claims) were prevalent on 97% of products and most commonly referred to flavors (on 72% of products) and colors (71%).ConclusionsAll New Zealand infant and toddler products carried multiple claims. Regulation is needed to align with international best practice and prevent caregivers from being potentially misled by these promotional messages when making purchasing decisions for young children.
DOI: 10.1111/1747-0080.70042
ISSN: 1446-6368
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/1747-0080.70042-2025-09-23-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>