<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 01:17:57 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 01:17:57 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Natural Speech Analysis Can Reveal Individual Differences in Executive Function Across the Adult Lifespan</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00268</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 137
Autoren: Hsi T. Wei, Dana Kulzhabayeva, Lella Erceg, Mira Kates Rose, Kiah A. Spencer, Jessica Robin, Ellen Bialystok, Jed A. Meltzer
Journal: Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-10
Abstract: 
                    Purpose:
                    Automated analysis of naturalistic speech has emerged as an effective tool for detecting cognitive decline in dementia but has seldom been used to examine the ordinary cognitive decline occurring in normal aging. Executive function (EF) declines throughout the adult lifespan but is difficult to track longitudinally due to practice effects, making speech-based assessments particularly attractive. This study examined relationships between EF and speech characteristics.
                  
                  
                    Method:
                    We collected two audio picture descriptions from participants in two experiments that also included EF assessments, with 67 healthy older adults (aged 65–75 years) in Study 1 and 174 healthy adults (aged 18–90 years) in Study 2. Language composite scores were computed by aggregating relevant speech features indexing aspects of speech that have been reported to show changes in pathological aging. Principal components reflecting common covariation in speech features were extracted from a large training data set to compute speech domain scores. The relationships between language composites/speech principal components and EF were assessed while controlling for age, gender, and education.
                  
                  
                    Results:
                    In Study 1, older adults' word-finding difficulties, measured as speech disfluencies, showed significant associations with EF. Study 2 confirms that speech disfluencies can explain individual differences in EF not only for adults above the age of 65 years but also across the adult lifespan. Information units and coherence in speech showed weaker associations with EF and Montreal Cognitive Assessment scores that were not significant after correction for multiple comparisons.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion:
                    The findings revealed associations between word-finding ability in natural speech and general EF across the adult lifespan, supporting natural speech analysis as a convenient and sensitive assessment of general cognitive ability.
                  
DOI: 10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00268
ISSN: 1092-4388
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00268-2026-01-11-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Developmental Language Disorder as a Multidimensional Neurodevelopmental Spectrum: Implications for Diagnosis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00089</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 25
Autoren: Karla K. McGregor, Lisa Goffman, Elena Plante, Krystal Werfel
Journal: Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-10
Abstract: 
                    Purpose:
                    We aimed to create a comprehensive understanding of the dilemmas involved in the diagnosis of developmental language disorder (DLD) and to highlight the potential of a multidimensional spectral account of DLD for addressing these dilemmas.
                  
                  
                    Method:
                    We conducted an integrative literature review.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions:
                    Considerable gains in understanding the genetics and neurobiology of DLD provide new explanations for long-observed phenomena such as heterogeneity of presentation, phenotypic overlap with other neurodevelopmental conditions, and the challenges of diagnosis. Although categorical nosologies benefit diagnostic decision making, facilitate communication, and align well with bureaucratic systems, they offer overly simple ways of defining DLD. The presentation of DLD is broad rather than narrow, spectral rather than categorical, and dynamic rather than static; therefore, DLD is better described as a multidimensional spectral system than as a categorical entity. It is not practical or even advisable to abandon the traditional categorical framing of DLD at this point. However, maintaining awareness of the tension between the categorical framing and the spectral nature of DLD may improve diagnosis, prognosis, and alignment with the construct of neurodiversity.
                  
DOI: 10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00089
ISSN: 1092-4388
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00089-2026-01-11-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Patient Concerns Are Often Overlooked by Low Back Pain (LBP) Guidelines</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2026.9001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 24
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: Infographic illustrating the article “People With Acute Low Back Pain Have Concerns That May Not Be Addressed by Guideline-Recommended Advice: A Mixed-Methods Study”, which was published in the September 2024 issue of JOSPT.
                  J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2026;56(1):64. doi:10.2519/jospt.2026.9001
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2026.9001
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2026.9001-2026-01-11-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The pain education paradox and validation gap</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103476</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 21
Autoren: Asaf Weisman, Monica Noy, Youssef Masharawi
Journal: Musculoskeletal Science and Practice
Veröffentlicht: 2026-02-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103476
ISSN: 2468-7812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103476-2026-01-11-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>This is our rhythm: academic becoming and realignment in deaf space</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/jdsade/enaf061</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 20
Autoren: Maartje De Meulder, Joseph J Murray, Annelies Kusters
Journal: Journal of Deaf Studies and Deaf Education
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-08
Abstract: Abstract
                  Deaf scholars have long worked at the margins of academic institutions not designed for them. Designated deaf academic spaces—where deaf ways of knowing, teaching, and communicating are centered—remain rare. This study explores what becomes possible when such a space exists, presenting Dr Deaf as a case study. Drawing on interviews with participants and teachers, we show how deaf epistemologies and pedagogies are enacted through cross-stage responsibility and academic becoming through re-alignment of deaf participants and teachers. We also identify a distinct deaf rhythm that emerges in this space. At the same time, we recognize that these practices are not experienced or valued equally by all participants and teachers: needs, priorities, and ways of engaging differ, and Dr Deaf’s approaches may not resonate for all. Yet its values offer a flexible framework for imagining and sustaining other deaf academic and broader educational spaces.
DOI: 10.1093/jdsade/enaf061
ISSN: 1081-4159
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/jdsade/enaf061-2026-01-11-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>