<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 01:02:02 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 01:02:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Baseline individual factors associated with clinical outcomes in adults with non-specific low back pain following manual therapy: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Gaetan Barbier, Mathieu Picchiottino, Arnaud Delafontaine, Guillaume Goncalves, André Bussières, François Cottin, Arnaud Lardon
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y-2025-10-16-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Revealing the anticancer potential of nano-encapsulated graviola extract on tongue carcinoma (SCC154) cell line: targeting the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway (in vitro study)</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05113-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Amany Hany Mohamed Kamel, Ahmed A. Abd-Rabou, Ahmed Basuoni, Nermeen AbuBakr
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-02
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Graviola emerged as a promising anticancer agent, with nanotechnology enhancing drugs’ therapeutic potential. The purpose of this work was to explore graviola extract and its nano-platform’s effects on tongue carcinoma (SCC154 cells) in vitro model.
          
          
            Methods
            Graviola leaves extract (GLE) was isolated, and its phenolic content was identified. Three nano-formulations (F1-F3) were optimized for GLE delivery, with F1 chosen for its optimal size and stability to synthesize graviola nanoparticles (GNPs). SCC154 cells were split into three groups: group Ι (untreated SCC154 cells), group ΙΙ: SCC154 cells + ethanolic GLE, and group ΙΙΙ: SCC154 cells + GLE encapsulated in a nano-void delivery system (GNPs). In vitro tests assessed cell viability via MTT assay, cell cycle, and apoptosis by flow cytometry, DNA damage using comet assay, and gene expression of the key molecular markers (PI3K, AKT, mTOR, and GSK-3β) by quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction. Transmission electron microscopic examination of cells was also performed.
          
          
            Results
            GLE and GNPs reduced SCC154 cells’ proliferation compared to untreated cells, with GNPs showing significantly higher cytotoxicity. Both treatments also induced apoptosis, arrested the cell cycle, and caused DNA damage with a significant pronounced effect in the GNPs-treated group. Gene expression analysis revealed a substantial decline in PI3K, AKT, mTOR, and GSK-3β in both treated groups relative to the control group, with a significant downregulation in the GNPs-treated group. Ultrastructural examination revealed severe destruction in tongue carcinoma cells of both treated groups, with substantial damage in the GNPs-treated group.
          
          
            Conclusion
            GNPs showed a better impact than GLE in tongue carcinoma therapy, causing cytotoxicity and apoptosis, potentially through the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05113-4
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05113-4-2025-10-16-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Vapor phase of white thyme essential oil: effect on Candida albicans and preservation of Lactobacillus species in the context of vulvovaginal candidiasis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05067-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Liliana Fernandes, Inês Silva, Daniela Araújo, Raquel Costa, Sónia Silva, Nuno Pereira Mira, Sofia Costa-de-Oliveira, Mariana Henriques, Maria Elisa Rodrigues
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-06
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05067-7
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05067-7-2025-10-16-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Probiotics mitigates ovarian angiogenic disturbance in letrozole-induced PCOS</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05109-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Stephanie E. Areloegbe, Ikenna A. Abugu, Isaac O. Ajadi, Ayodeji Aturamu, Mary B. Ajadi, Chukwubueze L. Atuma, Christopher O. Akintayo, Gloria O. Omoruyi, Samuel O. Onyekweli, Olabimpe C. Badejogbin, Oluwatobi A. Amusa, Oluseyi E. Adelekan, Kayode Ajayi, Paul A. Oyewole, Kehinde S. Olaniyi
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05109-0
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05109-0-2025-10-16-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>In vitro effect of Mikania cordata leaf extracts on wound healing</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05110-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Naomi Navaneeta Vijithsingh, Kaushalya Anuradha, Shiroma Mangalika Handunnetti, Narmada Fernando, Kanishka Senarath
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-09
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05110-7
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05110-7-2025-10-16-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>