<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:06:31 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:06:31 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Single Treatment With MM120 (Lysergide) in Generalized Anxiety Disorder</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2025.13481</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2906
Autoren: Reid Robison, Robert Barrow, Craig Conant, Eric Foster, Jamie M. Freedman, Paula L. Jacobsen, Jamileh Jemison, Sarah M. Karas, Daniel R. Karlin, Todd M. Solomon, Miri Halperin Wernli, Maurizio Fava
Journal: JAMA
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-21
Abstract: ImportanceEffective and well-tolerated pharmacotherapies for generalized anxiety disorder (GAD), which is one of the most common psychiatric disorders, are needed.ObjectiveTo determine the dose-response relationship of MM120 (lysergide D-tartrate) in adults with moderate to severe GAD.Design, Settings, and ParticipantsThis phase 2b, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study enrolled 198 adults aged 18 to 74 years with a primary GAD diagnosis who presented with moderate to severe symptoms (defined by a Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale [HAM-A] score ≥20) and was conducted at 22 outpatient psychiatric research sites in the US from August 2022 to August 2023. The anxiety and depression end point assessments were conducted by independent central raters who were blinded to the trial protocol, treatment allocation, and study visit date. The last date of follow-up was November 27, 2023.InterventionsParticipants were randomized to receive a single (freebase equivalent) treatment dose with 25 µg (n = 39), 50 µg (n = 40), 100 µg (n = 40), or 200 µg (n = 40) of MM120 or placebo (n = 39).Main Outcome and MeasuresThe primary outcome was a dose-response relationship assessed using the multiple comparison procedure modeling (MCP-Mod) method for change in HAM-A score at 4 weeks (score range, 0-56; higher scores indicate greater severity; ≤7 indicates no or minimal anxiety; 8-14, mild; 15-23, moderate; and ≥24, severe). The minimal clinically important difference was 2.5 points.ResultsOf the 198 participants randomized, 194 were included in the full analysis set (mean age, 41.3 [SD, 13.6] years; 56.7% were female; and 3.6% were Asian, 7.7% were Black or African American, and 83.0% were White). The dose-response relationship assessed using the MCP-Mod method for change in HAM-A score at week 4 was statistically significant for the 100-µg and the 200-µg dose groups vs placebo (least-squares mean difference, −5.0 points [95% CI, −9.6 to −0.4 points] with 100 µg of MM120 and −6.0 points [95% CI, −9.8 to −2.0 points] with 200 µg of MM120) but the 25-µg and 50-µg dose groups did not reach significance vs placebo (least-squares mean difference, −1.2 points [95% CI, −6.0 to 3.5 points] with 25 µg of MM120 and −1.8 points [95% CI, −7.6 to 4.0 points] with 50 µg of MM120). The adverse events were consistent with the expected effects of MM120. The most common adverse events were visual perceptual changes (illusion, pseudo-hallucination, and visual hallucination), which occurred in 46.2% of participants who received 25 µg of MM120, in 75.0% who received 50 µg, in 92.5% who received 100 µg, in 100% who received 200 µg, and in 10.3% who received placebo; nausea occurred in 7.7%, 27.5%, 40.0%, 60.0%, and 7.7%, respectively; and headache occurred in 12.8%, 22.5%, 35.0%, 27.5%, and 23.1%.Conclusions and RelevanceIn participants with moderate to severe GAD, a single dose of MM120 produced a dose-dependent reduction in anxiety. These results support the dose-dependent efficacy of MM120 and inform the dose selection for phase 3 pivotal trials.Trial RegistrationClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT05407064
DOI: 10.1001/jama.2025.13481
ISSN: 0098-7484
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jama.2025.13481-2025-11-25-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Azelastine Nasal Spray for Prevention of SARS-CoV-2 Infections</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.4283</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2452
Autoren: Thorsten Lehr, Peter Meiser, Dominik Selzer, Torben Rixecker, Frank Holzer, Ralph Mösges, Sigrun Smola, Robert Bals, CONTAIN Study Group, Veronika Alberg, Florian Bub, Nicholas Biwank, Charlotte Dette, Lale Dastgir, Alina Kuntz, Christopher Hale, Johanna Sophie Kapp, Kathrin Litzenburger, Henning Morr, Johanna Wagner, Hacer Sahin, Nelli Schröder, Martina Seibert, Katrin Thieser, Quirin Werthner
Journal: JAMA Internal Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
Abstract: 
                    Importance
                    Limited pharmaceutical options exist for preexposure prophylaxis of COVID-19 beyond vaccination. Azelastine, an antihistamine nasal spray used for decades to treat allergic rhinitis, has in vitro antiviral activity against respiratory viruses, including SARS-CoV-2.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    To determine the efficacy and safety of azelastine nasal spray for prevention of SARS-CoV-2 infections in healthy adults.
                  
                  
                    Design, Setting, and Participants
                    A phase 2, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single-center trial was conducted from March 2023 to July 2024. Healthy adults from the general population were enrolled at the Saarland University Hospital in Germany.
                  
                  
                    Interventions
                    Participants were randomly assigned 1:1 to receive azelastine, 0.1%, nasal spray or placebo 3 times daily for 56 days. SARS-CoV-2 rapid antigen testing (RAT) was conducted twice weekly, with positive results confirmed by polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Symptomatic participants with negative RAT results underwent multiplex PCR testing for respiratory viruses.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcome
                    The primary end point was the number of PCR-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infections during the study.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    A total of 450 participants were randomized, with 227 assigned to azelastine and 223 to placebo; 299 (66.4%) were female, 151 (33.6%) male, with a mean (SD) age of 33.0 (13.3) years. Most were White (417 [92.7%]), with 4 (0.9%) African, 22 (4.9%) Asian, and 7 (1.6%) of other ethnicity. In the intention-to-treat (ITT) population, the incidence of PCR-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection was significantly lower in the azelastine group (n = 5 [2.2%]) compared with the placebo group (n = 15 [6.7%]) (OR, 0.31; 95% CI, 0.11-0.87). As secondary end points, azelastine demonstrated an increase in mean (SD) time to SARS-CoV-2 infection among infected participants (31.2 [9.3] vs 19.5 [14.8] days), a reduction of the overall number of PCR-confirmed symptomatic infections (21 of 227 participants vs 49 of 223 participants), and a lower incidence of PCR-confirmed rhinovirus infections (1.8% vs 6.3%). Adverse events were comparable between the groups.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions and Relevance
                    In this single-center trial, azelastine nasal spray was associated with reduced risk of SARS-CoV-2 respiratory infections. These findings support the potential of azelastine as a safe prophylactic approach warranting confirmation in larger, multicentric trials.
                  
                  
                    Trial registration
                    
                      EudraCT number:
                      2022-003756-13
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.4283
ISSN: 2168-6106
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.4283-2025-11-25-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The effects of antidepressants on cardiometabolic and other physiological parameters: a systematic review and network meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140-6736(25)01293-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2401
Autoren: Toby Pillinger, Atheeshaan Arumuham, Robert A McCutcheon, Enrico D’Ambrosio, Georgios Basdanis, Marco Branco, Richard Carr, Valeria Finelli, Toshi A Furukawa, Siobhan Gee, Adrian Heald, Sameer Jauhar, Zihan Ma, Valentina Mancini, Calum Moulton, Georgia Salanti, David M Taylor, Anneka Tomlinson, Allan H Young, Orestis Efthimiou, Oliver D Howes, Andrea Cipriani
Journal: The Lancet
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/s0140-6736(25)01293-0
ISSN: 0140-6736
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s0140-6736(25)01293-0-2025-11-25-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The 2025 report of the Lancet Countdown on health and climate change</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140-6736(25)01919-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2238
Autoren: Marina Romanello, Maria Walawender, Shih-Che Hsu, Annalyse Moskeland, Yasna Palmeiro-Silva, Daniel Scamman, James W Smallcombe, Sabah Abdullah, Melanie Ades, Abdullah Al-Maruf, Nadia Ameli, Denitsa Angelova, Sonja Ayeb-Karlsson, Joan Ballester, Xavier Basagaña, Hannah Bechara, Paul J Beggs, Wenjia Cai, Diarmid Campbell-Lendrum, Gina E C Charnley, Orin Courtenay, Troy J Cross, Carole Dalin, Niheer Dasandi, Shouro Dasgupta, Michael Davies, Matthew Eckelman, Chris Freyberg, Paulina Garcia Corral, Olga Gasparyan, Joseph Giguere, Georgiana Gordon-Strachan, Sophie Gumy, Samuel H Gunther, Ian Hamilton, Yun Hang, Risto Hänninen, Stella Hartinger, Kehan He, Julian Heidecke, Jeremy J Hess, Slava Jankin, Ollie Jay, Dafni Kalatzi Pantera, Ilan Kelman, Harry Kennard, Gregor Kiesewetter, Patrick Kinney, Dominic Kniveton, Vally Koubi, Rostislav Kouznetsov, Pete Lampard, Jason K W Lee, Bruno Lemke, Bo Li, Andrew Linke, Yang Liu, Zhao Liu, Rachel Lowe, Siqi Ma, Tafadzwanashe Mabhaudhi, Carla Maia, Anil Markandya, Greta Martin, Jaime Martinez-Urtaza, Mark Maslin, Lucy McAllister, Celia McMichael, Zhifu Mi, James Milner, Kelton Minor, Jan Minx, Nahid Mohajeri, Natalie C Momen, Maziar Moradi-Lakeh, Karyn Morrisey, Simon Munzert, Kris A Murray, Nick Obradovich, Papa Orgen, Matthias Otto, Fereidoon Owfi, Olivia L Pearman, Frank Pega, Andrew J Pershing, Ana-Catarina Pinho-Gomes, Jamie Ponmattam, Mahnaz Rabbaniha, Tim Repke, Jorge Roa, Elizabeth Robinson, Joacim Rocklöv, David Rojas-Rueda, Jorge Ruiz-Cabrejos, Matilde Rusticucci, Renee N Salas, Adrià San José Plana, Jan C Semenza, Jodi D Sherman, Joy Shumake-Guillemot, Pratik Singh, Henrik Sjödin, Matthew R Smith, Mikhail Sofiev, Cecilia Sorensen, Marco Springmann, Jennifer D Stowell, Meisam Tabatabaei, Federico Tartarini, Jonathon Taylor, Cathryn Tonne, Marina Treskova, Joaquin A Trinanes, Andreas Uppstu, Nicolas Valdes-Ortega, Fabian Wagner, Nick Watts, Hannah Whitcombe, Richard Wood, Pu Yang, Ying Zhang, Shaohui Zhang, Chi Zhang, Shihui Zhang, Qiao Zhu, Peng Gong, Hugh Montgomery, Anthony Costello
Journal: The Lancet
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/s0140-6736(25)01919-1
ISSN: 0140-6736
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s0140-6736(25)01919-1-2025-11-25-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Beta-Blockers after Myocardial Infarction without Reduced Ejection Fraction</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2504735</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1767
Autoren: Borja Ibanez, Roberto Latini, Xavier Rossello, Alberto Dominguez-Rodriguez, Felipe Fernández-Vazquez, Valentina Pelizzoni, Pedro L. Sánchez, Manuel Anguita, José A. Barrabés, Sergio Raposeiras-Roubín, Stuart Pocock, Noemí Escalera, Lidia Staszewsky, Carlos Nicolás Pérez-García, Pablo Díez-Villanueva, Jose-Angel Pérez-Rivera, Oscar Prada-Delgado, Ruth Owen, Gonzalo Pizarro, Onofre Caldes, Sandra Gómez-Talavera, José Tuñón, Matteo Bianco, Jesus Zarauza, Alfredo Vetrano, Ana Campos, Susana Martínez-Huertas, Héctor Bueno, Miguel Puentes, Giulietta Grigis, Juan L. Bonilla-Palomas, Elvira Marco, José R. González-Juanatey, Roi Bangueses, Carlos González-Juanatey, Ana García-Álvarez, Juan Ruiz-García, Anna Carrasquer, Juan C. García-Rubira, Domingo Pascual-Figal, Carlos Tomás-Querol, J. Alberto San Román, Pasquale Baratta, Jaume Agüero, Roberto Martín-Reyes, Furio Colivicchi, Rosario Ortas-Nadal, Pablo Bazal, Alberto Cordero, Antonio Fernández-Ortiz, Pierangelo Basso, Eva González, Fabrizio Poletti, Giulia Bugani, Marzia Debiasio, Deborah Cosmi, Alessandro Navazio, Javier Bermejo, Giovanni Tortorella, Marco Marini, Javier Botas, José M. de la Torre-Hernández, Filippo Ottani, Valentín Fuster
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-13
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2504735
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2504735-2025-11-25-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>