<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 01:06:33 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 01:06:33 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of Computerized Cognitive Training on Vesicular Acetylcholine Transporter Levels using [18F]Fluoroethoxybenzovesamicol Positron Emission Tomography in Healthy Older Adults: Results from the Improving Neurological Health in Aging via Neuroplasticity-based Computerized Exercise (INHANCE) Randomized Clinical Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/75161</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 890
Autoren: Mouna Attarha, Ana de Figueiredo Pelegrino, Lydia Ouellet, Paule-Joanne Toussaint, Sarah-Jane Grant, Thomas Van Vleet, Etienne de Villers-Sidani
Journal: JMIR Serious Games
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-13
Abstract: 
            Background
            The cholinergic system mediates essential aspects of cognitive function, yet its structure and function decline progressively with age, by an estimated 2.5% per decade across the lifespan. Cognitive training may help counteract age-related declines in cholinergic functioning and slow associated deficits in cognitive performance.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aims to evaluate whether cognitive training modifies cholinergic binding in older adults.
          
          
            Methods
            The Improving Neurological Health in Aging via Neuroplasticity-based Computerized Exercise (INHANCE) trial is a double-blind randomized controlled trial assessing whether 2 computerized cognitive training programs modify cholinergic expression. The intent-to-treat (ITT) population included 92 community-dwelling healthy older adults aged 65 and above (enrolled July 2021-December 2023; final follow-up June 2024). Participants were randomized at McGill University to either an intervention of speed-based cognitive training exercises designed to improve the speed and accuracy of information processing or an active control of nonspeeded games designed for entertainment (eg, similar in design to Solitaire). Participants completed 35 hours of training on their assigned program at home over a 10-week period using a loaned or personal internet-connected device. Cholinergic binding was measured with the vesicular acetylcholine transporter ligand [18F]fluoroethoxybenzovesamicol (FEOBV) and positron emission tomography (PET). The primary outcome was mean FEOBV binding (standard uptake value ratios [SUVRs]) within the anterior cingulate cortex from baseline to posttest in the ITT population. All other end points were exploratory.
          
          
            Results
            Among the 92 participants in the ITT population (mean age 71.9 years; mean education 16.5 years; 61/92, 66%, women; 88/92, 96%, White), 82 (89%) completed all study activities. The speed-based intervention showed a significant within-group increase in FEOBV binding in the primary region of interest, the anterior cingulate cortex (SUVR change mean +0.044, 95% CI 0.006-0.082, P=.03, medium effect size, ω²=0.09). The p24c subregion demonstrated a significant between-groups effect favoring speed training (speeded vs nonspeeded SUVR change difference +0.058, 95% CI 0.007-0.110, P=.03, small effect size, ω²=0.05). Prespecified exploratory analyses revealed significant within-group effects for speed training in the hippocampus (P=.02) and parahippocampal gyrus (P=.04). No effects on FEOBV binding were observed in the active control group.
          
          
            Conclusions
            INHANCE is the largest FEOBV-PET trial to date and demonstrates, for the first time in humans, that speed training can reverse losses in cholinergic terminal densities in brain regions vulnerable to age-related cognitive decline. The 2.3% gain in FEOBV binding in the anterior cingulate achieved over a 10-week intervention may offset the estimated 2.5% decline typically observed over a decade of natural aging. These findings clarify the neurochemical basis of cognitive training benefits, showing that speed training upregulates binding in networks that support attention, memory, and executive function.
          
          
            Trial Registration
            ClinicalTrials.gov NCT04149457; https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT04149457
          
          
            International Registered Report Identifier (IRRID)
            RR2-10.2196/59705
          
DOI: 10.2196/75161
ISSN: 2291-9279
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/75161-2025-11-12-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>When helpfulness backfires: LLMs and the risk of false medical information due to sycophantic behavior</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-02008-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 199
Autoren: Shan Chen, Mingye Gao, Kuleen Sasse, Thomas Hartvigsen, Brian Anthony, Lizhou Fan, Hugo Aerts, Jack Gallifant, Danielle S. Bitterman
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
Abstract: Abstract
                  Large language models (LLMs) exhibit a vulnerability arising from being trained to be helpful: a tendency to comply with illogical requests that would generate false information, even when they have the knowledge to identify the request as illogical. This study investigated this vulnerability in the medical domain, evaluating five frontier LLMs using prompts that misrepresent equivalent drug relationships. We tested baseline sycophancy, the impact of prompts allowing rejection and emphasizing factual recall, and the effects of fine-tuning on a dataset of illogical requests, including out-of-distribution generalization. Results showed high initial compliance (up to 100%) across all models, prioritizing helpfulness over logical consistency. Prompt engineering and fine-tuning improved performance, improving rejection rates on illogical requests while maintaining general benchmark performance. This demonstrates that prioritizing logical consistency through targeted training and prompting is crucial for mitigating the risk of generating false medical information and ensuring the safe deployment of LLMs in healthcare.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-02008-z
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-02008-z-2025-11-12-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Extension of the GRACE score for non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome: a development and validation study in ten countries</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landig.2025.100907</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 118
Autoren: Florian A Wenzl, Klaus F Kofoed, Moa Simonsson, Gareth Ambler, Niels M R van der Sangen, Erik Lampa, Francesco Bruno, Mark A de Belder, Jiri Hlasensky, Matthias Mueller-Hennessen, Maria A Smolle, Peizhi Wang, José P S Henriques, Wouter J Kikkert, Henning Kelbæk, Luboš Bouček, Sergio Raposeiras-Roubín, Emad Abu-Assi, Jaouad Azzahhafi, Matthijs A Velders, Konstantinos Stellos, Thomas Engstrøm, Dean R P P Chan Pin Yin, Clive Weston, David Adlam, Hans Rickli, Evangelos Giannitsis, Dragana Radovanovic, Jiri Parenica, Charalambos A Antoniades, Keith A A Fox, Fabrizio D'Ascenzo, Jurriën M ten Berg, Lars V Køber, Stefan James, John Deanfield, Thomas F Lüscher
Journal: The Lancet Digital Health
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.landig.2025.100907
ISSN: 2589-7500
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.landig.2025.100907-2025-11-12-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>An Exploration of How Functional Neurological Disorder Is Discussed on X (Twitter): Mixed Methods Study Using Social Network and Content Analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/73439</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 64
Autoren: Caoimhe McLoughlin, Jing-Yi Wang, Florence Do, Takamichi Kanbayashi, Anna Couturier, Alan Carson, Jon Stone
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
Abstract: 
            Background
            Functional neurological disorder (FND) is one of the commonest conditions in neurological practice, describing symptoms like paralysis and seizures that can be severe and disabling. It is a diagnosis that is confirmed clinically rather than by scans or laboratory results. It is a stigmatized and widely misperceived condition, and since the emergence of long COVID, there has been some conflation of FND with other conditions, which has caused further misunderstanding. Social media has become increasingly popular for patients to learn and interact about their conditions, and the information that they seek and receive may be shaped by many factors. Prior to this study, the online discourse about FND had not been described in the literature.
          
          
            Objective
            We aimed to analyze and describe how FND is discussed on the social media platform X (formerly known as Twitter) using a mixed methods approach.
          
          
            Methods
            Using search terms related to FND, the authors collected data from 426 users and 1104 posts, generating a total of 7640 replies and reposts over a 2-month time frame in 2024. Quantitative descriptive and social network analyses were carried out to map key influential users and communities, in addition to measuring the influence of users. Content analysis was undertaken to describe the prevalent topics being discussed.
          
          
            Results
            More users overall associated with conditions outside FND (n=180, 42.3%), mostly long COVID and myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome, compared with FND (n=148, 34.7%). Self-declared patients made up 40.8% (450/1104) of posts and 36.4% (n=155) of users. Social network analysis revealed 2 separate communities with little interaction. There was a prominence of myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome and long COVID–associated users (nodes) over FND users (nodes). The former cluster showed stronger connections outwardly or peripherally than the FND cluster, suggesting that they may have a stronger impact on shaping the public narrative around FND than FND nodes. In total, 7 of the top 10 most influential users often displayed anti-FND views, while FND organizations and professionals had much less influence. There were 58 posts with at least 5000 views. Of these 58, 10 were from self-declared FND professionals, while 19 were from self-declared professionals associated with other conditions. Of these highly viewed posts, 38 of 58 were negatively predisposed toward FND. Content analysis showed themes of (1) conflict, (2) deception, (3) mistreatment and harm, (4) symptom experience, (5) knowledge, and (6) support.
          
          
            Conclusions
            A large proportion of the discourse around FND on X is shaped by users who are dismissive of the concept of FND and those associated with it. These findings have implications for individuals getting support for a condition that is already widely misunderstood. This study could provide a template for assessing how other stigmatized conditions are perceived on the web.
          
DOI: 10.2196/73439
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/73439-2025-11-12-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Artificial intelligence and computer-aided diagnosis in diagnostic decisions: 5 questions for medical informatics and human-computer interface research</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocaf123</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 44
Autoren: Tad T Brunyé, Stephen R Mitroff, Joann G Elmore
Journal: Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
Abstract: Abstract
               
                  Objectives
                  Artificial intelligence (AI) has the potential to transform medical informatics by supporting clinical decision-making, reducing diagnostic errors, and improving workflows and efficiency. However, successful integration of AI-based decision support systems depends on careful consideration of human-AI collaboration, trust, skill maintenance, and automation bias. This work proposes five central questions to guide future research in medical informatics and human-computer interface (HCI).
               
               
                  Materials and Methods
                  We focus on AI-based clinical decision support systems, including computer vision algorithms for medical imaging (radiology, pathology), natural language processing for structured and unstructured electronic health record (EHR) data, and rule-based systems. Relevant data modalities include clinician-acquired images, EHR text, and increasingly, patient-generated content in telehealth contexts. We review existing evidence regarding diagnostic errors across specialties, the effectiveness and risks of AI tools in reducing perceptual and interpretive errors, and the human factors influencing diagnostic decision-making in AI-enabled contexts. We synthesize insights from medicine, cognitive science, and HCI to identify gaps in knowledge and propose five key questions for continued research.
               
               
                  Results
                  Diagnostic errors remain common across medicine, with AI offering potential to reduce both perceptual and interpretive errors. However, the impact of AI depends critically on how and when information is presented. Studies indicate that delayed or toggleable cues may outperform immediate ones, but attentional capture, overreliance, and bias remain significant risks. Explainable AI provides transparency but can also bias decisions. Long-term reliance on AI may erode clinician skills, particularly for trainees and in low-prevalence contexts. Historical failures of computer-aided diagnosis in mammography highlight these challenges.
               
               
                  Discussion and Conclusion
                  Effective AI integration requires human-centered and adaptive design. Five central research questions address: (1) what type and format of information AI should provide; (2) when information should be presented; (3) how explainable AI affects diagnostic decisions; (4) how AI influences automation bias and complacency; and (5) the risks of skill decay due to reliance on AI. Each question underscores the importance of balancing efficiency, accuracy, and clinician expertise while mitigating bias and skill degradation. AI holds promise for improving diagnostic accuracy and efficiency, but realizing its potential requires post-deployment evaluation, equitable access, clinician oversight, and targeted training. AI must complement, rather than replace, human expertise, ensuring safe, effective, and sustainable integration into diagnostic decision-making. Addressing these challenges proactively can maximize AI’s potential across healthcare and other high-stakes domains.
               
DOI: 10.1093/jamia/ocaf123
ISSN: 1067-5027
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/jamia/ocaf123-2025-11-12-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>