<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 00:58:54 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 00:58:54 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>All the Colors of the Rainbow: Synthetic Dyes in US Packaged Foods and Beverages in 2020</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 942
Autoren: Elizabeth K. Dunford, Thomas M. Galligan, Lindsey Smith Taillie, Aviva A. Musicus
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007-2025-08-30-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Healthfulness of Foods Purchased at Dollar Stores: Insights from Household Scanner Data from 2008 to 2020</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 239
Autoren: Wenhui Feng, Elina T. Page, Bangyao Sun, Sean B. Cash
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001-2025-08-30-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Nutritional Epidemiology Risk–Survival Paradox</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 154
Autoren: Raphael E Cuomo
Journal: The Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020
ISSN: 0022-3166
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020-2025-08-30-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Low-fat and whole milk consumption in relation to cardiovascular disease–related and all-cause mortality: a prospective cohort study in 3 Norwegian counties</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 131
Autoren: Erik Kristoffer Arnesen, Jacob Juel Christensen, Ida Laake, Monica H Carlsen, Marit B Veierød, Kjetil Retterstøl
Journal: The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035
ISSN: 0002-9165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035-2025-08-30-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Intermittent fasting in the treatment of type 2 diabetes</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1629154</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 79
Autoren: Damian Dyńka, Łukasz Rodzeń, Mateusz Rodzeń, Dorota Łojko, Adam Deptuła, Żaneta Grzywacz, Sebastian Kraszewski, Karolina Bartoń, Peter Martin, Anna Małgorzata Deptuła, Ken Berry, David Unwin
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-18
Abstract: The increasing prevalence of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) has inspired researchers to investigate therapies and tools supporting the treatment of this disease. One such tool is intermittent fasting (IF). Given the nature and mechanism of action of IF, it would be logical for it to have a beneficial effect on T2DM patients. This study analyzes the role of IF in the treatment of type 2 diabetes, used alongside standard recommendations, based on the current literature available to the authors. The authors discuss the benefits of IF in T2DM treatment, such as improved glycaemic control, improved insulin sensitivity, facilitated adherence to recommendations, weight reduction, and lower risk of complications. This study covers the results of meta-analyses, systematic reviews, and randomized controlled trials (RCTs) and shows how novel technologies, including continuous glucose monitors and mobile applications, can support the implementation of IF. The importance of safety monitoring is also highlighted, particularly in insulin-treated patients due to the potential risk of hypoglycaemia.
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1629154
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1629154-2025-08-30-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>