<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:11:00 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:11:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Natural daylight during office hours improves glucose control and whole-body substrate metabolism</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.006</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 793
Autoren: Jan-Frieder Harmsen, Ivo Habets, Andrew D. Biancolin, Agata Lesniewska, Nicholas E. Phillips, Loic Metz, Juan Sanchez-Avila, Marit Kotte, Merel Timmermans, Dzhansel Hashim, Soraya S. de Kam, Gert Schaart, Johanna A. Jörgensen, Anne Gemmink, Esther Moonen-Kornips, Daniel Doligkeit, Tineke van de Weijer, Mijke Buitinga, Florian Haans, Rebecca De Lorenzo, Hannah Pallubinsky, Marijke C.M. Gordijn, Tinh-Hai Collet, Achim Kramer, Patrick Schrauwen, Charna Dibner, Joris Hoeks
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.006
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.006-2026-01-17-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Aluminium adjuvants and childhood health: a call for science</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtemb.2025.127810</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 148
Autoren: Guillemette Crépeaux, Jeremy R. Hammond, Jonathan B. Handley, Brian Hooker, Karl Jablonowski, Lluís Luján, James Lyons-Weiler, Marika Nosten-Bertrand, Christopher A. Shaw, Yehuda Shoenfeld, Lucija Tomljenovic, Christopher Exley
Journal: Journal of Trace Elements in Medicine and Biology
Veröffentlicht: 2026-02-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jtemb.2025.127810
ISSN: 0946-672X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jtemb.2025.127810-2026-01-17-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cytoarchitectural multi-depot profiling reveals immune-metabolic crosstalk in human colon-associated adipose tissue</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.12.008</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 143
Autoren: Jutta Jalkanen, Jiawei Zhong, Pamela A. Nono Nankam, Nayanika Bhalla, Merve Elmastas, Jiaxin Luo, Sophie Weinbrenner, Scott Frendo-Cumbo, Benedek Pesti, William Gourash, Anita Courcoulas, Zinger Yang Loureiro, Arne Dietrich, Jesper Bäckdahl, Anders Thorell, Marcus Buggert, Joanna Kalucka, Margo P. Emont, Evan D. Rosen, Matthias Blüher, Peter Kovacs, Patrik L. Ståhl, Lucas Massier, Mikael Rydén, Niklas Mejhert
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.12.008
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.12.008-2026-01-17-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Enhanced non-enzymatic H2S generation extends lifespan and healthspan in male mice</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.012</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 136
Autoren: María Ángeles Cáliz-Molina, Raúl López-Fernández-Sobrino, Inmaculada Pino-Pérez, Concepción Panadero-Morón, María del Carmen Vilches-Pérez, María Camacho-Cabrera, Almudena García-Ruiz, Leopoldo Pérez-Rosendo, Isabel Espadas, Alejandro Sola-García, Mario Soriano-Navarro, Franz Martin, Mónica Venegas-Calerón, Joaquín Jesús Salas, Enrique Martínez-Force, Luis C. Romero, Ángeles Aroca, Román González-Prieto, Máximo Bernabeu-Wittel, Vivian Capilla-González, Christopher Hine, Alejandro Martín-Montalvo
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.012
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.11.012-2026-01-17-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Application of continuous glucose monitoring and automated insulin delivery technologies for pregnant women with type 1, type 2, or gestational diabetes: an international consensus statement</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00335-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 115
Autoren: Katrien Benhalima, Celeste Durnwald, Arianne Sweeting, Dawn Adams, Ananta Addala, Tadej Battelino, Richard M Bergenstal, Anders Carlson, Lois E Donovan, Denise Reis Franco, Julie Heverly, Diana Isaacs, Kamlesh Khunti, Anne-Beatrice Kihara, Naomi Levitt, Carol J Levy, Mareda Lewer, Elisabeth Mathiesen, Helen R Murphy, Rimei Nishimura, Sarit Polsky, Uma Ram, David Simmons, Jennifer M Yamamoto, Ádám G Tabák, Denice Feig, Eleanor M Scott
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2026-02-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00335-3
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00335-3-2026-01-17-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>