<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 00:58:56 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 00:58:56 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>All the Colors of the Rainbow: Synthetic Dyes in US Packaged Foods and Beverages in 2020</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 942
Autoren: Elizabeth K. Dunford, Thomas M. Galligan, Lindsey Smith Taillie, Aviva A. Musicus
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007-2025-09-06-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Healthfulness of Foods Purchased at Dollar Stores: Insights from Household Scanner Data from 2008 to 2020</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 239
Autoren: Wenhui Feng, Elina T. Page, Bangyao Sun, Sean B. Cash
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001-2025-09-06-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Are all ultra-processed foods bad? A critical review of the NOVA classification system</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0029665125100645</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 176
Autoren: Jimmy Chun Yu Louie
Journal: Proceedings of the Nutrition Society
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-04
Abstract: Abstract
	  The NOVA food classification system and its categorisation of ultra-processed foods (UPFs) have significantly influenced dietary guidelines worldwide, yet the assumption that all UPFs are uniformly harmful warrants critical examination. Here, a review of evidence revealed substantial heterogeneity in health outcomes across UPF subtypes, with products like sugar-sweetened beverages consistently associated with adverse outcomes while fortified cereals and certain dairy products demonstrate neutral or protective effects. The binary nature of NOVA’s classification fails to account for nutritional composition, fortification benefits, and cultural food traditions, creating inconsistencies in categorisation across different contexts. Methodological limitations in UPF research include inadequate dietary assessment tools, selective reporting of negative findings, and experimental design flaws that conflate processing with other dietary factors. Implementation challenges extend to socioeconomic accessibility, as UPFs often provide cost-effective nutrients for disadvantaged populations and environmental sustainability, where wholesale reduction could increase resource demands. Future directions should develop more nuanced classification systems that integrate processing methods with nutritional quality to better inform public health strategies rather than categorically rejecting all UPFs.
DOI: 10.1017/s0029665125100645
ISSN: 0029-6651
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1017/s0029665125100645-2025-09-06-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Nutritional Epidemiology Risk–Survival Paradox</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 166
Autoren: Raphael E Cuomo
Journal: The Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020
ISSN: 0022-3166
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020-2025-09-06-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cluttered with claims: Composition, nutrition, health and marketing claims on commercial infant and toddler foods in New Zealand</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/1747-0080.70042</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 148
Autoren: Sally Mackay, Berit Follong, Baylee Wilde, Maria Ferreria, Maree Scully
Journal: Nutrition &amp;amp; Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-26
Abstract: AbstractAimThe World Health Organization Regional Office for Europe's Nutrient and Promotion Profile Model recommends that commercial infant and toddler foods do not carry compositional, nutrition, health, or marketing claims. Our objective was to identify on‐pack claims displayed on commercial foods for infants and toddlers in New Zealand.MethodThe packaging of products intended for infants (aged up to 11 months) and toddlers (ages 12 months to &amp;lt;36 months) was analyzed for the presence of claims using a coding structure based on categories outlined by the World Health Organization Europe Nutrient and Promotion Profile Model. Descriptive statistics were conducted to analyze the frequency of types of claims. Relevant infant and toddler products available in New Zealand supermarkets were identified through a packaged food database of products collected in 2023.ResultsTwo hundred and ten products were identified: 167 infant and 43 toddler products. On average, there were 7.5 unique claims per product (range 3–15), with composition and nutrition claims being the most common (mean 4.0 per product), followed by marketing (3.3) and health claims (0.2). Composition and nutrition claims relating to the absence of ingredients generally perceived to be harmful (i.e. ‘free from’ claims) were prevalent on 97% of products and most commonly referred to flavors (on 72% of products) and colors (71%).ConclusionsAll New Zealand infant and toddler products carried multiple claims. Regulation is needed to align with international best practice and prevent caregivers from being potentially misled by these promotional messages when making purchasing decisions for young children.
DOI: 10.1111/1747-0080.70042
ISSN: 1446-6368
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/1747-0080.70042-2025-09-06-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>