<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 01:08:50 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 01:08:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Clinical Efficacy, Safety and Imaging Effects of Oral Valiltramiprosate in APOEε4/ε4 Homozygotes with Early Alzheimer’s Disease: Results of the Phase III, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, 78-Week APOLLOE4 Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s40265-025-02250-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 436
Autoren: Susan Abushakra, Aidan Power, David Watson, Anton Porsteinsson, Marwan Sabbagh, Emer MacSweeney, Sharon Cohen, Mercè Boada Rovira, P. Murali Doraiswamy, Earvin Liang, Susan Flint, J. Patrick Kesslak, Rosalind McLaine, Adem Albayrak, Jean Schaefer, Jeremy Yu, Luke Tolar, Sam Dickson, John A. Hey, Martin Tolar
Journal: Drugs
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-28
DOI: 10.1007/s40265-025-02250-5
ISSN: 0012-6667
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s40265-025-02250-5-2025-11-01-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Deaths following illicit ketamine use in England, Wales and Northern Ireland 1999–2024: An update report to inform the reclassification debate</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/02698811251373058</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 382
Autoren: Jade Pullen, John M. Corkery, Rebecca McKnight, Caroline S. Copeland
Journal: Journal of Psychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-29
Abstract: 
            Background:
            Ketamine is increasingly used in the United Kingdom in non-clinical settings for its psychoactive effects, with rising reports of harms including hospital admissions, dependence and deaths. In light of current debates surrounding the reclassification of ketamine under the Misuse of Drugs Act 1971, up-to-date surveillance of associated mortality is warranted.
          
          
            Aims:
            We aimed to quantify trends in deaths following illicit ketamine use in England, Wales and Northern Ireland, and to examine changes in demographic and contextual characteristics since the last national analysis which comprised illicit ketamine deaths up to 2019.
          
          
            Methods:
            Cases where illicit ketamine was detected at post-mortem were extracted from the National Programme on Substance Use Mortality and analysed.
          
          
            Results:
            There were 696 deaths identified with illicit ketamine between 1999 and 2024. Annual deaths increased over 10-fold from 2014 (15 deaths) to 2024 (197 projected deaths). Whilst absolute deaths implicating illicit ketamine rose (2014: 6 deaths; 2023: 123 projected deaths), the proportion of deaths where illicit ketamine was implicated in causing death declined (2014: 60.0% of cases; 2024: 42.6% of cases). Concurrently, polydrug use increased (median number of co-administered substances 1999–2004: 3; 2005–2009: 3, 2010–2014: 4, 2015–2019: 6; 2020–2024: 6), and the demographic profile of decedents shifted towards greater deprivation and dependence-related contexts.
          
          
            Discussion and Conclusions:
            There has been an acceleration in deaths following illicit ketamine in recent years, which are increasingly featuring complex patterns of polydrug use and socio-economic vulnerability. Policy responses must extend beyond single-substance legislative controls to encompass harm reduction, treatment integration, and social support strategies.
          
DOI: 10.1177/02698811251373058
ISSN: 0269-8811
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/02698811251373058-2025-11-01-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The continued impact of COVID-19 during the Omicron era on immunocompromised individuals in Japan</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 111
Autoren: Toshibumi Taniguchi, Mitsuru Hoshino, Ryotaro Ide, Tomoyuki Homma, Keiji Sugiyama, Shinichi Kanazu, Atsushi Maruyama, Kazuhiro Tateda
Journal: Journal of Infection and Chemotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840
ISSN: 1341-321X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840-2025-11-01-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Optochemical modulation of corneal cold nerve terminal impulse activity with a photochromic ion channel blocker</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/bph.70189</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 109
Autoren: David Ares‐Suárez, Almudena Iñigo‐Portugués, Enrique Velasco, Susana Quirce, Fernando Aleixandre‐Carrera, Ariadna Díaz‐Tahoces, M. Carmen Acosta, Wan‐Chen Lin, Richard H. Kramer, Carlos Belmonte, Juana Gallar, Victor Meseguer
Journal: British Journal of Pharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-28
Abstract: Background and PurposeThe functional organization of corneal cold nerve endings, critical structures in maintaining the ocular surface, remains poorly understood. Here, the photoisomerizable small‐molecule diethylamine‐azobenzene‐quaternary ammonium (DENAQ) was used to photomodulate activity of cold‐sensing nerve terminals in control and chronic tear‐deficient corneas. Furthermore, DENAQ was used for in vivo photochemical regulation of the thermally induced blink reflex.Experimental ApproachExtracellular nerve terminal impulse activity was recorded on cold terminals in excised corneas of naïve and tear‐deficient guinea pigs pre‐incubated with DENAQ. Pulses of light at a wavelength of 460 nm were delivered to the perfused corneas. The thermally induced blink reflex was assessed using orbicularis oculi electromyography in anaesthetised rats after topical administration of DENAQ to the eye under blue light and darkness conditions.Key ResultsExposure to blue light robustly reduced spontaneous activity of both naïve and tear‐deficient cold nerve terminals pre‐incubated with DENAQ, while cold‐evoked responses remained unaffected. Pre‐incubation of excised corneas with DENAQ, along with pharmacological P2X receptor antagonists, prevented the DENAQ‐mediated photoreduction of the cold nerve terminal spontaneous activity. In addition, blue light increased cold‐evoked reflex blink in eyes pre‐treated with DENAQ.Conclusion and ImplicationsDENAQ enters guinea pig cold sensory nerve endings primarily through P2X channels in excised corneas. Subsequently, DENAQ decreases the spontaneous nerve terminal impulse activity upon light irradiation by modulating voltage‐gated potassium (KV) channel activity. Furthermore, the cold‐evoked blink reflex is modulated by light in DENAQ‐treated eyes. Chemical photoswitches like DENAQ might be potential new treatments for ocular discomfort and pain in dry eye disease.
DOI: 10.1111/bph.70189
ISSN: 0007-1188
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/bph.70189-2025-11-01-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Hyper-maturity and accelerated aging in the hippocampus of mouse models of neuropsychiatric disorders with anxiety-like behavior</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-025-02237-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 78
Autoren: Hideo Hagihara, Hisatsugu Koshimizu, Satoko Hattori, Hirotaka Shoji, Miho Tanaka, Kazutaka Ikeda, Tsuyoshi Miyakawa
Journal: Neuropsychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-27
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Proper maturation of neuronal and glial cells in the hippocampus is essential for emotional regulation and cognitive function. While pseudo-immaturity, defined as arrested or reversed development, has been extensively implicated in various neuropsychiatric conditions, the opposite phenomenon, hyper-maturity, remains underexplored. Here, we present transcriptomic evidence of hippocampal hyper-maturity across 17 datasets from 16 mouse models with genetic, pharmacological, or other experimental manipulations, identified through a comprehensive screening of over 260,000 omics datasets. These models were characterized by a pronounced overrepresentation of gene expression changes typically observed during postnatal development and included serotonin transporter knockout mice, glucocorticoid receptor overexpressing mice, and corticosterone-treated mice, models of depression and anxiety, Df(16)A
                    +/−
                    mice, a 22q11.2 deletion schizophrenia model, β-glucuronidase-deficient lysosomal storage disorder model mice, and senescence-prone SAMP8 mice. Meta-analysis of enriched pathways highlighted associations of synapse-related genes with the hyper-maturity signature. Behavioral annotations from public datasets further suggest that hippocampal hyper-maturity models predominantly exhibit increased anxiety-like behaviors, whereas immaturity models tend to display the opposite pattern. Notably, hippocampal hyper-maturity encompassed two transcriptional dimensions: enhanced postnatal development and accelerated aging. For example, SAMP8 mice aligned more with developmental enhancement, whereas corticosterone-treated and lysosomal storage disorder models reflected aging acceleration. Combined analysis with available single-cell RNA-sequencing data further delineated that microglia and granule cells may contribute to aging-associated transcriptional shifts. These findings suggest that hippocampal hyper-maturity and accelerated aging represent convergent molecular phenotypes associated with anxiety-like behavior. Bidirectional alterations in hippocampal maturity may serve as a transdiagnostic endophenotype and offer novel therapeutic or anti-aging targets for neuropsychiatric disorders.
                  
DOI: 10.1038/s41386-025-02237-6
ISSN: 0893-133X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41386-025-02237-6-2025-11-01-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>