<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 01:04:42 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 01:04:42 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Medial Tibial Stress Syndrome Needs a New Name—Make No Bones About It</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13411</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 35
Autoren: Laura M. Anderson, Stuart J. Warden, Richard W. Willy, Daniel R. Bonanno, Hylton B. Menz
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
Abstract:  SYNOPSIS: Pain near the posteromedial tibia is common in running and jumping athletes. This problem has had many names, with “shin splints” and “medial tibial stress syndrome” (MTSS) the most common. The term shin splints is nonspecific and nondescript, and has never gained clinical traction. Similarly, the clinical use of MTSS with athletes and coaches is often met with confusion as “tibial stress” is frequently misinterpreted as indicating a bone stress injury. With no conclusive evidence regarding the pathophysiology of MTSS, we advocate renaming it “Load Induced Medial-Leg Pain” (LIMP). LIMP avoids the use of “tibial stress,” which is problematic due to the unknown pathology of the condition and its confusion with bone stress injury. Using the term LIMP instead of MTSS gives clinicians, researchers, and athletes a clearer, more accurate way to approach managing exercise-related lower leg pain. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2025;55(10):621-622. Epub 18 August 2025. doi:10.2519/jospt.2025.13411 
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13411
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13411-2025-10-22-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Broken Wing Sign: A New Clinical Test to Detect Gluteus Medius Pathology with and without Fatty Infiltration</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2106/jbjs.25.00427</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 32
Autoren: Rafael J. Sierra, Sergio F. Guarin Perez, Diego J. Restrepo, Benjamin M. Howe, Ta-Wei Tai
Journal: Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-12
Abstract: 
            Background:
            Gluteus medius tears and atrophy cause lateral hip pain, limp, and functional impairment. We developed the “broken wing sign,” a novel physical examination test for detecting gluteus medius tendon tears and muscle degeneration. This study evaluated its diagnostic accuracy and clinical utility against magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and intraoperative findings.
          
          
            Methods:
            We prospectively examined 59 patients (75 hips; mean age, 69.5 ± 10.8 years; 48 women) with suspected hip abductor insufficiency. The broken wing sign was tested with patients prone, the knee flexed at 90°, and the hip actively extended. A positive sign involved ≥10° of compensatory external hip rotation, visible as an inward drift of the foot, indicating gluteus medius (and resulting internal rotation) weakness. MRI served as the reference standard for classifying gluteus medius integrity as no tear, partial, full-thickness, or massive. Fatty infiltration was graded (Goutallier grades 0 to 4), quantified, and analyzed for a correlation with the examination findings. Diagnostic accuracy metrics were calculated.
          
          
            Results:
            The broken wing sign demonstrated high accuracy (sensitivity, 81.8%; specificity, 80.0%; positive predictive value [PPV], 91.8%; negative predictive value, 61.5%; diagnostic odds ratio, 17.8). An external rotation threshold of ≥30° yielded 100% specificity and 100% PPV for a tear. The sign detected acute tears with no or minimal fatty infiltration (100% sensitivity for massive tears). The degree of the external rotation angle was strongly correlated with muscle atrophy with fatty infiltration, showing 88.0% sensitivity for Goutallier grade ≥3 and 100% sensitivity for grade 4.
          
          
            Conclusions:
            The broken wing sign is clinically useful for diagnosing gluteus medius tendon tears and muscle atrophy, particularly massive tears and advanced fatty degeneration. It effectively guides MRI utilization and surgical planning, serving as a valuable initial diagnostic tool in the clinical setting.
          
          
            Level of Evidence:
            Diagnostic Level II. See Instructions for Authors for a complete description of levels of evidence.
          
DOI: 10.2106/jbjs.25.00427
ISSN: 0021-9355
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2106/jbjs.25.00427-2025-10-22-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The changing face of acute low back pain management by physiotherapists, osteopaths and chiropractors in the UK: a 20-year comparison from 2003 to 2023</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 23
Autoren: David W. Evans, Nadine E. Foster, Alan C. Breen, Tamar Pincus, Martin Underwood, Steven Vogel
Journal: BMC Musculoskeletal Disorders
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-02
DOI: 10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9
ISSN: 1471-2474
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9-2025-10-22-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Time‐dependent wound management protocol prevents periprosthetic joint infection in total knee arthroplasty with persistent drainage</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/ksa.70077</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 14
Autoren: Filippo Leggieri, Francesco Ferriani, Enrico Di Benedetto, Enrick Miani, Enrico Festa, Giovanni Balato, Stefano M. P. Rossi, Francesco Benazzo, Andrea Baldini
Journal: Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-29
Abstract: AbstractPurposeThis study aimed to evaluate the success rate of a standardised protocol for managing persistent wound drainage following total knee arthroplasty (TKA).MethodsA prospective observational study was conducted at four institutions between January and June 2022 across primary and revision TKAs. Sixty‐two patients (mean age 71.5 ± 9.3 years; 45.2% male) who experienced postoperative wound drainage after primary (58.1%) or revision (41.9%) TKA were enrolled. The protocol included staged interventions: anticoagulation adjustments and dressing changes during Days 1–3, incisional negative pressure wound therapy during Days 3–5, and wound debridement above the joint capsule if drainage persisted beyond Day 7. Outcomes were evaluated using the ASEPSIS score. The primary outcome was defined as complete wound healing without progression to debridement, antibiotics and implant retention (DAIR) procedure or periprosthetic joint infection (PJI).ResultsThe mean follow‐up was 13.2 months (range, 11.7–15.1 months). The protocol achieved a 91.9% success rate in preventing progression to DAIR. The median number of visits required to achieve wound healing was 3.5 for the cohort. DAIR rate was 8.1% (n = 5), while PJI rate was 1.6% (n = 1). Primary TKA procedures demonstrated more efficient healing trajectories compared to revision cases, requiring fewer clinical visits (median 3 vs. 5, p &amp;lt; 0.001) and shorter hospital stays (mean 4.5 vs. 7.5 days, p = 0.017). Cox proportional hazards model identified intervention type (revision vs. primary, hazard ratio [HR] 0.24, p &amp;lt; 0.001), advanced age (HR: 0.95 per year, p = 0.006), and male gender (HR: 0.45, p = 0.020) as significant independent predictors of increased time required to achieve wound healing.ConclusionOur standardised wound management protocol achieved a high success rate in preventing progression to PJI following TKA. The time‐dependent approach to intervention escalation provides clear clinical decision‐making criteria and suggests that early identification and systematic management of wound complications are critical determinants of successful outcomes, particularly for primary TKA procedures.Level of EvidenceLevel II.
DOI: 10.1002/ksa.70077
ISSN: 0942-2056
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/ksa.70077-2025-10-22-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy of Therapeutic Patient Education for Managing Subacute and Chronic Musculoskeletal Conditions: A Systematic Review With Meta-Analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13247</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 12
Autoren: Audrey-Anne Cormier, François Desmeules, Frédérique Dupuis, Simon Lafrance, Jean-Sébastien Côté, Marc-Olivier Dubé, Lori Michener, Peter Malliaras, Marie Désilets, Hugo Masse-Alarie, Jean-Sébastien Roy
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
Abstract:  OBJECTIVE: To evaluate the efficacy of therapeutic patient education delivered by a health care provider, either alone or in combination with other rehabilitation interventions, for reducing pain and disability in adults with subacute and chronic musculoskeletal conditions.  DESIGN: Intervention systematic review with meta-analysis.  LITERATURE SEARCH: Five databases were searched from 2005 to 2025.  STUDY SELECTION CRITERIA: Randomized clinical trials (RCTs) evaluating the efficacy of therapeutic patient education in adults with subacute and chronic musculoskeletal conditions, compared to other interventions such as exercise programs. Outcomes included pain, disability, quality of life, kinesiophobia, and catastrophizing.  DATA SYNTHESIS: Treatment effects were estimated using random-effects models with standardized mean differences. Risk of bias was assessed using the Cochrane RoB 2.0 tool. Certainty of evidence was evaluated using the Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development and Evaluation (GRADE) framework.  RESULTS: Sixty-nine RCTs were included, and 56 contributed data to meta-analyses (n = 6773 participants; mean age, 43.1 ± 10.3 years; 63% female). Adding therapeutic patient education to other interventions likely reduced pain, disability, and catastrophizing in the short term (moderate-certainty evidence), may reduce pain and disability in the medium term (low-certainty evidence), and likely resulted in a large reduction in kinesiophobia in the short and medium terms (moderate-certainty evidence). The efficacy of therapeutic patient education as a stand-alone intervention was uncertain.  CONCLUSION: Evidence supports using therapeutic patient education, in combination with other rehabilitation interventions, to reduce pain, disability, kinesiophobia, and catastrophizing in adults with subacute and chronic musculoskeletal conditions. The magnitude of the effects may vary from small to large. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2025;55(10):623-648. Epub 20 August 2025. doi:10.2519/jospt.2025.13247 
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13247
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13247-2025-10-22-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>