<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 01:05:52 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 01:05:52 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>A Flexible Multi-Sensor Device Enabling Handheld Sensing of Heart Sounds by Untrained Users</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1109/jbhi.2025.3551882</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 311
Autoren: Andrew McDonald, Maximilian Nussbaumer, Nirmani Rathnayake, Richard Steeds, Anurag Agarwal
Journal: IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1109/jbhi.2025.3551882
ISSN: 2168-2194
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1109/jbhi.2025.3551882-2025-08-31-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Evaluating gender bias in large language models in long-term care</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 114
Autoren: Sam Rickman
Journal: BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-11
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Large language models (LLMs) are being used to reduce the administrative burden in long-term care by automatically generating and summarising case notes. However, LLMs can reproduce bias in their training data. This study evaluates gender bias in summaries of long-term care records generated with two state-of-the-art, open-source LLMs released in 2024: Meta’s Llama 3 and Google Gemma.
          
          
            Methods
            Gender-swapped versions were created of long-term care records for 617 older people from a London local authority. Summaries of male and female versions were generated with Llama 3 and Gemma, as well as benchmark models from Meta and Google released in 2019: T5 and BART. Counterfactual bias was quantified through sentiment analysis alongside an evaluation of word frequency and thematic patterns.
          
          
            Results
            The benchmark models exhibited some variation in output on the basis of gender. Llama 3 showed no gender-based differences across any metrics. Gemma displayed the most significant gender-based differences. Male summaries focus more on physical and mental health issues. Language used for men was more direct, with women’s needs downplayed more often than men’s.
          
          
            Conclusion
            Care services are allocated on the basis of need. If women’s health issues are underemphasised, this may lead to gender-based disparities in service receipt. LLMs may offer substantial benefits in easing administrative burden. However, the findings highlight the variation in state-of-the-art LLMs, and the need for evaluation of bias. The methods in this paper provide a practical framework for quantitative evaluation of gender bias in LLMs. The code is available on GitHub.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0
ISSN: 1472-6947
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0-2025-08-31-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of The Legend of Zelda: Breath of the Wild and Studio Ghibli Films on Young People’s Sense of Exploration, Calm, Mastery and Skill, Purpose and Meaning, and Overall Happiness in Life: Exploratory Randomized Controlled Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/76522</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 103
Autoren: Annisa Arigayota, Barbara Duffek, Congcong Hou, Andreas Benedikt Eisingerich
Journal: JMIR Serious Games
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
Abstract: 
            Background
            Young people feel increasingly anxious and sad nowadays. Engaging with works of art and entertainment, such as playing open-world games or watching Studio Ghibli films, can be more than just a pastime. However, the extent to which, if at all, open-world games and feelings of nostalgia affect overall happiness in life remains unclear.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aimed to examine the extent to which open-world games, such as The Legend of Zelda: Breath of the Wild, and nostalgia evoked by Studio Ghibli films, such as Hayao Miyazaki’s My Neighbor Totoro or Kiki’s Delivery Service, affect postgraduate students’ sense of exploration, calm, mastery and skill, purpose and meaning, and, ultimately, happiness in life.
          
          
            Methods
            A controlled laboratory experiment was conducted using a 2 (playing an open-world game vs no open-world game) × 2 (nostalgia vs no nostalgia) between-subject design. Study participants (N=518) were randomly assigned to the study’s 4 conditions and answered a brief questionnaire, examining their sense of exploration, calm, mastery and skill, purpose and meaning, and, ultimately, happiness in life. As part of the study, we conducted univariate analysis and bootstrapping-based moderated mediation analysis with 5000 resamples.
          
          
            Results
            The results showed a significant and positive impact of playing an open-world game on overall life happiness (mean [M]playedgame 4.563, SD 0.072, vs Mnotplayedgame 3.170, SD 0.072; F(1, 517)=117.246, P&amp;lt;.001). Furthermore, the positive impact of open-world games on overall life happiness was significantly enhanced by nostalgia evoked by watching Studio Ghibli films (Mnostalgia 5.45, SD 0.102, vs Mnonostalgia 3.58, SD 0.102; SE 0.144, 95% CI 1.332-1.900; P&amp;lt;.001). Moreover, exploratory moderated mediation with bootstrapped-based analyses and 5000 resamples demonstrated that the effect of playing open-world games on happiness is mediated by a sense of exploration (effect=0.11; SE 0.05, 95% CI 0.04-0.21), sense of calm (effect=0.32; SE 0.09, 95% CI 0.15-0.51), sense of skill and mastery (effect=0.08; SE 0.05, 95% CI 0.01-0.18), and sense of purpose and meaning (effect=0.32; SE 0.14, 95% CI 0.06-0.60).
          
          
            Conclusions
            This study shows that playing an open-world game, such as The The Legend of Zelda: Breath of the Wild, and nostalgia evoked by Studio Ghibli films significantly foster a sense of exploration and calm in life, as well as a feeling of mastery and skill, and purpose and meaning, hence ultimately contributing positively to one’s overall happiness in life.
          
          
            Trial Registration
            ISRCTN ISRCTN14757739; https://www.isrctn.com/ISRCTN14757739
          
DOI: 10.2196/76522
ISSN: 2291-9279
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/76522-2025-08-31-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>AI as an independent second reader in detection of clinically relevant breast cancers within a population-based screening programme in the Netherlands: a retrospective cohort study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landig.2025.100882</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 96
Autoren: Suzanne L van Winkel, Jim Peters, Natasja Janssen, Jaap Kroes, Elizabeth A Loehrer, Jessie Gommers, Ioannis Sechopoulos, Linda de Munck, Jonas Teuwen, Mireille Broeders, Nico Karssemeijer, Ritse M Mann
Journal: The Lancet Digital Health
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.landig.2025.100882
ISSN: 2589-7500
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.landig.2025.100882-2025-08-31-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Personalized home based neurostimulation via AI optimization augments sustained attention</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01744-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 95
Autoren: Roi Cohen Kadosh, Delia Ciobotaru, Malin I. Karstens, Vu Nguyen
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-29
Abstract: Abstract
          Brain-based technologies for human augmentation face challenges in personalization and real-world translation. We present an AI-driven personalized Bayesian optimization algorithm that remotely adjusts neurostimulation parameters based on baseline ability and head anatomy to enhance sustained attention at home. Validated through in silico modeling and a double-blind, sham-controlled study, our approach aligns with MRI-based models and neurobiological theories, maximizing efficacy and enabling scalable, personalized cognitive enhancement and therapy in real-world settings.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01744-6
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01744-6-2025-08-31-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>