<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 01:16:52 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 01:16:52 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Mobilization with movement plus exercise versus exercise alone for patients with central sensitization associated with chronic subacromial pain syndrome: a sham-controlled randomized clinical trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 13
Autoren: Volkan Deniz, Bayram Kelle
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-28
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0-2025-08-10-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Antitumor effects of cannabidiol (CBD) on osteosarcoma by targeting TNF-α/NF-κB/CCL5 signaling axis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phymed.2025.157066</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 6
Autoren: Fan Yang, Shuqin Duan, Jingwei Liu, Zhechao An, Wangyang Liu, Xinyue Wang, Tingting Zhang, Mingyu Liu, Fengda Li, Wei Wu, Yingzhe Liu, Jianyong Tang, Xiaojuan Wang, Wenhui Xu, Wenyi Qi, Yunhe Liu, Liangliang Li, Yuan Li, Xin Liu, Baofeng Yang, Zheng Zhang, Li Wang, Lei Yang
Journal: Phytomedicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.phymed.2025.157066
ISSN: 0944-7113
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.phymed.2025.157066-2025-08-10-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A Turning Point for Homeopathy?</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1055/a-2634-8630</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 5
Autoren: Robert T. Mathie
Journal: Homeopathy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
DOI: 10.1055/a-2634-8630
ISSN: 1475-4916
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1055/a-2634-8630-2025-08-10-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Minneola tangelo essential oil exhibits antibacterial activity against multidrug-resistant pathogens while maintaining cell safety</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05015-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 3
Autoren: Nouran M. Fahmy, Haidy A. Gad, Masarra M. Sakr, Mai I. Shahin, Shaimaa Fayez
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            The significant rise in antibiotic resistance has become an alarming situation urging the search for new antibacterial agents. Nature has always been a limitless source of bioactives with high safety profile. This study evaluates the antibacterial activity of essential oils from the leaves and fruit peels of Minneola tangelo cultivated in Egypt. In vitro cytotoxicity assay was conducted to ensure the safety profile of the active essential oils.
          
          
            Methods
            The antibacterial activity of clinical isolates of Acinetobacter baumannii and methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus was assessed using the Kirby-Bauer disk diffusion method. Chemical profiling of the leaf and peel essential oils was performed using GC-MS. In vitro cytotoxicity assay of the leaf essential oil was conducted using sulforhodamine B assay. In silico docking study was conducted to explore the possible antibacterial mechanisms.
          
          
            Results
            The leaf essential oil exhibited antibacterial activity against the tested isolates, whereas the peel oil was inactive. GC-MS analysis showed differences in the chemical composition of the leaf and fruit peel oils, where 60% of the leaf oil is dominated by linalool (31.6%), cis-β-ocimene (16.1%), and γ-terpinene (14.3%), whereas the fruit peel oil is solely dominated by D-limonene (82%). Cytotoxicity assay on Caco-2 cell line showed IC50 value of 277.36 µg/mL while that on fibroblast HFB4 cell line was &amp;gt; 1000 µg/mL. In silico studies revealed high affinity of linalool to FabI, a crucial enzyme in the fatty acid biosynthesis pathway of MRSA as well as an affinity to Penicillin binding protein PBP2a. Binding of linalool to shikimate kinase of Acinetobacter baumannii was also demonstrated.
          
          
            Conclusion
            Essential oil of M. tangelo is a promising antibacterial agent against multidrug resistant strains with a high safety profile.
          
          
            Graphical abstract
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05015-5
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05015-5-2025-08-10-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Host-microbe co-metabolism system as potential targets: the promising way for natural medicine to treat atherosclerosis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60909-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 3
Autoren: Yun Wang, Ziwei Zhou, Haiping Hao, Lijuan Cao
Journal: Chinese Journal of Natural Medicines
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60909-5
ISSN: 1875-5364
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60909-5-2025-08-10-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>