<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 01:03:40 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 01:03:40 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Early meal timing attenuates high polygenic risk of obesity</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.24319</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 251
Autoren: R De la Peña‐Armada, María Rodríguez‐Martín, Hassan S. Dashti, Ana Isabel Cascales, Frank A. J. L. Scheer, Richa Saxena, Marta Garaulet
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-20
Abstract: AbstractObjectiveWe examined whether meal timing is associated with long‐term weight‐loss maintenance and whether meal timing interacts with a genome‐wide polygenic score (PRS‐BMI) on body weight‐related outcomes. We then examined the interaction of meal timing with 97 BMI‐related single‐nucleotide polymorphisms on obesity outcome.MethodsParticipants (N = 1195, mean age 41.07 [SD 12.68] years, female 80.8%, baseline mean BMI 31.32 [SD 5.53] kg/m2) were adults with overweight or obesity from the Obesity, Nutrigenetics, Timing, and Mediterranean (ONTIME) study. We developed a PRS‐BMI to assess the genetic risk for obesity and estimated the timing of the midpoint of meal intake. We also calculated the success in long‐term weight‐loss maintenance after a dietary obesity treatment (at least 3 years). Linear regression analyses were performed for association and interaction assessments.ResultsEach hour of delay in meal timing was associated with 2.2% higher long‐term body weight (β [SE] = 2.177% [1.067%]; p = 0.042) (i.e., with lower weight‐loss maintenance following dietary obesity treatment). There was a significant interaction between meal timing and PRS‐BMI (p = 0.008); BMI increased by more than 2 kg/m2 for every hour of delay in meal timing in individuals with high PRS‐BMI (β [SE] = 2.208 [0.502] kg/m2; p = 1.0E‐5), whereas no associations were evident for those with lower genetic risk.ConclusionsMeal timing is associated with weight‐loss maintenance and may influence the association between obesity genetics and BMI. Findings underscore the importance of personalized obesity management.image
DOI: 10.1002/oby.24319
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.24319-2025-08-20-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Low-fat and whole milk consumption in relation to cardiovascular disease–related and all-cause mortality: a prospective cohort study in 3 Norwegian counties</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 110
Autoren: Erik Kristoffer Arnesen, Jacob Juel Christensen, Ida Laake, Monica H Carlsen, Marit B Veierød, Kjetil Retterstøl
Journal: The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035
ISSN: 0002-9165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035-2025-08-20-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association between dairy intake and multiple health outcomes: a scoping review of systematic reviews and meta-analyses</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41430-025-01639-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 77
Autoren: Saskia Akyil, Stefanie Winkler, Dorothy Meyer, Eva Kiesswetter, Martin Kussmann, Lukas Schwingshackl, Hans Hauner
Journal: European Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-26
Abstract: Abstract
          Food-based dietary guidelines acknowledge non-fortified dairy foods as a source of multiple essential vitamins and minerals as well as high-quality protein. Considering the cultural significance of dairy foods in our diet and the increasing prevalence of non-communicable diseases, it is essential to continuously evaluate the entirety of data regarding the impact of dairy consumption on various health-related outcomes. A systematic literature search was performed in three databases: Medline, Embase, and Web of Science. Systematic reviews published between January 2014 and February 2024 based on randomized controlled trials (RCTs), prospective cohort studies, case-control studies, and/or cross-sectional studies in adults, focusing on the consumption of bovine dairy products were evaluated for inclusion. Reports from the World Cancer Research Fund on selected cancer outcomes were also included in this review. We identified 95 reports encompassing five dairy exposure categories on 29 different health outcomes. Out of 281 associations identified, 37.7% linked dairy consumption to a reduced risk, while 48.0% showed no association with disease risk. Inconclusive results were found in 10.0% of the associations, and 4.3% indicated an increased risk of adverse health outcomes. Overall, the evidence suggests that consuming dairy is not associated with an increased risk of non-communicable diseases or mortality. In fact, it may moderately reduce the risk of several health outcomes, including adverse cardiovascular outcomes and certain cancers such as bladder, breast, colorectal, liver, oral, and ovarian. Some studies have also linked dairy consumption to improved body composition, lower rates of type 2 diabetes, and better bone health.
DOI: 10.1038/s41430-025-01639-5
ISSN: 0954-3007
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41430-025-01639-5-2025-08-20-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Nutritional Epidemiology Risk–Survival Paradox</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 74
Autoren: Raphael E Cuomo
Journal: The Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020
ISSN: 0022-3166
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020-2025-08-20-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Pediatric endoscopic mucosal resection: A 10‐year single‐center experience</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/jpn3.70194</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 66
Autoren: Brett J. Hoskins, Jared M. Grabau, Douglas K. Rex
Journal: Journal of Pediatric Gastroenterology and Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-12
Abstract: ABSTRACTObjectivesEndoscopic mucosal resection (EMR) is well established in adult gastroenterology but remains underutilized in pediatrics due to limited data, training opportunities, and equipment. This study presents a 10‐year, single‐center experience with conventional hot and cold snare EMR, band‐assisted (B‐EMR), and underwater EMR (U‐EMR) techniques in pediatric patients.MethodsA retrospective review was conducted of all EMR procedures performed in patients under 21 years of age between 2015 and 2025 at a tertiary care children's hospital. Data on patient demographics, lesion characteristics, procedural details, pathology, and outcomes were collected and analyzed descriptively.ResultsTwenty EMRs were performed in 18 patients (mean age 17.1 years, range 3–20). The most common underlying diagnoses included familial adenomatous polyposis (n = 7), sporadic mucosal polyps (n = 4), subepithelial lesions (n = 4), juvenile polyposis syndrome (n = 2), Peutz‐Jeghers syndrome (n = 1), and Lynch syndrome (n = 1). Lesions ranged from 6 to 80 mm and were located throughout the gastrointestinal tract, most commonly in the colon (n = 9), duodenum (n = 5), and esophagus (n = 3). Techniques included hot snare EMR (n = 9), cold snare EMR (n = 6), B‐EMR (n = 4), and U‐EMR (n = 1). Complete resection was achieved in 95% of cases, with one incomplete resection requiring surgical management for adenocarcinoma. B‐EMR was safely applied to subepithelial lesions. No delayed complications occurred.ConclusionsEMR is feasible, safe, and effective in pediatric patients for both mucosal and subepithelial lesions. Broader adoption in pediatric practice will require expanded training, multidisciplinary collaboration, and development of pediatric‐specific guidelines. These findings support EMR as a valuable therapeutic option in complex pediatric gastrointestinal disease.
DOI: 10.1002/jpn3.70194
ISSN: 0277-2116
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/jpn3.70194-2025-08-20-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>