<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 01:13:50 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 01:13:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Prevalence and severity of symptoms across the menopause transition: cross-sectional findings from the Australian Women's Midlife Years (AMY) Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00138-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 508
Autoren: Rakibul M Islam, Molly Bond, Aida Ghalebeigi, Yuanyuan Wang, Karen Walker-Bone, Susan R Davis
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00138-x
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00138-x-2025-08-11-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Primary Aldosteronism: An Endocrine Society Clinical Practice Guideline</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1210/clinem/dgaf284</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 506
Autoren: Gail K Adler, Michael Stowasser, Ricardo R Correa, Nadia Khan, Gregory Kline, Michael J McGowan, Paolo Mulatero, M Hassan Murad, Rhian M Touyz, Anand Vaidya, Tracy A Williams, Jun Yang, William F Young, Maria-Christina Zennaro, Juan P Brito
Journal: The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp;amp; Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-14
Abstract: Abstract
               
                  Background
                  Primary aldosteronism (PA), a primary adrenal disorder leading to excessive aldosterone production by one or both adrenal glands, is a common cause of hypertension. It is associated with an increased risk of cardiovascular complications compared with primary hypertension. Despite effective methods for diagnosing and treating PA, it remains markedly underdiagnosed and undertreated.
               
               
                  Objective
                  To develop an updated guideline that provides a practical, clinical approach to identifying and managing PA to improve diagnosis rates and encourage targeted treatment.
               
               
                  Methods
                  The Guideline Development Panel (GDP), composed of a multidisciplinary panel of clinical experts and experts in systemic review methodology, used the Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) approach to define 10 questions related to the diagnosis and treatment of PA. Systematic reviews were conducted for each question. The GDP used the GRADE Evidence to Decision (EtD) framework to consider contextual factors, such as stakeholder values and preferences, costs and required resources, cost-effectiveness, acceptability, feasibility, and the potential impact on health equity.
               
               
                  Results
                  We suggest that all individuals with hypertension be screened for PA by measuring aldosterone and renin and determining the aldosterone to renin ratio, and that subsequent clinical care be guided by the results. We suggest that individuals with PA receive PA-specific therapy, either medical or surgical. In individuals who screen positive for PA, we suggest (1) commencement of PA-specific medical therapy in individuals who do not desire or are not candidates for surgery and in situations where the probability of lateralizing PA (excess aldosterone produced by one adrenal) is low based on screening results; and (2) aldosterone suppression testing in situations when screening results indicate an intermediate probability for lateralizing PA and individualized decision making confirms a desire to pursue eligibility for surgical therapy. In those who test positive by aldosterone suppression testing, and in those in whom screening results show a high probability of lateralizing PA (obviating the need for aldosterone suppression testing), we suggest adrenal lateralization with computed tomography scanning and adrenal venous sampling prior to deciding the treatment approach (medical vs surgical). In all individuals with PA and an adrenal adenoma, we suggest performing a 1-mg overnight dexamethasone suppression test. We suggest the use of mineralocorticoid receptor antagonists (MRAs) over epithelial sodium-channel (ENaC) inhibitors in the medical treatment of PA. We suggest the use of spironolactone over other MRAs, given its lower cost and greater availability; however, all MRAs, when titrated to equivalent potencies, are anticipated to have similar efficacy in treating PA. Thus, MRAs with greater mineralocorticoid receptor specificity and fewer androgen/progesterone receptor-mediated side effects may be preferred in some situations. In individuals receiving MRA therapy, we suggest monitoring renin and, in those whose hypertension remains uncontrolled and renin is suppressed, titrating the MRA to increase renin.
               
               
                  Conclusion
                  These recommendations provide a practical framework for the diagnosis and treatment of PA. They are based on currently available literature and take into consideration outcomes that are important to key stakeholders. The goal is to increase identification of individuals with PA and, by initiating PA-specific medical or surgical therapy, improve blood pressure control and reduce PA-associated adverse cardiovascular events. The guidelines also highlight important knowledge gaps in PA diagnosis and management.
               
DOI: 10.1210/clinem/dgaf284
ISSN: 0021-972X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1210/clinem/dgaf284-2025-08-11-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The role of ultra-processed food in obesity</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41574-025-01143-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 505
Autoren: Filippa Juul, Euridice Martinez-Steele, Niyati Parekh, Carlos A. Monteiro
Journal: Nature Reviews Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-14
DOI: 10.1038/s41574-025-01143-7
ISSN: 1759-5029
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41574-025-01143-7-2025-08-11-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Non-autoimmune, insulin-deficient diabetes in children and young adults in Africa: evidence from the Young-Onset Diabetes in sub-Saharan Africa (YODA) cross-sectional study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00120-2</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 341
Autoren: Jean Claude Katte, Steven Squires, Mesmin Y Dehayem, Priscilla A Balungi, Carolyn J Padoa, Dhriti Sengupta, Segun Fatumo, Thereza Piloya, Catherine Nyangabyaki-Twesigye, Silver Bahendeka, Edna Majaliwa, Kandi C Muze, Kaushik Ramaiya, Suzanne Sap, Ayesha A Motala, Fraser J Pirie, Paul Rheeder, Jacobus C Van Dyk, Jean Claude Mbanya, Beverley M Shields, Amy S Shah, Catherine Pihoker, Jasmin Divers, Kashyap A Patel, Richard A Oram, Dana Dabelea, Andrew T Hattersley, Timothy J McDonald, Nigel J Crowther, Moffat J Nyirenda, Eugene Sobngwi, Angus G Jones
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00120-2
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00120-2-2025-08-11-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Standardization of TSH and FT4 to gestational age in early pregnancy and associations with clinical outcomes</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1530/etj-24-0344</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 266
Autoren: Joris A J Osinga, Layal Chaker, Sjoerd van den Berg, Vincent W V Jaddoe, Eric A P Steegers, Henning Tiemeier, Robin P Peeters, Tim Korevaar
Journal: European Thyroid Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-15
Abstract: 
Background
To account for pregnancy-specific changes in thyroid physiology, international guidelines recommend the use of trimester-specific reference intervals. However, the pragmatic division in trimesters does not necessarily align with the changes in thyroid physiology. While the goal of treating gestational thyroid dysfunction is to prevent thyroid hormone-mediated adverse events, it remains unclear which method of standardizing to gestational age, if any, is most effective in identifying individuals at higher risk of adverse pregnancy events.


Methods
We included 5,675 women participating in a population-based prospective cohort with data on thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH), free thyroxine (FT4) and thyroperoxidase antibodies (TPOAbs) during early pregnancy (median: 13.2 weeks, 95% range: 9.8–17.6). We studied the association of TSH and FT4 with pre-eclampsia, premature delivery, birth weight and offspring IQ with or without full gestational age standardization of TSH and FT4 using multivariable regression models.


Results
There was a positive association of gestational age at blood sampling with TSH (difference in mean TSH: +9.6%; P &amp;lt; 0.001) and a negative association with FT4 (difference in mean FT4: −20.2%; P &amp;lt; 0.001). Standardizing TSH to gestational age led to reclassification of 36 women as having normal TSH (9.9%) and 27 as having abnormal TSH (0.5%). For FT4, 62 women were reclassified as having normal FT4 (20.3%) and 57 as having abnormal FT4 (1.1%). Standardization of TSH and FT4 concentrations led to an attenuation of the associations with any outcome of up to 71% as compared to non-standardized TSH or FT4.


Conclusions
Full standardization of TSH and FT4 to gestational age either does not affect or weakens their associations with clinical outcomes, suggesting that accounting for gestational age offers no benefit with regard to identifying high-risk thyroid dysfunction during early pregnancy.

DOI: 10.1530/etj-24-0344
ISSN: 2235-0640
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1530/etj-24-0344-2025-08-11-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>