<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 01:07:08 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 01:07:08 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of Computerized Cognitive Training on Vesicular Acetylcholine Transporter Levels using [18F]Fluoroethoxybenzovesamicol Positron Emission Tomography in Healthy Older Adults: Results from the Improving Neurological Health in Aging via Neuroplasticity-based Computerized Exercise (INHANCE) Randomized Clinical Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/75161</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 303
Autoren: Mouna Attarha, Ana de Figueiredo Pelegrino, Lydia Ouellet, Paule-Joanne Toussaint, Sarah-Jane Grant, Thomas Van Vleet, Etienne de Villers-Sidani
Journal: JMIR Serious Games
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-13
Abstract: 
            Background
            The cholinergic system mediates essential aspects of cognitive function, yet its structure and function decline progressively with age, by an estimated 2.5% per decade across the lifespan. Cognitive training may help counteract age-related declines in cholinergic functioning and slow associated deficits in cognitive performance.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aims to evaluate whether cognitive training modifies cholinergic binding in older adults.
          
          
            Methods
            The Improving Neurological Health in Aging via Neuroplasticity-based Computerized Exercise (INHANCE) trial is a double-blind randomized controlled trial assessing whether 2 computerized cognitive training programs modify cholinergic expression. The intent-to-treat (ITT) population included 92 community-dwelling healthy older adults aged 65 and above (enrolled July 2021-December 2023; final follow-up June 2024). Participants were randomized at McGill University to either an intervention of speed-based cognitive training exercises designed to improve the speed and accuracy of information processing or an active control of nonspeeded games designed for entertainment (eg, similar in design to Solitaire). Participants completed 35 hours of training on their assigned program at home over a 10-week period using a loaned or personal internet-connected device. Cholinergic binding was measured with the vesicular acetylcholine transporter ligand [18F]fluoroethoxybenzovesamicol (FEOBV) and positron emission tomography (PET). The primary outcome was mean FEOBV binding (standard uptake value ratios [SUVRs]) within the anterior cingulate cortex from baseline to posttest in the ITT population. All other end points were exploratory.
          
          
            Results
            Among the 92 participants in the ITT population (mean age 71.9 years; mean education 16.5 years; 61/92, 66%, women; 88/92, 96%, White), 82 (89%) completed all study activities. The speed-based intervention showed a significant within-group increase in FEOBV binding in the primary region of interest, the anterior cingulate cortex (SUVR change mean +0.044, 95% CI 0.006-0.082, P=.03, medium effect size, ω²=0.09). The p24c subregion demonstrated a significant between-groups effect favoring speed training (speeded vs nonspeeded SUVR change difference +0.058, 95% CI 0.007-0.110, P=.03, small effect size, ω²=0.05). Prespecified exploratory analyses revealed significant within-group effects for speed training in the hippocampus (P=.02) and parahippocampal gyrus (P=.04). No effects on FEOBV binding were observed in the active control group.
          
          
            Conclusions
            INHANCE is the largest FEOBV-PET trial to date and demonstrates, for the first time in humans, that speed training can reverse losses in cholinergic terminal densities in brain regions vulnerable to age-related cognitive decline. The 2.3% gain in FEOBV binding in the anterior cingulate achieved over a 10-week intervention may offset the estimated 2.5% decline typically observed over a decade of natural aging. These findings clarify the neurochemical basis of cognitive training benefits, showing that speed training upregulates binding in networks that support attention, memory, and executive function.
          
          
            Trial Registration
            ClinicalTrials.gov NCT04149457; https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT04149457
          
          
            International Registered Report Identifier (IRRID)
            RR2-10.2196/59705
          
DOI: 10.2196/75161
ISSN: 2291-9279
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/75161-2025-10-20-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of a Smartphone-Based Positive Reflection Diary on Work Engagement Among Japanese Workers: Randomized Controlled Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/55664</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 82
Autoren: Masahito Tokita, Shuichiro Kobayashi, Daisuke Miyanaka, Nobuyuki Takate, Hiroyuki Nakano, Kazuki Takeuchi, Akihito Shimazu
Journal: JMIR mHealth and uHealth
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-25
Abstract: 
            Abstract 
          
          
            Background
            Work engagement is an important determinant of workers’ well-being. According to the job demands–resources model, personal resources are one of the key antecedents of work engagement. Enhancing personal resources leads to improved work engagement. Furthermore, reflecting positively on one’s achievements at work may enhance personal resources. Hence, there is a need for a simple, self-guided tool such as a smartphone app that can be used by employees to record and reflect on their work accomplishments.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aimed to evaluate the effect of a smartphone-based diary (ie, Work Engagement Diary) that promotes positive reflection in daily working life on work engagement among Japanese workers in a randomized controlled trial.
          
          
            Methods
            Six hundred Japanese workers who met the inclusion criteria were randomly allocated to either the intervention group or the wait-list control group (300 participants each) via a web survey company. Participants in the intervention group kept the Work Engagement Diary for 2 weeks, whereby they were required to set a weekly goal at the beginning of the week and fill in their work achievements at the end of the day. Those in the waitlist control group did not receive any interventions until they completed a follow-up survey. Work engagement was assessed at preintervention (T1), postintervention (T2), and 3 weeks after intervention (T3) in both groups.
          
          
            Results
            A mixed model for repeated measures conditional growth model analysis using intention-to-treat revealed a significant improvement in work engagement for the intervention group compared to the wait-list control group throughout the study period (P=.04). Effect sizes were small in work engagement for T1 versus T2 (Cohen d=0.11 [95% CI −0.06 to 0.28]) and for T1 versus T3 (Cohen d=0.12 [95% CI −0.06 to 0.28]).
          
          
            Conclusions
            This randomized controlled trial demonstrated that our newly developed smartphone-based positive reflection diary at work effectively improved work engagement among Japanese workers. Future research needs to clarify longer-term intervention effects and detailed mechanisms of the intervention effects.
          
DOI: 10.2196/55664
ISSN: 2291-5222
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/55664-2025-10-20-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Research Implications of Increased Political Oversight in the United States</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/83499</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 47
Autoren: Kayleigh-Ann Clegg
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-19
DOI: 10.2196/83499
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/83499-2025-10-20-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Virtual Transition of Care Clinics and Associated Readmission Rates: 3-Year Retrospective Cohort Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/73495</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 44
Autoren: Sarah F Horman, Milla Kviatkovsky, Edward Castillo, Patricia Maysent, Chad VanDenBerg, John Bell, Christopher A Longhurst
Journal: JMIR Medical Informatics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-23
Abstract: 
            Background
            Hospital readmissions pose a significant burden on patients, health care providers, and systems, with an estimated annual cost of $17 billion. Timely follow-up within 7 days postdischarge is known to reduce readmissions but is often limited by access constraints. While transitions of care clinics have demonstrated benefits in reducing unplanned readmissions, physical space requirements can be logistically and financially challenging.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aimed to evaluate the effectiveness of a virtual transitions of care (VToC) clinic in reducing 30-day hospital readmissions and improving postdischarge care coordination.
          
          
            Methods
            University of California, San Diego Health implemented a hospitalist-led VToC clinic designed to support clinical management, medication reconciliation, primary care provider repatriation, and specialty care navigation. The study included 2314 patients seen in the VToC clinic between September 2021 and September 2024. Outcomes were compared to a benchmark group using regression analysis to assess the impact on 30-day readmission rates.
          
          
            Results
            The 30-day readmission rate for VToC patients was 14.9% (344/2314), significantly lower than the 20.1% (4659/23,129) observed in the benchmark group (P&amp;lt;.001). Regression analysis indicated that patients not participating in the VToC clinic had a higher likelihood of readmission (odds ratio=1.37; 95% CI=1.21-1.54; P&amp;lt;.001). The most substantial reduction in readmissions was observed among patients with moderate readmission risk (LACE+ score of 50-75).
          
          
            Conclusions
            VToC clinics are a feasible and effective strategy for enhancing postdischarge care, reducing hospital readmissions, and improving care coordination. This model supports the quadruple aim by promoting better health outcomes, improved patient experience, cost-efficiency, and care equity.
          
DOI: 10.2196/73495
ISSN: 2291-9694
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/73495-2025-10-20-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Quality safety and disparity of an AI chatbot in managing chronic diseases: simulated patient experiments</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01956-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 43
Autoren: Yafei Si, Yurun Meng, Xi Chen, Ruopeng An, Limin Mao, Bingqin Li, Hazel Bateman, Han Zhang, Hongbin Fan, Jiaqi Zu, Shaoqing Gong, Zhongliang Zhou, Yudong Miao, Xiaojing Fan, Gang Chen
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-25
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01956-w
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01956-w-2025-10-20-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>