<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:07:20 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:07:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Nanobodies: a new paradigm for brain disorder therapies</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2025.10.004</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 468
Autoren: Pierre-André Lafon, Laurent Prézeau, Jean-Philippe Pin, Philippe Rondard
Journal: Trends in Pharmacological Sciences
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tips.2025.10.004
ISSN: 0165-6147
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tips.2025.10.004-2025-11-25-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>MCH11, a new monoacylglycerol lipase inhibitor, reduces ethanol consumption and motivation to drink in mice, with sex-dependent differences</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118662</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 152
Autoren: Abraham B. Torregrosa, María S. García-Gutiérrez, Daniela Navarro, Francisco Navarrete, Jorge Manzanares
Journal: Biomedicine &amp;amp; Pharmacotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118662
ISSN: 0753-3322
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118662-2025-11-25-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mass balance, pharmacokinetics, metabolism, and excretion of radiolabeled acoziborole, a potential novel treatment for human African trypanosomiasis, following single microtracer oral dose to humans</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.00580-25</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 142
Autoren: Jean-Yves Gillon, François Simon, Sharan Sidhu, Mathieu Louis, Delphine Launay, Valérie Wauthier, Marta Pelay-Gimeno, Lotte van Andel, Sabrina Loyau, Sandra Rembry, Estelle Weinling, Antoine Tarral
Journal: Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-05
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    
                    
                      Acoziborole is an oxaborole 6-carboxamide active against
                      Trypanosoma brucei gambiense
                      and
                      rhodesiense
                      , the parasites responsible for human African trypanosomiasis. This open-label, phase I study in six healthy male participants evaluated the mass balance, pharmacokinetics, metabolism pathways, and excretion of a single oral 960 mg dose of [
                      14
                      C]-acoziborole. Blood, plasma, and feces were collected for 120 days and urine for 16 days. The excretion balance and systemic exposure of total circulating radioactivity were determined using accelerator mass spectrometry. Metabolism profiling was performed in pools of plasma, urine, and feces. Liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry quantified acoziborole and its metabolite SCYX-3109 in plasma and urine. By Day 60, 87.3% of the total radioactivity had been recovered (10.9% and 74.2% of the total dose in urine and in feces, respectively), with an excretion increment of &amp;lt;1% between Days 59 and 61. Mean ratios of total radioactivity indicated an equivalent distribution between blood cells and plasma. The concentration-time profiles of total radioactivity and acoziborole in plasma were similar. In plasma, acoziborole accounted for 95.1%, an oxidized form of acoziborole for 2.3% of the total radioactivity, while SCYX-3109 was not detected. Seven metabolites (oxidative deboronation, glucuronidation, and mono-oxidation) were detected in urine with individual abundances relative to the dose of 0.1–2.1%; unchanged acoziborole accounted for 0.6%. In feces, acoziborole, SCYX-3109, and two other oxidized or deboronated forms of acoziborole represented 33.6%, 12.3%, and 2.3% of the dose, respectively. Acoziborole showed good absorption, limited metabolism, minimal urinary elimination, and predominant but slow biliary-fecal elimination.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1128/aac.00580-25
ISSN: 0066-4804
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1128/aac.00580-25-2025-11-25-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Liposomal-synthetic-cannabidiol: preliminary translational evidence of efficacy, tolerability and pharmacokinetics following repeated subcutaneous injections in two goats</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2025.1689226</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 117
Autoren: Yael Shilo-Benjamini, Wiessam Abu Ahmad, Dinorah Barasch, Eran Lavy, Daniel Zilbersheid, Yechezkel Barenholz, Ahuva Cern
Journal: Frontiers in Pharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-10
Abstract: 
                    Cannabidiol (CBD), the primary non-psychoactive component of
                    Cannabis sativa
                    , has been gaining popularity as an analgesic in treatment of chronic painful conditions. Due to first-pass hepatic metabolism, oral CBD is considered to have low bioavailability. Our previous studies on dogs indicate that synthetic CBD encapsulation in liposomes facilitates controlled drug release and provides long-term CBD plasma concentrations. In the present study, liposomal CBD (5 mg/kg) was repeatedly injected subcutaneously in two goats, due to suspected pain and deterioration in quality of life (QoL). Blood samples were collected for assessment of plasma concentrations, complete blood count (CBC), and biochemical analysis before and up to 6 weeks after each injection. Efficacy was assessed by the caregivers via QoL weekly scoring, and adverse effects were monitored. A total of 14 injections were administered. No adverse effects were recorded, nor were significant changes observed in CBC and biochemistry. The CBD peak plasma concentration (C
                    max
                    ) was 4.4–28.2 ng/mL, while its primary metabolite, 7-carboxy-CBD (7-COOH-CBD), was much higher (129–1,524 ng/mL), similar to those in reports of humans. The time to C
                    max
                    and half-life of CBD were 0.25–21 and 5.1–24.2 days, respectively, and those in 7-COOH-CBD were 3–28 and 5.6–24.5 days, respectively. The concentration–time curves flattened with repeated injections. QoL improvement was observed for 4 weeks following injections. The results of this study offer clinically translatable information. Liposomal CBD injections every 6 weeks are practical, have no adverse effects, and provide long-term CBD and 7-COOH-CBD concentrations that approach steady-state concentrations over time. Additionally, liposomal CBD demonstrated remarkable efficacy in pain control and wellbeing improvement for several weeks and can potentially provide similar results in humans.
                  
DOI: 10.3389/fphar.2025.1689226
ISSN: 1663-9812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fphar.2025.1689226-2025-11-25-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The continued impact of COVID-19 during the Omicron era on immunocompromised individuals in Japan</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 109
Autoren: Toshibumi Taniguchi, Mitsuru Hoshino, Ryotaro Ide, Tomoyuki Homma, Keiji Sugiyama, Shinichi Kanazu, Atsushi Maruyama, Kazuhiro Tateda
Journal: Journal of Infection and Chemotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840
ISSN: 1341-321X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840-2025-11-25-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>