<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 01:06:01 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 01:06:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Detecting, Characterizing, and Mitigating Implicit and Explicit Racial Biases in Health Care Datasets With Subgroup Learnability: Algorithm Development and Validation Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/71757</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 77
Autoren: Faris Gulamali, Ashwin Shreekant Sawant, Lora Liharska, Carol Horowitz, Lili Chan, Ira Hofer, Karandeep Singh, Lynne Richardson, Emmanuel Mensah, Alexander Charney, David Reich, Jianying Hu, Girish Nadkarni
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-04
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            The growing adoption of diagnostic and prognostic algorithms in health care has led to concerns about the perpetuation of algorithmic bias against disadvantaged groups of individuals. Deep learning methods to detect and mitigate bias have revolved around modifying models, optimization strategies, and threshold calibration with varying levels of success and tradeoffs. However, there have been limited substantive efforts to address bias at the level of the data used to generate algorithms in health care datasets.
          
          
            Objective
            The aim of this study is to create a simple metric (AEquity) that uses a learning curve approximation to distinguish and mitigate bias via guided dataset collection or relabeling.
          
          
            Methods
            We demonstrate this metric in 2 well-known examples, chest X-rays and health care cost utilization, and detect novel biases in the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey.
          
          
            Results
            We demonstrated that using AEquity to guide data-centric collection for each diagnostic finding in the chest radiograph dataset decreased bias by between 29% and 96.5% when measured by differences in area under the curve. Next, we wanted to examine (1) whether AEquity worked on intersectional populations and (2) if AEquity is invariant to different types of fairness metrics, not just area under the curve. Subsequently, we examined the effect of AEquity on mitigating bias when measured by false negative rate, precision, and false discovery rate for Black patients on Medicaid. When we examined Black patients on Medicaid, at the intersection of race and socioeconomic status, we found that AEquity-based interventions reduced bias across a number of different fairness metrics including overall false negative rate by 33.3% (bias reduction absolute=1.88×10−1, 95% CI 1.4×10−1 to 2.5×10−1; bias reduction of 33.3%, 95% CI 26.6%‐40%; precision bias by 7.50×10−2, 95% CI 7.48×10−2 to 7.51×10−2; bias reduction of 94.6%, 95% CI 94.5%‐94.7%; false discovery rate by 94.5%; absolute bias reduction=3.50×10−2, 95% CI 3.49×10−2 to 3.50×10−2). Similarly, AEquity-guided data collection demonstrated bias reduction of up to 80% on mortality prediction with the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (bias reduction absolute=0.08, 95% CI 0.07-0.09). Then, we wanted to compare AEquity to state-of-the-art data-guided debiasing measures such as balanced empirical risk minimization and calibration. Consequently, we benchmarked against balanced empirical risk minimization and calibration and showed that AEquity-guided data collection outperforms both standard approaches. Moreover, we demonstrated that AEquity works on fully connected networks; convolutional neural networks such as ResNet-50; transformer architectures such as VIT-B-16, a vision transformer with 86 million parameters; and nonparametric methods such as Light Gradient-Boosting Machine.
          
          
            Conclusions
            In short, we demonstrated that AEquity is a robust tool by applying it to different datasets, algorithms, and intersectional analyses and measuring its effectiveness with respect to a range of traditional fairness metrics.
          
DOI: 10.2196/71757
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/71757-2025-10-05-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Research Implications of Increased Political Oversight in the United States</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/83499</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 47
Autoren: Kayleigh-Ann Clegg
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-19
DOI: 10.2196/83499
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/83499-2025-10-05-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New Doc on the Block: Scoping Review of AI Systems Delivering Motivational Interviewing for Health Behavior Change</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/78417</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 43
Autoren: Zev Karve, Jacob Calpey, Christopher Machado, Michelle Knecht, Maria Carmenza Mejia
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-16
Abstract: 
            Background
            Artificial intelligence (AI) is increasingly used in digital health, particularly through large language models (LLMs), to support patient engagement and behavior change. One novel application is the delivery of motivational interviewing (MI), an evidence-based, patient-centered counseling technique designed to enhance motivation and resolve ambivalence around health behaviors. AI tools, including chatbots, mobile apps, and web-based agents, are being developed to simulate MI techniques at scale. While these innovations are promising, important questions remain about how faithfully AI systems can replicate MI principles or achieve meaningful behavioral impact.
          
          
            Objective
            This scoping review aimed to summarize existing empirical studies evaluating AI-driven systems that apply MI techniques to support health behavior change. Specifically, we examined the feasibility of these systems; their fidelity to MI principles; and their reported behavioral, psychological, or engagement outcomes.
          
          
            Methods
            We systematically searched PubMed, Embase, Scopus, Web of Science, and Cochrane Library for empirical studies published between January 1, 2018, and February 25, 2025. Eligible studies involved AI-driven systems using natural language generation, understanding, or computational logic to deliver MI techniques to users targeting a specific health behavior. We excluded studies using AI solely for training clinicians in MI. Three independent reviewers screened and extracted data on study design, AI modality and type, MI components, health behavior focus, MI fidelity assessment, and outcome domains.
          
          
            Results
            Of the 1001 records identified, 15 (1.5%) met the inclusion criteria. Of these 15 studies, 6 (40%) were exploratory feasibility or pilot studies, and 3 (20%) were randomized controlled trials. AI modalities included rule-based chatbots (9/15, 60%), LLM-based systems (4/15, 27%), and virtual or mobile agents (2/15, 13%). Targeted behaviors included smoking cessation (6/15, 40%), substance use (3/15, 20%), COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy, type 2 diabetes self-management, stress, mental health service use, and opioid use during pregnancy. Of the 15 studies, 13 (87%) reported positive findings on feasibility or user acceptability, while 6 (40%) assessed MI fidelity using expert review or structured coding, with moderate to high alignment reported. Several studies found that users perceived the AI systems as judgment free, supportive, and easier to engage with than human counselors, particularly in stigmatized contexts. However, limitations in empathy, safety transparency, and emotional nuance were commonly noted. Only 3 (20%) of the 15 studies reported substantially significant behavioral changes.
          
          
            Conclusions
            AI systems delivering MI show promise for enhancing patient engagement and scaling behavior change interventions. Early evidence supports their usability and partial fidelity to MI principles, especially in sensitive domains. However, most systems remain in early development, and few have been rigorously tested. Future research should prioritize randomized evaluations; standardized fidelity measures; and safeguards for LLM safety, empathy, and accuracy in health-related dialogue.
          
          
            Trial Registration
            OSF Registries 10.17605/OSF.IO/G9N7E; https://osf.io/g9n7e
          
DOI: 10.2196/78417
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/78417-2025-10-05-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Demographic and Socioeconomic Disparities in Telemedicine Use Among Individuals With Type 2 Diabetes in Primary Care: Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/73113</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 34
Autoren: Nawwarah Alfarwan, Maria Panagioti, Alexander Hodkinson, Lamiece Hassan, Salwa S Zghebi, Evangelos Kontopantelis
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-09
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Telemedicine has revolutionized the management of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) in primary care by improving access to health care services and enhancing health outcomes. Despite these advancements, it remains unclear whether telemedicine has reduced access inequalities among different demographic and socioeconomic groups.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aimed to investigate the most important demographic and socioeconomic factors associated with telemedicine use among individuals with T2DM in primary care.
          
          
            Methods
            We conducted a systematic review and meta-analysis. Databases including MEDLINE, Embase, PsycINFO, Google Scholar, Scopus, and CINAHL were searched from inception to December 2023. The reference lists of eligible studies and other relevant systematic reviews were also searched. We included observational and cohort studies that assessed the effects of telemedicine interventions on individuals with T2DM in primary care. The core outcomes were the factors associated with telemedicine use, reported as adjusted odds ratios and 95% CIs for each factor, using a random-effects model. Heterogeneity was quantified using the I² statistic, and publication bias was assessed. The protocol for this review was registered with PROSPERO (CRD42024550410).
          
          
            Results
            Of the 3006 records identified, 16 studies involving 71,336 patients were included in the meta-analysis. Female patients had higher odds of using telemedicine than males (pooled adjusted odds ratio [OR] 1.05, 95% CI 1.02-1.09). Older patients were significantly less likely to use telemedicine than younger patients (pooled OR 0.979, 95% CI 0.98-0.98). Compared with White patients, Black patients were less likely to use telemedicine (pooled OR 0.55, 95% CI 0.32-0.94), while no statistically significant differences were observed for Hispanic (pooled OR 1.075, 95% CI 0.36-3.24) or Asian participants (pooled OR 0.56, 95% CI 0.29-1.06). Patients with higher education levels had greater odds of using telemedicine than those with lower education levels (pooled OR 1.681, 95% CI 1.48-1.91).
          
          
            Conclusions
            This systematic review and meta-analysis provide evidence of significant disparities in telemedicine use among men, older adults, Black individuals, and those with lower levels of education who have T2DM in primary care. Given that these groups are among the most vulnerable to T2DM, these disparities highlight the critical need for strategic interventions and robust policies that ensure telemedicine fosters equitable access to health care while preventing further exacerbation of existing health inequalities.
          
DOI: 10.2196/73113
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/73113-2025-10-05-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Virtual Transition of Care Clinics and Associated Readmission Rates: 3-Year Retrospective Cohort Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/73495</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 31
Autoren: Sarah F Horman, Milla Kviatkovsky, Edward Castillo, Patricia Maysent, Chad VanDenBerg, John Bell, Christopher A Longhurst
Journal: JMIR Medical Informatics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-23
Abstract: 
            Background
            Hospital readmissions pose a significant burden on patients, health care providers, and systems, with an estimated annual cost of $17 billion. Timely follow-up within 7 days postdischarge is known to reduce readmissions but is often limited by access constraints. While transitions of care clinics have demonstrated benefits in reducing unplanned readmissions, physical space requirements can be logistically and financially challenging.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aimed to evaluate the effectiveness of a virtual transitions of care (VToC) clinic in reducing 30-day hospital readmissions and improving postdischarge care coordination.
          
          
            Methods
            University of California, San Diego Health implemented a hospitalist-led VToC clinic designed to support clinical management, medication reconciliation, primary care provider repatriation, and specialty care navigation. The study included 2314 patients seen in the VToC clinic between September 2021 and September 2024. Outcomes were compared to a benchmark group using regression analysis to assess the impact on 30-day readmission rates.
          
          
            Results
            The 30-day readmission rate for VToC patients was 14.9% (344/2314), significantly lower than the 20.1% (4659/23,129) observed in the benchmark group (P&amp;lt;.001). Regression analysis indicated that patients not participating in the VToC clinic had a higher likelihood of readmission (odds ratio=1.37; 95% CI=1.21-1.54; P&amp;lt;.001). The most substantial reduction in readmissions was observed among patients with moderate readmission risk (LACE+ score of 50-75).
          
          
            Conclusions
            VToC clinics are a feasible and effective strategy for enhancing postdischarge care, reducing hospital readmissions, and improving care coordination. This model supports the quadruple aim by promoting better health outcomes, improved patient experience, cost-efficiency, and care equity.
          
DOI: 10.2196/73495
ISSN: 2291-9694
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/73495-2025-10-05-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>