<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:59:12 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:59:12 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Global, regional, and national cascades of diabetes care, 2000–23: a systematic review and modelling analysis using findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00217-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 1160
Autoren: Lauryn K Stafford, Anna Gage, Yvonne Yiru Xu, Madeleine Conrad, Ismael Barreras Beltran, Edward J Boyko, Bruce B Duncan, Simon I Hay, Hailey Lenox, Rafael Lozano, Dianna J Magliano, Carlos A Aguilar Salinas, Nikhil Tandon, Pedro Zitko, Christopher J L Murray, Theo Vos, Annie Haakenstad, Kanyin Liane Ong
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00217-7
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00217-7-2025-10-02-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Fructose and glucose from sugary drinks enhance colorectal cancer metastasis via SORD</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s42255-025-01368-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 574
Autoren: Tianshi Feng, Qin Luo, Yanlin Liu, Zeyu Jin, David Skwarchuk, Rumi Lee, Miso Nam, John M. Asara, Daya R. Adye, Philip L. Lorenzi, Lin Tan, Guangsheng Pei, Zhongming Zhao, Neda Zarrin-Khameh, Adriana Paulucci-Holthauzen, Brian W. Simons, Ju-Seog Lee, Scott Kopetz, Jihye Yun
Journal: Nature Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-19
Abstract: Abstract
          The consumption of sugar-sweetened beverages (SSBs), which contain high levels of fructose and glucose, has been causally and mechanistically linked to an increased risk of colorectal cancer (CRC). However, the effects of SSB consumption on advanced stages of disease progression, including metastasis, remain poorly understood. Here we show that exposure of CRC cells to a glucose and fructose formulation—reflecting the composition of both high-fructose corn syrup and sucrose found in SSBs—enhances cellular motility and metastatic potential compared to glucose alone. Given that CRC cells grow poorly in fructose alone, and cells in vivo are not physiologically exposed to fructose without glucose, we excluded the fructose-only condition from our studies unless needed as a control. Mechanistically, the combination of glucose and fructose elevates the NAD⁺/NADH ratio by activation of the reverse reaction of sorbitol dehydrogenase in the polyol pathway. This redox shift relieves NAD⁺ limitations and accelerates glycolytic activity, which in turn fuels activation of the mevalonate pathway, ultimately promoting CRC cell motility and metastasis. Our findings highlight the detrimental impact of SSBs on CRC progression and suggest potential dietary and therapeutic strategies to mitigate metastasis in patients with CRC.
DOI: 10.1038/s42255-025-01368-w
ISSN: 2522-5812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s42255-025-01368-w-2025-10-02-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Once-weekly semaglutide 7·2 mg in adults with obesity (STEP UP): a randomised, controlled, phase 3b trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00226-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 558
Autoren: Sean Wharton, Paula Freitas, Jøran Hjelmesæth, Maria Kabisch, Kristian Kandler, Ildiko Lingvay, Maria Quiroga, Julio Rosenstock, W Timothy Garvey
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00226-8
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00226-8-2025-10-02-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association of metformin treatment with changes in metal dynamics in individuals with type 2 diabetes</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 343
Autoren: Natsu Otowa-Suematsu, Kazuhiko Sakaguchi, Tomoko Yamada, Marika Nishisaka, Yasuko Morita, Hayato Fukumitsu, Yukari Katsura, Yuko Okada, Yushi Hirota, Kenji Sugawara, Wataru Ogawa
Journal: BMJ Open Diabetes Research &amp;amp; Care
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-31
Abstract: 
                  Introduction
                  The metal-chelating activity of metformin, which has long been known but of unclear clinical relevance, has recently been implicated in the pleiotropic effects, including antitumorigenic and anti-inflammatory actions, of the drug. However, whether metformin actually influences metal dynamics in humans has remained unknown. We here investigate whether metformin influences serum metal levels in individuals with type 2 diabetes.
               
               
                  Research design and methods
                  In this cross-sectional study, individuals with type 2 diabetes treated or not treated with metformin for at least 6 months were recruited. The primary outcome was the difference in serum copper concentration between metformin users and non-users. Secondary outcomes included differences in serum levels of iron, zinc, and vitamin B12 as well as in copper-related and iron-related parameters between the two groups.
               
               
                  Results
                  A total of 189 individuals (93 metformin users and 96 non-users) were analyzed. Metformin users showed significantly lower serum copper (16.0 vs 17.8 µmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) and iron levels (16.3 vs 17.3 µmol/L, p=0.02) and higher zinc levels (13.3 vs 12.5 µmol/L, p=0.01) compared with non-users. Copper-related and iron-related parameters for metformin users were consistent with latent deficiencies of these metals. Serum homocysteine levels (12.2 vs 11.2 µmol/L, p=0.03) were significantly higher, whereas vitamin B12 levels (338.7 vs 412.8 pmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) were significantly lower, in metformin users. Multiple regression analysis including variables that potentially influence metal dynamics identified metformin use as an independent predictor of serum copper (B = –1.54 µmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) and iron levels (B = –2.49 µmol/L, p=0.004).
               
               
                  Conclusions
                  Metformin use was associated with reduced serum levels of copper and iron, as well as with increased serum zinc levels. These changes in metal dynamics may be related to the pharmacological effects of this widely administered drug.
               
DOI: 10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255
ISSN: 2052-4897
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255-2025-10-02-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Emotion regulation strategies differentially impact memory in hormonal contraceptive users</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yhbeh.2025.105805</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 327
Autoren: Beatriz M. Brandao, Madelyn Castro, Jacob B. Buergler, Kayla R. Clark, Bryan T. Denny, Stephanie L. Leal
Journal: Hormones and Behavior
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.yhbeh.2025.105805
ISSN: 0018-506X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.yhbeh.2025.105805-2025-10-02-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>