<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 01:05:44 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 01:05:44 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of Exercise Snacks on Cardiometabolic Health and Body Composition in Adults: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/sms.70114</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 561
Autoren: Ke‐wen Wan, Zi‐han Dai, Po‐san Wong, Wendy Y. Huang, Evander Fung‐chau Lei, Jonathan P. Little, Feng‐Chang Lin, Bjorn T. Tam
Journal: Scandinavian Journal of Medicine &amp;amp; Science in Sports
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
Abstract: ABSTRACTThis systematic review and meta‐analysis aims to investigate the impact of exercise snacks (ExSn), which involve incorporating short bursts of high‐intensity physical activity into daily routines, on improving cardiometabolic health and body composition in adults. Six online databases [PubMed, Web of Science, Embase, Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (CENTRAL), CINAHL, and Scopus] were searched from inception through 22 May 2025, and relevant randomized controlled trials (RCTs) and non‐randomized controlled trials (non‐RCTs) were identified. Outcomes were analyzed using standardized mean differences and mean differences with 95% confidence intervals. Subgroup analyses were conducted based on physical activity levels and duration for each bout of ExSn. The GRADE scale was used to assess evidence certainty, while the revised Cochrane risk‐of‐bias tool (RoB 2) was used to evaluate the quality of RCTs, and the Risk of Bias In Non‐randomized Studies of Interventions (ROBINS‐I) tool was used for non‐RCTs. Twelve RCTs and two non‐RCTs, involving a total of 483 adults, were selected for the systematic review; 13 studies were included in the meta‐analysis. Among the RCTs, 2 studies showed a high risk of bias, and 10 showed some concerns. For the non‐RCTs, 1 study had a moderate risk of bias, and 1 had a serious risk of bias. The ExSn group showed significant improvements in maximal oxygen uptake (SMD = 1.43, 95% CI 0.61 to 2.25, p &amp;lt; 0.001) and peak power output (SMD = 0.68, 95% CI 0.00 to 1.36, p = 0.050), and reductions in total cholesterol (SMD = −0.65, 95% CI −1.18 to −0.11, p = 0.018) and LDL cholesterol (SMD = −0.65, 95% CI −1.22 to −0.09, p = 0.023). No significant differences were found for body weight, body fat, HDL cholesterol, or triglycerides. ExSn significantly enhances cardiometabolic health, especially in physically inactive adults. As a novel, time‐efficient approach, ExSn can be easily integrated into daily routines, offering a practical solution for sedentary and inactive individuals or those with limited time. These findings highlight its potential as a widely applicable public health strategy, warranting further research on long‐term effects and broader applications.PROSPERO Registration Number: CRD42024554446
DOI: 10.1111/sms.70114
ISSN: 0905-7188
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/sms.70114-2025-09-22-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Neurodegenerative Diseases in Male Former First-Class New Zealand Rugby Players</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s40279-025-02299-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 405
Autoren: Francesca Anns, Kenneth L. Quarrie, Barry J. Milne, Chao Li, Andrew J. Gardner, Ian R. Murphy, Evert Verhagen, Craig Wright, Susan M. B. Morton, Thomas Lumley, Lynette Tippett, Stephanie D’Souza
Journal: Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-04
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Growing concern surrounds the risk of neurodegenerative diseases in high-level collision sports, but research on Rugby Union's connection to these diseases is limited. 
          
          
            Objective
            This study sought to examine the long-term neurodegenerative disease risk associated with participation in high-level Rugby Union (‘rugby’), utilising whole-population administrative records.
          
          
            Methods
            This retrospective cohort study in New Zealand compared males born between 1920 and 1984 who were active in high-level (provincial or higher) rugby between 1950 and 2000 (n = 12,861) with males from the general population (n = 2,394,300), matched by age, ethnicity, and birthplace. We used Cox proportional hazards models to assess risks of Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease, motor neuron disease, and other dementias, ascertained using mortality and hospitalisation records from January 1988 to June 2023.
          
          
            Results
            A higher percentage of rugby players (6.5%) than males in the general population (5.2%) developed neurodegenerative diseases, with hazard ratios indicating players showed increased risks for any neurodegenerative disease (1.22; 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.14–1.30), Alzheimer's disease (1.61; 95% CI 1.42–1.83), and other dementias (1.23; 95% CI 1.14–1.33). Significant differences were not observed for Parkinson’s disease (1.05; 95% CI 0.89–1.22) and motor neuron disease (1.16; 95% CI 0.83–1.63). In general, this increased risk among players compared to the general population began around the ages of 70–79 years. Compared to the general population, small to moderate increased risks of any neurodegenerative disease were observed for a backline playing position, provincial and/or amateur players, international and/or professional players, participation in ≥ 2 years of play, and participation in five or more matches.
          
          
            Conclusions
            High-level rugby participation amongst males in New Zealand is associated with a small to moderate increase in neurodegenerative disease rates compared to the general population.
          
DOI: 10.1007/s40279-025-02299-y
ISSN: 0112-1642
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s40279-025-02299-y-2025-09-22-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Trans* Athletes in Sport: Not Ceding to the Sex/Gender Binary of Gender Critical Feminism1</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1123/ssj.2024-0030</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 145
Autoren: Michael Burke, Matthew Klugman
Journal: Sociology of Sport Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract: Debates over the position(ing) of trans* athletes in sport have been reignited in the last decade because of the confluence of broader political debates over the provision of rights of self-identification for trans* people with the International Olympic Committee’s decision to place responsibility for transgender regulations in the hands of international sporting federations. The effect of this confluence has meant a regressive shift back toward hard essentialism with regard to sex categories in sport. This paper challenges the politically powerful, yet romanticized and historically inaccurate, narrative that so-called gender critical feminists have produced to support this regressive move.
DOI: 10.1123/ssj.2024-0030
ISSN: 0741-1235
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1123/ssj.2024-0030-2025-09-22-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Could not prescribing exercise for depression be psychiatric malpractice?</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2025-110405</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 126
Autoren: Nicholas Fabiano, David Puder, Brendon Stubbs
Journal: British Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-09
DOI: 10.1136/bjsports-2025-110405
ISSN: 0306-3674
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bjsports-2025-110405-2025-09-22-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Longitudinal Performance Changes in Transgender Women Athletes Pre and Post Gender Affirming Hormone Therapy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/ejsc.70036</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 81
Autoren: Joanna Harper, Richard C. Blagrove, Eugenie Hunsicker, Gemma L. Witcomb, Richard A. Ferguson, Emma O'Donnell
Journal: European Journal of Sport Science
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-13
Abstract: ABSTRACTThe aim of this study was to evaluate athletic performance and training in transgender women (TW) athletes competing in running and swimming both pre and post gender affirming hormone therapy (GAHT). Using survey methods, 9 TW runners and 1 TW swimmer provided independently verified retrospective data for race times, training volume, height, body mass, and testosterone, oestrogen and haemoglobin concentrations and pre‐GAHT and post‐GAHT. Prospective data were collected for a further 12 months. Changes in performance and age‐grade scores (AGs) for runners and FINA scores for the swimmer were calculated. For runners, pre‐GAHT and post‐GAHT differences in AGs were adjusted based on training differences over time. Post‐GAHT, testosterone concentrations in TW (1.10 ± 0.52 nmol·L−1) were female typical. Average race time for the runners increased by 14.6 ± 5.6% after 31 ± 23 months (range 5–86 months) of GAHT. Changes in training were positively associated with changes in AGs (p = 0.008). Pre‐GAHT and post‐GAHT average AGs of the runners did not differ with or without adjustment (p = 0.304) for training differences. Average race times for the swimmer increased by 5.2 ± 2.3% and FINA score increased by 65 points after 34 months of GAHT. In our sample of TW athletes taking GAHT, longer distance events were associated with larger decrements in performance compared with shorter distance events, with exercise training helping attenuate these decrements. Event demands and exercise training may be important considerations in understanding the effects of GAHT on athletic performance in TW athletes.
DOI: 10.1002/ejsc.70036
ISSN: 1746-1391
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/ejsc.70036-2025-09-22-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>