<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 01:00:06 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 01:00:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Scapular kinematics variability in individuals with and without rotator cuff-related shoulder pain: A systematic review with multilevel meta-regression</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 48
Autoren: Rubén Fernández-Matías, Jorge Ballesteros-Frutos, Pablo Gallardo-Zamora, Néstor Requejo-Salinas, Iván Caballero-Pozo, Paula Ludewig, Enrique Lluch-Girbés
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261-2025-09-16-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of sitting posture and duration on lumbosacral nerve root function: A case-control study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/10538127251371635</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 31
Autoren: Hamad S Al Amer, Shahul Hameed Pakkir Mohamed, Sharon L Olson
Journal: Journal of Back and Musculoskeletal Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-26
Abstract: 
            Purpose
            This study aimed to investigate the effects of different sitting postures and prolonged sitting on lumbosacral nerve root function by measuring the amplitude of the soleus (SOL) Hoffmann reflex (H-reflex).
          
          
            Methods
            This study included 30 healthy individuals who were selected through convenience sampling and divided according to daily sitting duration over the past year into a prolonged sitting group (≥6 h/day) and a control group (≤4 h/day). The SOL H-reflex amplitude was recorded in erect, slumped, slouched, and supine positions. Ischial pressure was evaluated in all sitting postures to assess spinal loading.
          
          
            Results
            
              Slouched sitting significantly lowered ischial pressure (
              p
               
              &amp;lt;
               
              0.0005
              ) and produced higher H-reflex amplitudes (
              p
               
              &amp;lt;
               
              0.0005
              ), which were not significantly different from those in the supine position (
              p
               
              =
               
              0.362
              ). In contrast, (
              p
               
              &amp;lt;
               
              0.0005
              ) erect and slumped (
              p &amp;lt; 0.0005
              ) postures showed increased ischial pressure and significantly reduced H-reflex amplitudes (
              p
               
              &amp;lt;
               
              0.0005
              for both postures). Participants in the prolonged sitting group demonstrated significantly lower SOL H-reflex amplitudes than those in the control group (
              p
               
              =
               
              0.008, ηp²
               
              =
               
              0.23
              ).
            
          
          
            Conclusion
            Various sitting postures and durations exert different effects on the lumbosacral spine and nerve roots. Slouched sitting reduces spinal stress and lower nerve root compression compared to erect and slumped seated positions. Extended sitting duration may partially compress the lumbosacral nerve root, thereby potentially contributing to postural low back pain over time.
          
DOI: 10.1177/10538127251371635
ISSN: 1053-8127
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/10538127251371635-2025-09-16-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Risk factors for the development of knee osteoarthritis across the lifespan: A systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joca.2025.03.003</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 30
Autoren: Vicky Duong, Christina Abdel Shaheed, Manuela L. Ferreira, Sujita W. Narayan, Venkatesha Venkatesha, David J. Hunter, Jimmy Zhu, Inoshi Atukorala, Sarah Kobayashi, Siew Li Goh, Andrew M. Briggs, Marita Cross, Rolando Espinosa-Morales, Kai Fu, Francis Guillemin, Francis Keefe, L. Stefan Lohmander, Lyn March, George J. Milne, Yifang Mei, Ali Mobasheri, Mosedi Namane, George Peat, May Arna Risberg, Saurab Sharma, Regina Sit, Rosa Weiss Telles, Yuqing Zhang, Cyrus Cooper
Journal: Osteoarthritis and Cartilage
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.joca.2025.03.003
ISSN: 1063-4584
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.joca.2025.03.003-2025-09-16-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cervical flexion posture during smartphone use was not a risk factor for neck pain, but low sleep quality and insufficient levels of physical activity were. A longitudinal investigation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 28
Autoren: Igor Macedo Tavares Correia, Arthur de Sá Ferreira, Jessica Fernandez Mosqueira Gomes, Felipe José Jandre Reis, Leandro Alberto Calazans Nogueira, Ney Meziat-Filho
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258-2025-09-16-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Medial Tibial Stress Syndrome Needs a New Name—Make No Bones About It</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13411</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 22
Autoren: Laura M. Anderson, Stuart J. Warden, Richard W. Willy, Daniel R. Bonanno, Hylton B. Menz
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-18
Abstract:  Pain near the posteromedial tibia is common in running and jumping athletes. This problem has had many names, with “shin splints” and “medial tibial stress syndrome” (MTSS) the most common. The term shin splints is nonspecific and nondescript, and has never gained clinical traction. Similarly, the clinical use of MTSS with athletes and coaches is often met with confusion as ‘tibial stress’ is frequently misinterpreted as indicating a bone stress injury. With no conclusive evidence regarding the pathophysiology of MTSS, we advocate renaming it “Load Induced Medial-Leg Pain” (LIMP). LIMP avoids the use of ‘tibial stress’ which is problematic due to the unknown pathology of the condition and its confusion with bone stress injury. Using the term LIMP instead of MTSS gives clinicians, researchers, and athletes a clearer, more accurate way to approach managing exercise-related lower leg pain. 
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13411
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13411-2025-09-16-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>