<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 01:03:44 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 01:03:44 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Laboratory cultivated Cordyceps militaris modulates cockroach allergen-induced inflammation in keratinocytes and macrophages dual cell platforms</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Mey-Fann Lee, Jane-Yii Wu, Chi-Sheng Wu, Ching-Chun Lin, Yu-Wen Chu
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-15
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1-2025-10-21-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and safety of Shugan Jieyu capsules in combination with zolpidem for insomnia disorder with depressive symptoms: a double-blind randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Qianqian Xin, Dhirendra Paudel, Jiehan Zhang, Huafeng Wei, Yihong Cheng, Yan Xu, Ruichen Fang, Jinnong Jiang, Yuling Wang, Bin Zhang
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z-2025-10-21-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Baseline individual factors associated with clinical outcomes in adults with non-specific low back pain following manual therapy: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Gaetan Barbier, Mathieu Picchiottino, Arnaud Delafontaine, Guillaume Goncalves, André Bussières, François Cottin, Arnaud Lardon
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y-2025-10-21-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Inhibitory effect of [6]-shogaol against 3CLpro activity and SARS-CoV-2 infection</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05094-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Takashi Tanikawa, Tsuyoshi Hayashi, Yuka Kiba, Hitoshi Kamauchi, Yuichi Someya, Masashi Kitamura
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05094-4
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05094-4-2025-10-21-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Therapeutic potential of Atractylodes lancea in restoring cardio-renal function in rats with diet-induced metabolic syndrome</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05074-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Yun Jeong Yang, Mi Hyeon Hong, Jung Joo Yoon, Ai Lin Tai, Ho Sub Lee, Sung Joo Park, Hye Yoom Kim, Dae Gill Kang
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-30
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Cardio-Renal Metabolic Syndrome (CRS) encompasses metabolic disorders such as type 2 diabetes, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, chronic kidney disease, and heart failure. It is associated with obesity, systemic inflammation, and insulin resistance. Atractylodes lancea (AL), a traditional herbal remedy, has been previously reported to exhibit diuretic, sedative, antibacterial, and anticancer effects. However, the impact of AL on cardiovascular and renal functions within a metabolic syndrome (MS) model remains to be explored.
          
          
            Methods
            Metabolic syndrome was induced in rats through an 8-week high-fat, high-fructose diet. After induction, experimental groups were orally administered olmesartan (10 mg/kg/day) or Aqueous extract of Atractylodes lancea (AAL) at 100 or 200 mg/kg/day for an additional 8 weeks. Body weight, fasting blood glucose, triglycerides, abdominal circumference, systolic blood pressure, and HDL-cholesterol levels were measured. Insulin levels and oral glucose tolerance tests (OGTT) were conducted to evaluate insulin resistance. Cardiac function was assessed using echocardiography, and ejection fraction and fractional shortening were analyzed. Masson’s trichrome and Picrosirius red staining were performed to evaluate fibrosis in the heart and aorta. Renal function was measured through creatinine clearance, blood urea nitrogen (BUN), and electrolyte levels. Periodic acid-Schiff (PAS) staining was additionally performed to evaluate histological changes in the kidney.
          
          
            Results
            Administration of AAL resulted in significant reductions in body weight, fasting blood glucose, triglycerides, abdominal circumference, and systolic blood pressure, while HDL-cholesterol levels increased. AAL improved insulin resistance, as indicated by enhanced insulin levels and OGTT results. Echocardiography revealed improvements in ejection fraction and fractional shortening in AAL-treated groups compared to the MS group. Histological analysis showed that AAL reduced heart and aorta fibrosis, as well as attenuated kidney injury. Additionally, AAL improved renal function by enhancing creatinine clearance, reducing BUN levels, and stabilizing electrolyte balance.
          
          
            Conclusions
            The aqueous extract of Atractylodes lancea (AAL) effectively ameliorated cardiovascular and renal dysfunction in a rat model of metabolic syndrome model. These results suggest that AAL may have preventive and therapeutic potential for cardio-renal complications associated with MS. However, further investigation is needed to evaluate its suitability for diet-based interventions and evaluate its safety and pharmacological profile.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05074-8
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05074-8-2025-10-21-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>