<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 01:07:37 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 01:07:37 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Nanobodies: a new paradigm for brain disorder therapies</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2025.10.004</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 425
Autoren: Pierre-André Lafon, Laurent Prézeau, Jean-Philippe Pin, Philippe Rondard
Journal: Trends in Pharmacological Sciences
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tips.2025.10.004
ISSN: 0165-6147
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tips.2025.10.004-2025-11-13-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mass balance, pharmacokinetics, metabolism, and excretion of radiolabeled acoziborole, a potential novel treatment for human African trypanosomiasis, following single microtracer oral dose to humans</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.00580-25</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 142
Autoren: Jean-Yves Gillon, François Simon, Sharan Sidhu, Mathieu Louis, Delphine Launay, Valérie Wauthier, Marta Pelay-Gimeno, Lotte van Andel, Sabrina Loyau, Sandra Rembry, Estelle Weinling, Antoine Tarral
Journal: Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-05
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    
                    
                      Acoziborole is an oxaborole 6-carboxamide active against
                      Trypanosoma brucei gambiense
                      and
                      rhodesiense
                      , the parasites responsible for human African trypanosomiasis. This open-label, phase I study in six healthy male participants evaluated the mass balance, pharmacokinetics, metabolism pathways, and excretion of a single oral 960 mg dose of [
                      14
                      C]-acoziborole. Blood, plasma, and feces were collected for 120 days and urine for 16 days. The excretion balance and systemic exposure of total circulating radioactivity were determined using accelerator mass spectrometry. Metabolism profiling was performed in pools of plasma, urine, and feces. Liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry quantified acoziborole and its metabolite SCYX-3109 in plasma and urine. By Day 60, 87.3% of the total radioactivity had been recovered (10.9% and 74.2% of the total dose in urine and in feces, respectively), with an excretion increment of &amp;lt;1% between Days 59 and 61. Mean ratios of total radioactivity indicated an equivalent distribution between blood cells and plasma. The concentration-time profiles of total radioactivity and acoziborole in plasma were similar. In plasma, acoziborole accounted for 95.1%, an oxidized form of acoziborole for 2.3% of the total radioactivity, while SCYX-3109 was not detected. Seven metabolites (oxidative deboronation, glucuronidation, and mono-oxidation) were detected in urine with individual abundances relative to the dose of 0.1–2.1%; unchanged acoziborole accounted for 0.6%. In feces, acoziborole, SCYX-3109, and two other oxidized or deboronated forms of acoziborole represented 33.6%, 12.3%, and 2.3% of the dose, respectively. Acoziborole showed good absorption, limited metabolism, minimal urinary elimination, and predominant but slow biliary-fecal elimination.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1128/aac.00580-25
ISSN: 0066-4804
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1128/aac.00580-25-2025-11-13-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The continued impact of COVID-19 during the Omicron era on immunocompromised individuals in Japan</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 110
Autoren: Toshibumi Taniguchi, Mitsuru Hoshino, Ryotaro Ide, Tomoyuki Homma, Keiji Sugiyama, Shinichi Kanazu, Atsushi Maruyama, Kazuhiro Tateda
Journal: Journal of Infection and Chemotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840
ISSN: 1341-321X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jiac.2025.102840-2025-11-13-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Hyper-maturity and accelerated aging in the hippocampus of mouse models of neuropsychiatric disorders with anxiety-like behavior</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-025-02237-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 86
Autoren: Hideo Hagihara, Hisatsugu Koshimizu, Satoko Hattori, Hirotaka Shoji, Miho Tanaka, Kazutaka Ikeda, Tsuyoshi Miyakawa
Journal: Neuropsychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-27
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Proper maturation of neuronal and glial cells in the hippocampus is essential for emotional regulation and cognitive function. While pseudo-immaturity, defined as arrested or reversed development, has been extensively implicated in various neuropsychiatric conditions, the opposite phenomenon, hyper-maturity, remains underexplored. Here, we present transcriptomic evidence of hippocampal hyper-maturity across 17 datasets from 16 mouse models with genetic, pharmacological, or other experimental manipulations, identified through a comprehensive screening of over 260,000 omics datasets. These models were characterized by a pronounced overrepresentation of gene expression changes typically observed during postnatal development and included serotonin transporter knockout mice, glucocorticoid receptor overexpressing mice, and corticosterone-treated mice, models of depression and anxiety, Df(16)A
                    +/−
                    mice, a 22q11.2 deletion schizophrenia model, β-glucuronidase-deficient lysosomal storage disorder model mice, and senescence-prone SAMP8 mice. Meta-analysis of enriched pathways highlighted associations of synapse-related genes with the hyper-maturity signature. Behavioral annotations from public datasets further suggest that hippocampal hyper-maturity models predominantly exhibit increased anxiety-like behaviors, whereas immaturity models tend to display the opposite pattern. Notably, hippocampal hyper-maturity encompassed two transcriptional dimensions: enhanced postnatal development and accelerated aging. For example, SAMP8 mice aligned more with developmental enhancement, whereas corticosterone-treated and lysosomal storage disorder models reflected aging acceleration. Combined analysis with available single-cell RNA-sequencing data further delineated that microglia and granule cells may contribute to aging-associated transcriptional shifts. These findings suggest that hippocampal hyper-maturity and accelerated aging represent convergent molecular phenotypes associated with anxiety-like behavior. Bidirectional alterations in hippocampal maturity may serve as a transdiagnostic endophenotype and offer novel therapeutic or anti-aging targets for neuropsychiatric disorders.
                  
DOI: 10.1038/s41386-025-02237-6
ISSN: 0893-133X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41386-025-02237-6-2025-11-13-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>MCH11, a new monoacylglycerol lipase inhibitor, reduces ethanol consumption and motivation to drink in mice, with sex-dependent differences</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118662</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 83
Autoren: Abraham B. Torregrosa, María S. García-Gutiérrez, Daniela Navarro, Francisco Navarrete, Jorge Manzanares
Journal: Biomedicine &amp;amp; Pharmacotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118662
ISSN: 0753-3322
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118662-2025-11-13-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>