<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 01:00:47 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 01:00:47 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>The effect of warm saltwater and warm water baths on pain, fatigue, sleep quality, and functional capacity in patients with rheumatoid arthritis: a randomized controlled study✰</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05050-2</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Okşan Aktaş, Ayşe Arikan Dönmez, Sevgisun Kapucu, Muhammet Çinar
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-12
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05050-2
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05050-2-2025-09-11-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Systematic review of clinical practice guidelines on acupuncture for chronic musculoskeletal pain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Leonard Ho, Cyrus Ngo Tin Lai, Haiyong Chen, Sheung Wai Law, Edwin Chau Leung Yu, Fiona Pui Yan Lam, Yi Chung Cheung, Irene Xinyin Wu, Samuel Yeung Shan Wong, Regina Wing Shan Sit
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Introduction
            Acupuncture is increasingly utilised in primary care to manage chronic musculoskeletal pain, supported by a growing body of evidence. This rising adoption has driven demand for clinical practice guidelines (CPGs). We summarised the characteristics of recent acupuncture CPGs for osteoarthritis, low back pain, neck pain, and shoulder pain, and critically appraised their methodological quality.
          
          
            Methods
            We searched nine databases to identify acupuncture CPGs published from January 2014 to November 2024. Eligible CPGs were required to be developed by guideline committees and to include evidence-informed recommendations linked to clearly defined levels of evidence. Two independent reviewers extracted CPG characteristics and assessed methodological quality using the Appraisal of Guidelines for Research and Evaluation II (AGREE II) instrument.
          
          
            Results
            Of the 1,999 records screened, 17 CPGs were included, encompassing 35 recommendations. Shoulder pain was the most addressed condition (n = 14), followed by low back pain (n = 11), osteoarthritis (n = 8), and neck pain (n = 2). Various types of acupuncture were considered, with manual acupuncture featuring in most (n = 26) recommendations. Overall, 60% of the recommendations supported the use of acupuncture, comprising 5.7% strong recommendations and 54.3% weak or conditional recommendations. In contrast, 22.9% of recommendations offered no explicit guidance, while 17.1% advised against its use. Methodological assessment classified 10 CPGs as high quality, while seven were of moderate quality.
          
          
            Conclusions
            Contradictions exist among the included CPGs regarding whether acupuncture should be recommended for routine practice, potentially reflecting differences in clinical and cultural contexts. Local CPGs should be developed using rigorous methodology, ensuring the involvement of local stakeholders. An AGREE II extension should be developed for the methodological quality assessment of acupuncture CPGs.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y-2025-09-11-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Potential clinical relevance of Buchholzia coriacea: in vitro antimicrobial characteristics of the methanol leaf extract</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05057-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Xiyao Feng, Chinonyerem O. Iheanacho
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-19
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05057-9
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05057-9-2025-09-11-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Trends and patterns of complementary and alternative medicine use among cancer patients in Jordan: a decade comparison</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05065-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Nedal Al-Rawashdeh, Mohammad Alqudimat, Ibrahim Alananzeh, Nour Kasasbeh, Khawlah Ammar, Amal Al-Omari
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-26
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05065-9
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05065-9-2025-09-11-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Herbal products use during pregnancy and postpartum: study of consumption and user profile in Catalonia</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05008-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 16
Autoren: Noelia G. Romero, Elisabet Teixido, Laia Guardia-Escote, Anna Tresserra, Salvador Cañigueral, Marta Barenys
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-08
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            The prevalence of herbal products (HPs) consumption among pregnant and postpartum women, the factors driving their use or the main sources of recommendation have never been studied in Spain or Catalonia. Investigating its prevalence of use during critical phases of development is crucial for providing guidance to health professionals.
          
          
            Methods
            A validated questionnaire, containing general data on socio-demographic status, lifestyle, maternal health data and its association with HP consumption, was performed in online personal interviews among women living in Catalonia between pregnancy week 22 and postpartum month 9.
          
          
            Results
            We identified a higher percentage of HPs consumption compared to other European countries, while the 5 most consumed products were similar to the products described to be consumed by pregnant women in other countries. The most frequently consumed HPs were ginger (28%), chamomile (9%), thyme (7%), rooibos (6%), cranberry (4%), and raspberry leaf (4%), and we identified specific temporal patterns of consumption for several of them, depending on the trimester of pregnancy. Furthermore, we found a significant relationship between women consuming oral HPs and the opinion that “pregnant women should preferably consume herbal remedies rather than conventional medicines”.
          
          
            Conclusions
            We provide evidence that women consuming HPs during pregnancy are not defined by a specific profile and therefore, healthcare professionals should be aware that any woman could potentially consume HPs during this period.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05008-4
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05008-4-2025-09-11-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>