<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:07:33 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:07:33 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Peri-Neuromal Botulinum Toxin Injection for War-Related Postamputation Pain: A Pragmatic, Multicenter, Comparative-Effectiveness Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 352
Autoren: Nadiya Segin, Roman Smolynets, Joana Barroso, Natalia Molinets, Paul F. Pasquina, Steven P. Cohen
Journal: Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026
ISSN: 0003-9993
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026-2025-11-04-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>(Not so) universal literacy screening: a survey of educators reveals variability in implementation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11881-025-00342-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 44
Autoren: Ola Ozernov-Palchik, Zoe Elizee, Fabio Catania, Meral Hacikamiloglu, Stefanie Shattuck-Hufnagel, Yaacov Petscher, Satrajit Ghosh, John D. E. Gabrieli
Journal: Annals of Dyslexia
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-29
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Currently, most states in the United States have enacted legislation mandating universal screening for literacy risk in kindergarten through 3rd grade. However, the degree to which these policies translate into consistent, high-quality screening practices remains unclear. In this survey study, we collected responses from a diverse sample of K–3 educators (
                    N
                     = 251) across 39 states, representing varied school types, professional roles, and experience levels, to examine the real-world implementation of universal screening. Guided by the Exploration, Preparation, Implementation, and Sustainment (EPIS) framework, we analyzed quantitative and qualitative data to identify real-world factors that could impede the fidelity and effectiveness of screening implementation. We found substantial variability across multiple dimensions of literacy screening implementation. Educators described considerable variation in screener selection, administration practices, testing environments, training quality, scoring accuracy, and the use of results to guide intervention. Notably, many indicated insufficient training and professional development, expressing uncertainty about administering and interpreting screeners, particularly for English language learners. Nearly half also reported the absence of systematic procedures for developing intervention plans, suggesting that many students identified as at risk do not receive appropriate follow-up support. These implementation challenges occurred despite widespread recognition among educators of screening’s importance for early literacy intervention. Educators from lower-socioeconomic status schools reported significantly greater time burdens in conducting screenings and more technology-related challenges compared to their higher-SES counterparts. Without systematic improvements to implementation support and training, current screening initiatives may fail to achieve their intended goal of early identification and intervention for struggling readers.
                  
DOI: 10.1007/s11881-025-00342-1
ISSN: 0736-9387
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s11881-025-00342-1-2025-11-04-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Episode of Care Characteristics Following Implementation of a No Co-pay Physical Therapy Program for Musculoskeletal Conditions</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/ptj/pzaf129</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 43
Autoren: Trevor Lentz, Adam Lutz, Uchechukwu Ikeaba, Brooke Alhanti, Steven Z George, Chad Cook, Charles Thigpen
Journal: Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-24
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Importance
                    New care models promoting early access to physical therapy by reducing or eliminating co-pays are emerging. Few studies have compared health care use in these programs to other care pathways across musculoskeletal conditions.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    The objective of this study was to describe episode-level musculoskeletal health care use across different care pathway options, including a no-copay physical therapy program.
                  
                  
                    Design
                    This study was a descriptive retrospective analysis of claims data.
                  
                  
                    Setting and Participants
                    This study included health care beneficiaries of a self-insured employer with approximately 52,000 covered lives.
                  
                  
                    Interventions or Exposures
                    The study included musculoskeletal care episodes from October 2019 to September 2020 categorized as no copay physical therapy, traditional physical therapy, or other management.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcomes
                    Rates of surgery/injection, imaging, inpatient services, physician services, emergency services, physical therapy, and other services by episode type, overall and stratified by body region: upper extremity, lower extremity, and spine.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Of 9696 total episodes, 886 (9.1%) were no copay physical therapy, 1261 (13%) were traditional physical therapy, and 7549 (77.9%) were other management. No copay physical therapy episodes had lower imaging rates (38%) compared to traditional physical therapy (47%) and other management (45%) episodes. Inpatient services were similar for no copay (16%) and traditional (12%) physical therapy, both lower than other management episodes (23%). Physician services were higher in other management (100%) and traditional physical therapy (81%) episodes compared to no copay physical therapy episodes (43%). Surgery/injection rates were similar for no copay (11%) and traditional (8%) physical therapy, both lower than other management episodes (27%). Differences by pathway were more pronounced for extremity conditions than for spine conditions.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    Rates of no copay program use were modest with those who used the program having lower rates of advanced imaging, injection, and surgery.
                  
                  
                    Relevance
                    Findings may be most relevant for employers, health systems, and payors planning resource allocation and benefit design for similar programs.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/ptj/pzaf129
ISSN: 0031-9023
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/ptj/pzaf129-2025-11-04-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Heavy slow resistance training combined with patient education in patients with gluteal tendinopathy: A feasibility study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103425</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 26
Autoren: Jan Moritz Grigat, Troels Kjeldsen, Stian Langgård Jørgensen, Inger Mechlenburg, Ulrik Dalgas
Journal: Musculoskeletal Science and Practice
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103425
ISSN: 2468-7812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103425-2025-11-04-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Blautia luti reduces neratinib-induced diarrhea in a rat model</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00520-025-09990-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 24
Autoren: Claire P. Vieyra, Micaela J. Quinn, Emma H. Bateman, Hannah R. Wardill, Joanne M. Bowen
Journal: Supportive Care in Cancer
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-14
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Purpose
            Neratinib is a pan-human epidermal growth factor receptor (HER) tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) used in the treatment of HER2+ breast cancer. Diarrhea is the most commonly reported toxicity, with the majority experiencing at least some grade of diarrhea. The mechanisms behind neratinib-induced diarrhea are yet to be fully defined, but have been linked to gut microbiome changes, specifically decreased levels of the genera Blautia. This study aimed to investigate the efficacy of Blautia luti (B.luti) administered as a daily probiotic on neratinib-induced diarrhea, and its effects on the gut microbiome in a well-established rat model.
          
          
            Methods
            Female albino Wistar (AW) rats (n = 40) were randomly allocated to groups including; vehicle control (VC), neratinib alone, B.luti alone and neratinib + B.luti in different schedules (Pre, Pre &amp;amp; Post or Post). Daily oral gavage administration of B.luti (107CFU/ml) was given according to corresponding schedules, alongside a 28-day cycle of neratinib (50 mg/kg). Diarrhea was graded daily, and faecal samples collected for gut microbiome analysis at study end. Ileum and colon samples were collected for intestinal analysis. 16S rRNA gene sequencing was performed on faecal samples and H&amp;amp;E performed on intestinal tissue for injury evaluation.
          
          
            Results
            Grade 3 diarrhea was reduced in the Post group when compared to the neratinib alone group (p = 0.0122). No significant differences were seen in the tissue injury scores of the ileum or colon. There was no significant change in microbial composition with B.luti administration.
          
          
            Conclusion
            This study demonstrated that administration of B.luti supplementation, was effective in reducing neratinib-induced diarrhea severity when consumed concurrently. This administration schedule may have a protective role in the intestines through immunomodulation.
          
DOI: 10.1007/s00520-025-09990-w
ISSN: 0941-4355
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00520-025-09990-w-2025-11-04-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>