<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 01:00:52 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 01:00:52 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Protective effect of metformin against dementia in patients with obesity: Results from a global federated health network analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/dom.16647</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 400
Autoren: Yu‐Liang Lin, Yi‐Jui Hung, Jin‐Hua Chen, Jia‐Ying Sung, Min‐Huei Hsu, Hoang Khanh Dinh, Kee‐Hsin Chen, Chiehfeng Chen
Journal: Diabetes, Obesity and Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-06
Abstract: AbstractAimsMetformin, a first‐line medication for Type 2 diabetes (T2D), has been suggested to reduce dementia risk. We investigated whether metformin use was associated with lower long‐term incidence of dementia and all‐cause mortality in obese patients.Materials and MethodsWe analysed electronic health record data from the TriNetX network. Patients were categorised into four body mass index (BMI) groups (25–29.9, 30–34.9, 35–39.9 and over 40). In each group, those prescribed metformin were compared with matched controls who were not prescribed metformin, using propensity score matching. Kaplan–Meier survival analysis was used to estimate dementia incidence and all‐cause mortality over a 10‐year follow‐up.ResultsThe matched cohorts included 132 920 (BMI 25–29.9), 142 723 (30–34.9), 94 402 (35–39.9) and 82 732 (over 40) patients per group. After 10 years of follow‐up, metformin users exhibited significantly lower risks of both dementia and all‐cause mortality compared to controls. Specifically, the hazard ratios for dementia across each BMI group were 0.875 (95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.848–0.904), 0.917 (0.885–0.951), 0.878 (0.834–0.924) and 0.891 (0.834–0.953), respectively. For all‐cause mortality, the corresponding hazard ratios were 0.719 (0.701–0.737), 0.727 (0.708–0.746), 0.717 (0.694–0.741) and 0.743 (0.717–0.771).ConclusionsIn this large, multi‐centre cohort study, metformin use was associated with reduced risks of dementia and all‐cause mortality in obese patients. The protective effect was observed across all BMI groups, with variations noted by population. These findings support the potential of metformin in lowering dementia risk in patients with obesity. Further studies are needed to explore the underlying mechanisms.
DOI: 10.1111/dom.16647
ISSN: 1462-8902
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/dom.16647-2025-09-09-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association of metformin treatment with changes in metal dynamics in individuals with type 2 diabetes</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 328
Autoren: Natsu Otowa-Suematsu, Kazuhiko Sakaguchi, Tomoko Yamada, Marika Nishisaka, Yasuko Morita, Hayato Fukumitsu, Yukari Katsura, Yuko Okada, Yushi Hirota, Kenji Sugawara, Wataru Ogawa
Journal: BMJ Open Diabetes Research &amp;amp; Care
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-31
Abstract: 
                  Introduction
                  The metal-chelating activity of metformin, which has long been known but of unclear clinical relevance, has recently been implicated in the pleiotropic effects, including antitumorigenic and anti-inflammatory actions, of the drug. However, whether metformin actually influences metal dynamics in humans has remained unknown. We here investigate whether metformin influences serum metal levels in individuals with type 2 diabetes.
               
               
                  Research design and methods
                  In this cross-sectional study, individuals with type 2 diabetes treated or not treated with metformin for at least 6 months were recruited. The primary outcome was the difference in serum copper concentration between metformin users and non-users. Secondary outcomes included differences in serum levels of iron, zinc, and vitamin B12 as well as in copper-related and iron-related parameters between the two groups.
               
               
                  Results
                  A total of 189 individuals (93 metformin users and 96 non-users) were analyzed. Metformin users showed significantly lower serum copper (16.0 vs 17.8 µmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) and iron levels (16.3 vs 17.3 µmol/L, p=0.02) and higher zinc levels (13.3 vs 12.5 µmol/L, p=0.01) compared with non-users. Copper-related and iron-related parameters for metformin users were consistent with latent deficiencies of these metals. Serum homocysteine levels (12.2 vs 11.2 µmol/L, p=0.03) were significantly higher, whereas vitamin B12 levels (338.7 vs 412.8 pmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) were significantly lower, in metformin users. Multiple regression analysis including variables that potentially influence metal dynamics identified metformin use as an independent predictor of serum copper (B = –1.54 µmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) and iron levels (B = –2.49 µmol/L, p=0.004).
               
               
                  Conclusions
                  Metformin use was associated with reduced serum levels of copper and iron, as well as with increased serum zinc levels. These changes in metal dynamics may be related to the pharmacological effects of this widely administered drug.
               
DOI: 10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255
ISSN: 2052-4897
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255-2025-09-09-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide receptor signaling in oligodendrocytes increases the weight-loss action of GLP-1R agonism</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.009</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 151
Autoren: Robert Hansford, Sophie Buller, Anthony H. Tsang, Simon Benoit, Anna G. Roberts, Emmy Erskine, Thomas Brown, Valentina Pirro, Frank Reimann, Norio Harada, Nobuya Inagaki, Ricardo J. Samms, Johannes Broichhagen, David J. Hodson, Alice Adriaenssens, Soyoung Park, Clemence Blouet
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.009
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.009-2025-09-09-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and safety of cAMP-biased GLP-1 receptor agonist ecnoglutide versus dulaglutide in patients with type 2 diabetes and elevated glucose concentrations on metformin monotherapy (EECOH-2): a 52-week, multicentre, open-label, non-inferiority, randomised, phase 3 trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00196-2</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 102
Autoren: Yang He, Nianrong Mi, Zhifeng Cheng, Haibo Xue, Jie Han, Haifang Wang, Huihui Wang, Jun Wu, Xiaoguang Shi, Shuping Zhao, Binhong Duan, Yikun Zhu, Yanqin Zhou, Feng Li, Xin Wang, Hongwei Ling, Su Wang, Qingju Li, Feifei Jiang, Ming Yang, Shaohui Bing, Qing Zheng, Jing Ning, Mengying Guo, Yue Bu, Lei Guan, Yao Li, Liu Yang, Wanjun Guo, Hai Pan, Xiaoying Li
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00196-2
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00196-2-2025-09-09-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Fluorescent GLP1R/GIPR dual agonist probes reveal cell targets in the pancreas and brain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s42255-025-01342-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 101
Autoren: Anne de Bray, Anna G. Roberts, Sarah Armour, Jason Tong, Christiane Huhn, Blaise Gatin-Fraudet, Kilian Roßmann, Ali H. Shilleh, Wanqing Jiang, Natalie S. Figueredo Burgos, James P. P. Trott, Katrina Viloria, Daniela Nasteska, Abigail Pearce, Satsuki Miyazaki, Jeremy W. Tomlinson, Dylan M. Owen, Daniel J. Nieves, Julia Ast, Malgorzata Cyranka, Alexey Epanchintsev, Carina Ämmälä, Frank Reimann, Tolga Soykan, Graham Ladds, Alice E. Adriaenssens, Stefan Trapp, Ben Jones, Johannes Broichhagen, David J. Hodson
Journal: Nature Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-19
Abstract: Abstract
          Dual agonists targeting glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor (GLP1R) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide receptor (GIPR) are breakthrough treatments for patients with type 2 diabetes and obesity. Compared to GLP1R agonists, dual agonists show superior efficacy for glucose lowering and weight reduction. However, delineation of dual agonist cell targets remains challenging. Here, we develop and test daLUXendin and daLUXendin+, non-lipidated and lipidated fluorescent GLP1R/GIPR dual agonist probes, and use them to visualize cellular targets. daLUXendins are potent GLP1R/GIPR dual agonists that advantageously show less functional selectivity for mouse GLP1R over mouse GIPR. daLUXendins label rodent and human pancreatic islet cells, with a signal intensity of β cells &amp;gt; α cells = δ cells. Systemic administration of daLUXendin strongly labels GLP1R+ and GIPR+ neurons in circumventricular organs characterized by an incomplete blood–brain barrier but does not penetrate the brain beyond labelling seen with single (ant)agonists. At the single-molecule level, daLUXendin targets endogenous GLP1R–GIPR nanodomains, which differ in organization and composition from those targeted by a single agonist. daLUXendins reveal dual agonist targets in the pancreas and brain and exclude a role for brain penetration in determining the superior efficacy of dual agonists, shedding new light on different modes of action of dual agonists versus single agonists.
DOI: 10.1038/s42255-025-01342-6
ISSN: 2522-5812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s42255-025-01342-6-2025-09-09-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>