<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 01:10:24 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 01:10:24 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of exercise snacks on fitness and cardiometabolic health in physically inactive individuals: systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2025-110027</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 617
Autoren: Miguel Ángel Rodríguez, Marcos Quintana-Cepedal, Boris Cheval, Cecilie Thøgersen-Ntoumani, Irene Crespo, Hugo Olmedillas
Journal: British Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-07
Abstract: 
                  Objectives
                  To evaluate the effects of brief bouts of exercise spread throughout the day, termed ‘exercise snacks’, on cardiorespiratory and muscular fitness, and cardiometabolic health outcomes in physically inactive adults and older adults (aged ≥65 years).
               
               
                  Design
                  Systematic review and meta-analysis.
               
               
                  Data sources
                  Seven databases were searched from inception to April 2025.
               
               
                  Eligibility criteria
                  Randomised controlled trials (RCTs) of adults and older adults, comparing exercise snacks with non-exercising controls.
               
               
                  Results
                  11 RCTs (n=414; 69.1% women, mean age 18.7±0.8 to 74.2±5.6 years) were included. Exercise snacks were defined as structured bouts lasting ≤5 min, performed at least twice daily, ≥3 times/week, for ≥2 weeks. The interventions varied in duration (4–12 weeks), frequency (3–7 days/week) and intensity (moderate-to-vigorous to near-maximal). Exercise snacks significantly improved cardiorespiratory fitness in adults (g=1.37, 95% CI 0.58 to 2.17; p&amp;lt;0.005; I2=71.4 %, k=6) and muscular endurance in older adults (g=0.40, 95% CI 0.06 to 0.75; p=0.02; I2=0 %, k=4), with moderate and very low certainty of evidence, respectively. No significant effects were observed for lower limb muscular strength or cardiometabolic outcomes, including body composition, blood pressure and blood lipid profiles. High compliance (91.1%) and adherence (82.8%) rates were observed.
               
               
                  Conclusions
                  Moderate certainty of evidence indicated that exercise snacks improved cardiorespiratory fitness in physically inactive adults. However, evidence for benefits on muscular endurance in older adults was limited, and the current data do not support their effectiveness for improving other cardiometabolic health markers.
               
               
                  PROSPERO registration number
                  CRD42024616514.
               
DOI: 10.1136/bjsports-2025-110027
ISSN: 0306-3674
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bjsports-2025-110027-2025-10-27-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Peri-Neuromal Botulinum Toxin Injection for War-Related Postamputation Pain: A Pragmatic, Multicenter, Comparative-Effectiveness Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 352
Autoren: Nadiya Segin, Roman Smolynets, Joana Barroso, Natalia Molinets, Paul F. Pasquina, Steven P. Cohen
Journal: Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026
ISSN: 0003-9993
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026-2025-10-27-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Is “Zone 2 Training”?: Experts’ Viewpoint on Definition, Training Methods, and Expected Adaptations</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1123/ijspp.2024-0303</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 178
Autoren: Sebastian Sitko, Xabier Artetxe, Martin Bonnevie-Svendsen, Miguel Ángel Galán-Rioja, Gabriele Gallo, Frédéric Grappe, Peter Leo, Manuel Mateo, Iñigo Mujika, Dajo Sanders, Stephen Seiler, Mikel Zabala, Pedro L. Valenzuela, Aitor Viribay
Journal: International Journal of Sports Physiology and Performance
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
Abstract: 
                    
                      Background
                      :
                    
                    The role of high-volume low-intensity training for enhancing endurance performance has gained growing interest in recent years. Specifically, so-called “zone 2 training” is currently receiving much attention, and many propose that this is the target intensity at which a large proportion of total endurance training should be performed. However, despite the popularity of this concept, there is no clear consensus among coaches, athletes, and scientists regarding the definition of zone 2 training.
                    
                      Purpose
                      :
                    
                    This commentary summarizes the perspectives, experience, and knowledge of an expert panel of 14 applied sport scientists and professional coaches with the aim of providing insight and a basis for definitional consensus on zone 2 training. Moreover, potential training strategies at this intensity are proposed, and the expected physiological adaptations when exercising at this intensity and related research gaps are also discussed.
                    
                      Results
                      :
                    
                    Experts reached consensus that zone 2 training should preferably be performed at intensities located immediately below the first lactate or ventilatory threshold through continuous, variable, or interval-type sessions. Furthermore, experts expected a broad range of central and peripheral adaptations from zone 2 training. These expected adaptations might not be unique to zone 2 and could also be induced with sessions performed at slightly higher and lower intensities.
                    
                      Conclusions
                      :
                    
                    This commentary provides practical insight and unified criteria regarding the preferred intensity, duration, and session type for the optimization of zone 2 training based on the perspectives of acknowledged sport scientists and professional coaches.
                  
DOI: 10.1123/ijspp.2024-0303
ISSN: 1555-0265
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1123/ijspp.2024-0303-2025-10-27-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Trans* Athletes in Sport: Not Ceding to the Sex/Gender Binary of Gender Critical Feminism1</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1123/ssj.2024-0030</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 145
Autoren: Michael Burke, Matthew Klugman
Journal: Sociology of Sport Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract: Debates over the position(ing) of trans* athletes in sport have been reignited in the last decade because of the confluence of broader political debates over the provision of rights of self-identification for trans* people with the International Olympic Committee’s decision to place responsibility for transgender regulations in the hands of international sporting federations. The effect of this confluence has meant a regressive shift back toward hard essentialism with regard to sex categories in sport. This paper challenges the politically powerful, yet romanticized and historically inaccurate, narrative that so-called gender critical feminists have produced to support this regressive move.
DOI: 10.1123/ssj.2024-0030
ISSN: 0741-1235
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1123/ssj.2024-0030-2025-10-27-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Human development and gender inequality are associated with cardiorespiratory fitness: A global systematic review of V̇O2peak</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101098</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 95
Autoren: Nicolas J. Pillon, Joaquin Ortiz de Zevallos, Juleen R. Zierath, Barbara E. Ainsworth
Journal: Journal of Sport and Health Science
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101098
ISSN: 2095-2546
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101098-2025-10-27-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>