<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 01:01:29 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 01:01:29 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Urtica dioica leaf infusion enhances cisplatin-induced apoptosis in ovarian cancer cells in vitro</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05053-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Perla Nafeh, Guy Nafeh, Maria Younes, Ahlam Chaaban, Louna El Bitar, José-Noel Ibrahim, Philippe H. Kobeissy, Sandra Rizk
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-13
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05053-z
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05053-z-2025-08-28-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Nanoparticles from grape seed extract inhibit inflammatory cytokines and ameliorate CCl4-induced hepatotoxicity</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05005-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Neveen Adel Madbouly, Doaa Mohammad Ali, Alyaa Ahmed Farid
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-19
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Xenobiotic-induced liver injury is a clinically reverent condition which may influence the development of steatohepatitis via affecting numerous pathways such as oxidative stress, inflammation, mitochondorial functioning and fatty acid biosynthesis. The current study was conducted to survey the antioxidant effect of grape seeds extract nanoparticles (GS extract NPs) against CCl4-induced oxidative stress, hepatic dysfunction and inflammatory changes.
          
          
            Methods
            Hydroethanolic Grape seed (GS) extract was prepared and characterized using high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), inductively coupled plasma–mass spectrometry (ICP-MS) and gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC-MS). Then, GS extract NPs were synthesized and in vitro antioxidant, anticoagulant, cytotoxicity and anti-inflammatory testes confirmed biological activity. Finally, Twenty-five male Sprague-Dawley rats were divided into five groups (n = 5/group). Either GS extract (200 mg/kg/day) or GS extract NPs (100 mg/kg/day) were orally administrated independently to CCL4-intoxicated (0.5 ml/kg twice a week for 3 weeks) rats. Four weeks after the treatment, serum levels of alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALP) were monitored. In addition, hepatic Malondialdehyde (MDA), Superoxide dismutases (SOD), Glutathione (GSH) and catalase (CAT) and hepatic inflammatory cytokines were assessed.
          
          
            Results
            GS extract NPs were spherical-shaped and regular particles (size: 16.5 to 22.5 nm and zeta potential: -39.42 mv). CCL4 -intoxicated rats showed increase of serum ALT, AST, ALP, elevation in MDA level accompanied by a decline in SOD, GSH and CAT levels in liver, compared with CCL4-untreated rats. Immunologically, serum C-Reactive Protein (CRP) and hepatic interleukin 1β (IL-1β), IL-4, IL-6 and Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha (TNF-α) showed significant elevation, compared with CCL4 -untreated rats. Conversely, GS extract NPs supplementation potentially ameliorate hepatic functions by normalization of serum ALT, AST and ALP, reduced MDA level, improved antioxidant CAT, regulated liver inflammatory cytokines via maximal reduction of hepatic IL-1β, IL-4, IL-6 and TNF-α. 
          
          
            Conclusion
            GS extract NPs augmented the antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties of GS extract thereby protecting the liver against oxidative stress induced by CCl4 as hepatic xenobiotic.
          
          
            Clinical trial number
            Not applicable.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05005-7
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05005-7-2025-08-28-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mobilization with movement plus exercise versus exercise alone for patients with central sensitization associated with chronic subacromial pain syndrome: a sham-controlled randomized clinical trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 13
Autoren: Volkan Deniz, Bayram Kelle
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-28
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0-2025-08-28-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Microbiological Risk Assessment and Safety Evaluation of Widely Used Herbal Pharmaceuticals</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 13
Autoren: Naveen Kumar Ramachandrappa, Kalyan Dola, Vakdevi Validandi, Senthilkumar Balakrishnan, Philip Raj Abraham, Aditi Ashutosh Kaledhonkar, SDG Gauthami, K Srinivasu, Surekha Mullapudi Venkata
Journal: Journal of Herbal Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047
ISSN: 2210-8033
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047-2025-08-28-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Facilitating microglial phagocytosis by which Jiawei Xionggui Decoction alleviates cognitive impairment via TREM2-mediated energy metabolic reprogramming</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60927-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 11
Autoren: Wen Wen, Jie Chen, Junbao Xiang, Shiqi Zhang, Jingru Liu, Jie Wang, Ping Wang, Shijun Xu
Journal: Chinese Journal of Natural Medicines
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60927-7
ISSN: 1875-5364
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60927-7-2025-08-28-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>