<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 01:07:03 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 01:07:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Peri-Neuromal Botulinum Toxin Injection for War-Related Postamputation Pain: A Pragmatic, Multicenter, Comparative-Effectiveness Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 352
Autoren: Nadiya Segin, Roman Smolynets, Joana Barroso, Natalia Molinets, Paul F. Pasquina, Steven P. Cohen
Journal: Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026
ISSN: 0003-9993
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026-2025-10-29-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The clinical effects of the Össur Power Knee with phase-based and default control during sitting, standing, and walking</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12984-025-01729-2</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 49
Autoren: T. Kevin Best, C. Andrew Seelhoff, Jeffrey Wensman, Robert D. Gregg
Journal: Journal of NeuroEngineering and Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-29
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            A lack of evidence of compelling clinical benefits is a key factor limiting the adoption of commercialized powered robotic knee prostheses into mainstream clinical practice. Previous studies have demonstrated mixed results, potentially due to a combination of limitations in prosthetic hardware, control algorithms, and testing methodologies.
          
          
            Methods
            We investigated the clinical effects of a commercialized robotic knee prosthesis (the latest generation Össur Power KneeTM) with n=7 above-knee amputee participants. Participants with both higher (K4) and lower mobility (K3) completed a series of experiments including repeated sitting and standing, a stand, walk, sit shuttle test, and fast walking on a treadmill. We tested both standard (ÖSSR) and novel (HKIC) control policies and compared the resulting clinical metrics to those found with the users’ prescribed passive prostheses. Our experiments were physically demanding, which could help elucidate the potential benefits of powered knees.
          
          
            Results
            The clinical effects of the Power Knee varied with mobility level and the control policy used. The phase-based controller often produced stronger walking and sit/stand improvements for the higher mobility group compared to the default controller, though it also presented a steeper learning curve and reduced walk-to-sit transition speed. Conversely, the default control policy was perceived as easier to master but was less assistive to the higher mobility group and produced slower sit/stand cycles. Lower mobility participants experienced improvements in standing speed (HKIC: 
                $$36.7\pm 15.1$$
              % faster, 
                $$p&amp;lt;0.001$$
              ; ÖSSR: 
                $$28.8\pm 15.1$$
              % faster, 
                $$p=0.001$$
              ), inter-limb ground reaction force symmetry (HKIC: 
                $$-0.214\pm 0.068$$
              , 
                $$p&amp;lt;0.001$$
              ; ÖSSR: 
                $$-0.199\pm 0.068$$
              , 
                $$p&amp;lt;0.001$$
              ), and inter-limb peak knee moment symmetry (HKIC: 
                $$-0.290\pm 0.126$$
              , 
                $$p&amp;lt;0.001$$
              ; ÖSSR: 
                $$-0.284\pm 0.126$$
              , 
                $$p&amp;lt;0.001$$
              ) during sit-to-stand tasks relative to their passive prostheses. In contrast, higher mobility participants benefited less in sit/stand but showed improvements while walking including increased toe clearance (HKIC: 
                $$25.4\pm 12.2$$
               mm, 
                $$p&amp;lt;0.001$$
              ; ÖSSR: 
                $$13.4\pm 12.2$$
               mm, 
                $$p=0.033$$
              ), greater early stance knee flexion (HKIC: 
                $$7.1\pm 2.9^\circ $$
              , 
                $$p&amp;lt;0.001$$
              ; ÖSSR: 
                $$4.5\pm 2.9^\circ $$
              , 
                $$p=0.005$$
              ), and, for the HKIC policy, a reduced swing-phase peak hip flexion moment (HKIC: 
                $$-0.18\pm 0.11$$
               Nm/kg/(m/s), 
                $$p=0.003$$
              ). Despite these biomechanical improvements and qualitative reports of reduced effort, neither control policy produced significant benefits in endurance or repeated task performance compared to the passive condition. Sit-to-stand cycle count in the lower mobility group was unchanged (HKIC: 
                $$p=0.268$$
              , ÖSSR: 
                $$p=0.848$$
              ), and it was reduced in the higher mobility group with the ÖSSR condition (
                $$2.0\pm 1.4$$
               fewer, 
                $$p=0.007$$
              ). In the shuttle walk test, laps completed by higher mobility users decreased with HKIC (
                $$157.3\pm 46.3$$
               fewer, 
                $$p&amp;lt;0.001$$
              ), and no significant differences were found for lower mobility users. No significant changes in fast walking distance or speed were observed across conditions.
          
          
            Conclusions
            The latest generation Power Knee can create clinical improvements in walking and sit/stand behaviors compared to passive (microprocessor) knees, though the effects are sensitive to the user’s mobility level and the Power Knee’s control policy. However, these improvements did not directly translate to improved functional performance or endurance. Some negative effects of the Power Knee were also observed including reduced agility, slower transitions, and thermal limitations, though some of these limitations could potentially be addressed through future control innovations or with more thorough acclimation. The observed benefits motivate future longitudinal studies to investigate the clinical effects of robotic knees compared to passive (microprocessor) knees in real-world settings and to elucidate how they could be best utilized in clinical practice.
            
              Trial Registration: The experimental protocol was approved by the University of Michigan Institutional Review Board (HUM00230065) on February 9th, 2024. The trial is registered with the National Institutes of Health under ClinicalTrials.gov ID NCT06138977.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12984-025-01729-2
ISSN: 1743-0003
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12984-025-01729-2-2025-10-29-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Blautia luti reduces neratinib-induced diarrhea in a rat model</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00520-025-09990-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 24
Autoren: Claire P. Vieyra, Micaela J. Quinn, Emma H. Bateman, Hannah R. Wardill, Joanne M. Bowen
Journal: Supportive Care in Cancer
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-14
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Purpose
            Neratinib is a pan-human epidermal growth factor receptor (HER) tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) used in the treatment of HER2+ breast cancer. Diarrhea is the most commonly reported toxicity, with the majority experiencing at least some grade of diarrhea. The mechanisms behind neratinib-induced diarrhea are yet to be fully defined, but have been linked to gut microbiome changes, specifically decreased levels of the genera Blautia. This study aimed to investigate the efficacy of Blautia luti (B.luti) administered as a daily probiotic on neratinib-induced diarrhea, and its effects on the gut microbiome in a well-established rat model.
          
          
            Methods
            Female albino Wistar (AW) rats (n = 40) were randomly allocated to groups including; vehicle control (VC), neratinib alone, B.luti alone and neratinib + B.luti in different schedules (Pre, Pre &amp;amp; Post or Post). Daily oral gavage administration of B.luti (107CFU/ml) was given according to corresponding schedules, alongside a 28-day cycle of neratinib (50 mg/kg). Diarrhea was graded daily, and faecal samples collected for gut microbiome analysis at study end. Ileum and colon samples were collected for intestinal analysis. 16S rRNA gene sequencing was performed on faecal samples and H&amp;amp;E performed on intestinal tissue for injury evaluation.
          
          
            Results
            Grade 3 diarrhea was reduced in the Post group when compared to the neratinib alone group (p = 0.0122). No significant differences were seen in the tissue injury scores of the ileum or colon. There was no significant change in microbial composition with B.luti administration.
          
          
            Conclusion
            This study demonstrated that administration of B.luti supplementation, was effective in reducing neratinib-induced diarrhea severity when consumed concurrently. This administration schedule may have a protective role in the intestines through immunomodulation.
          
DOI: 10.1007/s00520-025-09990-w
ISSN: 0941-4355
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00520-025-09990-w-2025-10-29-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Does resistance training improve pain intensity, quality of life, and disability in people with chronic nonspecific low back pain? A systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/09638288.2025.2566275</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 23
Autoren: Álvaro-José Rodríguez-Domínguez, Jose A. Moral-Munoz, Juan-David Guzmán-Gómez, Javier Valero-Ortiz, Luis González-Gómez, Melania Cardellat-González
Journal: Disability and Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-09
DOI: 10.1080/09638288.2025.2566275
ISSN: 0963-8288
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/09638288.2025.2566275-2025-10-29-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The effectiveness of pain neuroscience education in people with chronic non-specific low back pain: An umbrella review with meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rehab.2025.102020</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 20
Autoren: José García Cancela, Orlando Conde Vázquez, Santiago Navarro Ledesma, Leo Pruimboom
Journal: Annals of Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.rehab.2025.102020
ISSN: 1877-0657
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.rehab.2025.102020-2025-10-29-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>