<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 01:16:31 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 01:16:31 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Ultra-processed food intake is associated with altered glucose homeostasis in young adults with a history of overweight or obesity: a longitudinal study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12986-025-01036-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 357
Autoren: Yiping Li, Elizabeth Costello, Sarah Rock, William B. Patterson, Zhanghua Chen, Frank Gilliland, Michael I. Goran, Tanya L. Alderete, Jesse A. Goodrich, David V. Conti, Nikos Stratakis, Leda Chatzi
Journal: Nutrition &amp;amp; Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-10
DOI: 10.1186/s12986-025-01036-6
ISSN: 1743-7075
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12986-025-01036-6-2025-11-30-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Influence of Ultraprocessed Food Consumption on Energy Intake in Emerging Adulthood: A Controlled Feeding Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.70086</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 346
Autoren: Maria L. M. Rego, Emma Leslie, Emily Schmall, Bailey Capra, Summer Hudson, Monica L. Ahrens, Benjamin Katz, Kevin P. Davy, Valisa E. Hedrick, Alexandra G. DiFeliceantonio, Brenda M. Davy
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-19
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    Objective
                    This study examined the impact of a 2‐week eucaloric diet high in ultraprocessed foods (UPF) compared to a diet without UPF (non‐UPF) on ad libitum energy intake (EI) and food selection in individuals aged 18–25.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    In a randomized, crossover, proof‐of‐concept trial, participants completed two 14‐day controlled feeding periods (81% UPF vs. 0% UPF), with a 4‐week washout. Diets were matched for macronutrients, fiber, added sugar, diet quality, and energy density. Following each condition, participants consumed an ad libitum buffet meal including UPF and non‐UPF. Energy and food grams consumed were quantified. Statistical analyses were conducted for the full sample, late adolescents (aged 18–21), and young adults (aged 22–25).
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Twenty‐seven individuals aged 22 ± 2 years (mean BMI = 24 ± 3 kg/m
                      2
                      ) were included. Diet compliance was ~99% overall. There was no effect of diet condition on meal total kcal or grams consumed or UPF or non‐UPF consumption in the full sample (all
                      p
                       &amp;gt; 0.05). In the exploratory age subgroup analysis, an interaction between diet and age was observed for total EI (
                      p
                       &amp;lt; 0.001), where total EI increased among adolescents following the UPF diet (
                      p
                       = 0.03,
                      d
                       = 0.79), but not in young adults.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    Late adolescents may be susceptible to increased EI following a UPF diet. Future trials are warranted to evaluate this possibility.
                    
                      Trial Registration:
                      ClinicalTrials.gov
                      : NCT05550818.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/oby.70086
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.70086-2025-11-30-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Plant-based dietary index on the Mediterranean and a vegan diet: a secondary analysis of a randomized, cross-over trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1666807</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 279
Autoren: Hana Kahleova, Reagan Smith, Ilana Fischer, Haley Brennan, Tatiana Znayenko-Miller, Richard Holubkov, Neal D. Barnard
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-19
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    The plant-based diet index (PDI) has been proposed as a gauge of diet healthfulness. This study assessed the relationship between the PDI, and the “healthful” hPDI and “unhealthful” uPDI, and weight loss in the context of Mediterranean and vegan diets in overweight adults.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    In a cross-over trial, 62 overweight adults followed a Mediterranean and a low-fat vegan diet for 16 weeks in random order, separated by a 4-week washout. Body weight was the primary outcome. In a secondary analysis, three-day dietary records were analyzed, PDI indices were calculated. Their correlation with changes in body weight was assessed, using Spearman correlations.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Compared with no change on the Mediterranean diet, PDI significantly increased on the vegan diet; effect size: +7.6 (95% CI +4.1 to +11.0);
                      p
                       &amp;amp;lt; 0.001. The hPDI score increased on both diets; effect size: +3.8 (95% CI −0.0 to +7.6);
                      p
                       = 0.05. The uPDI score decreased on the Mediterranean diet, while it increased on the vegan diet; effect size: +11.9 (95% CI +8.9 to +14.8);
                      p
                       &amp;amp;lt; 0.001. In the first 16 weeks of the study, across both diets, changes in PDI and uPDI were negatively associated with changes in body weight, i.e., increases in PDI and uPDI were associated with weight loss:
                      r
                       = −0.32;
                      p
                       = 0.01; and
                      r
                       = −0.47;
                      p
                       &amp;amp;lt; 0.001, respectively. These associations remained significant even after adjustment for changes in energy intake. No association was observed between changes in hPDI and changes in body weight.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    These findings suggest that, replacing animal products even with the “unhealthful” plant-based foods on a vegan diet was associated with weight loss.
                  
                  
                    Clinical trial registration
                    
                      ClinicalTrials.gov
                      , identifier NCT03698955.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1666807
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1666807-2025-11-30-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Nutrient adequacy and environmental foot-print of Mediterranean, pesco-, ovo-lacto-, and vegan menus: a modelling study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1681512</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 207
Autoren: Ángela Alcalá-Santiago, Noelia M. Rodríguez-Martín, Eduardo Casas-Albertos, José María Gálvez-Navas, Adela Castelló-Pastor, Belén García-Villanova, Esther Molina-Montes
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-11
Abstract: 
                    Background
                    Consumer food choices are changing towards a more plant-based diet (PBD) due to growing awareness of their less detrimental effects on health and the environment. However, PBDs—particularly vegan diets—may lead to nutritional deficiencies compared to non-PBDs. These differences may, in part, be influenced by the typically lower caloric content of PBDs.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    To compare the nutritional adequacy and environmental footprints of four 7-day menu models (~ 2,000 kcal/day) Mediterranean (omnivorous) diet, two vegetarian-like diets, and one vegan.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Menus were designed based on the recommendations of the Spanish Society for Community Nutrition (SENC) and Vegetarian Union (UVE), substituting animal-based foods with plant-based alternatives. Nutritional intake was assessed using the Spanish BEDCA food composition table (Base de Datos Española de Composición de Alimentos) and adequacy was evaluated using Dietary Reference Intakes (DRIs) and recommended intake levels. Daily environmental footprints were estimated with Agribalyse. Differences between the four diet models were evaluated by one-way ANOVA or Kruskal-Wallis tests, followed by post-hoc analyses to identify pairwise differences in nutrient intake (significance level: 95%).
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Daily macronutrient intake did not differ substantially across the diet groups. Furthermore, all four menus met protein needs and most micronutrient DRIs. Shortfalls were observed for vitamin D and iodine across all diets, and for vitamin B₁₂ in the vegan model;
                      ω
                      -3 PUFA were below the 250 mg/day target in all diets, while saturated fat remained &amp;amp;lt; 8% of total energy intake. Mean daily environmental footprints decreased progressively from omnivorous to vegan diets: −46% CO₂, −6.6% deprived water and −33% land use among others.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Well-planned PBDs can achieve comparable sustainability and nutritional adequacy to a healthy Mediterranean diet, although attention is required to ensure adequate intake of certain micronutrients.
                  
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1681512
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1681512-2025-11-30-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Adipose Tissue in
                    SARS
                    ‐
                    CoV
                    ‐2 Viral Tropism, Viral Replication, and the Concept of a Viral Reservoir: An Update</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.70093</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 161
Autoren: Liam Charles Maher, Paul M. Ryan, Noel M. Caplice
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-24
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  Since the onset of the COVID‐19 pandemic, obesity has been consistently associated with worse clinical outcomes. In 2020, we hypothesized that adipose tissue (AT) might serve as a viral reservoir and amplifier of immune responses in SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Five years on, accumulating evidence supports this hypothesis. Recent autopsy and in vitro studies support that SARS‐CoV‐2 disseminates to and may replicate within human adipocytes. While several studies have detected SARS‐CoV‐2 RNA and proteins in AT, the recovery of infectious virus from this tissue has not yet been demonstrated. This remains a critical gap in our understanding of SARS‐CoV‐2 viral tropism and replication within adipocytes. Viral entry is mediated via angiotensin‐converting enzyme‐2 and neuropilin‐1 receptors. Infected AT exhibits immune cell infiltration and cytokine activation, implicating it in systemic inflammation. Persistent viral RNA in AT correlates with prolonged metabolic dysfunction. These findings highlight the dual role of AT as a potential viral reservoir and immunometabolic organ. Understanding these mechanisms is critical to mitigating the long‐term impact of COVID‐19 and guiding responses to future pandemics involving metabolically active tissues.
                  
                    
                      
                        image
                      
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/oby.70093
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.70093-2025-11-30-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>