<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 01:05:00 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 01:05:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Evaluating gender bias in large language models in long-term care</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 122
Autoren: Sam Rickman
Journal: BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-11
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Large language models (LLMs) are being used to reduce the administrative burden in long-term care by automatically generating and summarising case notes. However, LLMs can reproduce bias in their training data. This study evaluates gender bias in summaries of long-term care records generated with two state-of-the-art, open-source LLMs released in 2024: Meta’s Llama 3 and Google Gemma.
          
          
            Methods
            Gender-swapped versions were created of long-term care records for 617 older people from a London local authority. Summaries of male and female versions were generated with Llama 3 and Gemma, as well as benchmark models from Meta and Google released in 2019: T5 and BART. Counterfactual bias was quantified through sentiment analysis alongside an evaluation of word frequency and thematic patterns.
          
          
            Results
            The benchmark models exhibited some variation in output on the basis of gender. Llama 3 showed no gender-based differences across any metrics. Gemma displayed the most significant gender-based differences. Male summaries focus more on physical and mental health issues. Language used for men was more direct, with women’s needs downplayed more often than men’s.
          
          
            Conclusion
            Care services are allocated on the basis of need. If women’s health issues are underemphasised, this may lead to gender-based disparities in service receipt. LLMs may offer substantial benefits in easing administrative burden. However, the findings highlight the variation in state-of-the-art LLMs, and the need for evaluation of bias. The methods in this paper provide a practical framework for quantitative evaluation of gender bias in LLMs. The code is available on GitHub.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0
ISSN: 1472-6947
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12911-025-03118-0-2025-09-07-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>AI as an independent second reader in detection of clinically relevant breast cancers within a population-based screening programme in the Netherlands: a retrospective cohort study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landig.2025.100882</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 96
Autoren: Suzanne L van Winkel, Jim Peters, Natasja Janssen, Jaap Kroes, Elizabeth A Loehrer, Jessie Gommers, Ioannis Sechopoulos, Linda de Munck, Jonas Teuwen, Mireille Broeders, Nico Karssemeijer, Ritse M Mann
Journal: The Lancet Digital Health
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.landig.2025.100882
ISSN: 2589-7500
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.landig.2025.100882-2025-09-07-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Culture-free detection of bacteria from blood for rapid sepsis diagnosis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01948-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 73
Autoren: M. Henar Marino Miguélez, Mohammad Osaid, Erik Hallström, Kerem Kaya, Jimmy Larsson, Vinodh Kandavalli, Carolina Wählby, Johan Elf, Wouter van der Wijngaart
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-25
Abstract: Abstract
          Approximately 50 million people suffer from sepsis yearly, and 13 million die from it. For every hour a patient with septic shock is untreated, their survival rate decreases by 8%. Therefore, rapid detection and antibiotic susceptibility profiling of bacterial agents in the blood of sepsis patients are crucial for determining appropriate treatment. Here, we introduce a method to isolate bacteria from whole blood with high separation efficiency through Smart centrifugation, followed by microfluidic trapping and subsequent detection using deep learning applied to microscopy images. We detected, within 2 h, E. coli, K. pneumoniae, or E. faecalis from spiked samples of healthy human donor blood at clinically relevant concentrations as low as 9, 7 and 32 colony-forming units per ml of blood, respectively. However, the detection of S. aureus remains a challenge. This rapid isolation and detection represents a significant advancement towards culture-free detection of bloodstream infections.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01948-w
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01948-w-2025-09-07-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Assessing genotype−phenotype correlations in colorectal cancer with deep learning: a multicentre cohort study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landig.2025.100891</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 60
Autoren: Marco Gustav, Marko van Treeck, Nic G Reitsam, Zunamys I Carrero, Chiara M L Loeffler, Asier Rabasco Meneghetti, Bruno Märkl, Lisa A Boardman, Amy J French, Ellen L Goode, Andrea Gsur, Stefanie Brezina, Marc J Gunter, Neil Murphy, Pia Hönscheid, Christian Sperling, Sebastian Foersch, Robert Steinfelder, Tabitha Harrison, Ulrike Peters, Amanda Phipps, Jakob Nikolas Kather
Journal: The Lancet Digital Health
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.landig.2025.100891
ISSN: 2589-7500
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.landig.2025.100891-2025-09-07-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Web-Based Video Intervention and Associated Factors for the Uptake of the Catch-Up Human Papillomavirus Vaccination in Japan: Randomized Controlled Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/67778</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 44
Autoren: Toshiki Yoshioka, Atsushi Goto, Taichi Mizushima, Yukio Suzuki, Yutaka Ueda, Asami Yagi, Masayuki Sekine, Risa Kudo, Suzanne M Garland, Suresh Kumarasamy, Ida Ismail-Pratt, Katharina Reimer, Etsuko Miyagi, Asia Pacific HPV Coalition
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-15
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            In Japan, the human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccination rate has dropped to nearly zero since the suspension of proactive government recommendations in 2013. Following the termination of vaccination suspension in 2021 and subsequent proactive vaccination recommendation in 2022, it is crucial to promote catch-up vaccinations for those who missed their initial opportunity.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aims to evaluate the effect of video-based informational intervention and explore factors associated with the uptake of catch-up HPV vaccinations among unvaccinated young adult women in Japan.
          
          
            Methods
            In this randomized, parallel, single-blinded, internet-based trial, we recruited women aged 18‐26 years unvaccinated for HPV through a web-based research panel. The participants were randomly assigned (1:1) to receive either an educational leaflet containing information on the HPV vaccine and a short narrative video (intervention) or the leaflet alone (control). The primary outcome was the difference in proportion between both groups regarding the uptake of the free catch-up vaccinations at the follow-up survey after 3 months. No deviations from the registered protocol occurred during the study.
          
          
            Results
            We enrolled 4065 women in the trial and randomly assigned them to either the intervention (2274 women) or the control (2331 women) group. Of these, we excluded 2595 women (63.8%) who did not respond to the follow-up survey, resulting in 1017 and 993 women in the intervention and control groups, respectively, for the final analysis. At the 3-month follow-up, 11.3% (228/2010) of the participants received at least one catch-up vaccine dose. The intervention and control groups had 10.5% (107/1017) and 12.2% (121/993) uptake, respectively. The difference in proportions between both groups was −1.7% (95% CI −4.5 to 1.2%; P=.26), and the adjusted difference was −1.6% (95% CI −4.3 to 1%; P=.23). In the subgroup analysis, the intervention group had a lower proportion of catch-up vaccination among sexually experienced women who had previous sexual intercourse experience (difference in proportion −5%, 95% CI −10% to −1%; P=.03) and those who had undergone a Pap test within the past 2 years (difference in proportion −11%, 95% CI −20% to −1%; P=.03). In addition, in the overall sample, factors positively associated with catch-up vaccination included higher educational background (difference in proportion: 7%, 95% CI 4%-10%; P&amp;lt;.001) and having undergone a Pap test within the past 2 years (difference in proportion 5%, 95% CI 0%-9%, P=.06).
          
          
            Conclusions
            Our study demonstrated that video-based interventions did not have a substantial impact on the uptake of catch-up HPV vaccinations among young adults. However, our subgroup analyses suggested that the effectiveness of interventions may vary depending on individual characteristics. It is therefore desirable to explore and tailor more effective strategies based on the background and needs of specific populations in real-world settings.
          
DOI: 10.2196/67778
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/67778-2025-09-07-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>