<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 01:01:28 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 01:01:28 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>1-year risks of cancers associated with COVID-19 vaccination: a large population-based cohort study in South Korea</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s40364-025-00831-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 2412
Autoren: Hong Jin Kim, Min-Ho Kim, Myeong Geun Choi, Eun Mi Chun
Journal: Biomarker Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-26
Abstract: Abstract
          The oncogenic potential of SARS-CoV-2 has been hypothetically proposed, but real-world data on COVID-19 infection and vaccination are insufficient. Therefore, this large-scale population-based retrospective study in Seoul, South Korea, aimed to estimate the cumulative incidences and subsequent risks of overall cancers 1 year after COVID-19 vaccination. Data from 8,407,849 individuals between 2021 and 2023 were obtained from the Korean National Health Insurance database. The participants were categorized into two groups based on their COVID-19 vaccination status. The risks for overall cancer were assessed using multivariable Cox proportional hazards models, and data were expressed as hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs). The HRs of thyroid (HR, 1.351; 95% CI, 1.206–1.514), gastric (HR, 1.335; 95% CI, 1.130–1.576), colorectal (HR, 1.283; 95% CI, 1.122–1.468), lung (HR, 1.533; 95% CI, 1.254–1.874), breast (HR, 1.197; 95% CI, 1.069–1.340), and prostate (HR, 1.687; 95% CI, 1.348–2.111) cancers significantly increased at 1 year post-vaccination. In terms of vaccine type, cDNA vaccines were associated with the increased risks of thyroid, gastric, colorectal, lung, and prostate cancers; mRNA vaccines were linked to the increased risks of thyroid, colorectal, lung, and breast cancers; and heterologous vaccination was related to the increased risks of thyroid and breast cancers. Given the observed associations between COVID-19 vaccination and cancer incidence by age, sex, and vaccine type, further research is needed to determine whether specific vaccination strategies may be optimal for populations in need of COVID-19 vaccination.
DOI: 10.1186/s40364-025-00831-w
ISSN: 2050-7771
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s40364-025-00831-w-2025-10-06-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Heat-related mortality in Europe during 2024 and health emergency forecasting to reduce preventable deaths</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03954-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 909
Autoren: Tomáš Janoš, Marcos Quijal-Zamorano, Natalia Shartova, Elisa Gallo, Raúl Fernando Méndez Turrubiates, Nadia Denisse Beltrán Barrón, Fabien Peyrusse, Joan Ballester
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-22
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03954-7
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03954-7-2025-10-06-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Full-spectrum extract from Cannabis sativa DKJ127 for chronic low back pain: a phase 3 randomized placebo-controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03977-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 688
Autoren: Matthias Karst, Winfried Meissner, Sabine Sator, Jens Keßler, Volker Schoder, Winfried Häuser
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-29
Abstract: Abstract
          Chronic low back pain (CLBP) affects over half a billion people worldwide. Current pharmacologic treatments offer limited efficacy and carry substantial risks, warranting the development of safe and effective alternatives. This multicenter, randomized, placebo-controlled phase 3 trial evaluated the efficacy and safety of VER-01 in CLBP. It enrolled 820 adults with CLBP (VER-01, n = 394; placebo, n = 426) and included a double-blind 12-week treatment phase (phase A), a 6-month open-label extension (phase B), followed by either a 6-month continuation (phase C) or randomized withdrawal (phase D). The primary endpoint of phase A was a change in mean numeric rating scale (NRS) pain intensity, with a change in total neuropathic pain symptom inventory (NPSI) score as a key secondary endpoint in participants with a neuropathic pain component (PainDETECT &amp;gt; 18). The primary endpoint for phase D was time to treatment failure. The study met its primary endpoint in phase A, with a mean pain reduction of −1.9 NRS points in the VER-01 group (mean difference (MD) versus placebo = −0.6, 95% confidence interval (CI) = −0.9 to −0.3; P &amp;lt; 0.001). Pain further decreased to −2.9 NRS points in phase B, with effects sustained through phase C. The study also met its key secondary endpoint of phase A, with a mean NPSI decrease of −14.4 (standard error, 3.3) points from baseline in the VER-01 arm (MD versus placebo = −7.3, 95% CI = −13.2 to −1.3; P = 0.017). Although phase D did not meet its primary endpoint (hazard ratio = 0.75, 95% CI = 0.44–1.27; P = 0.288), pain increased significantly more with placebo upon withdrawal (MD = 0.5, 95% CI = 0.0–1.0; P = 0.034). In phase A, the incidence of adverse events—mostly mild to moderate and transient—was higher with VER-01 than with placebo (83.3% versus 67.3%; P &amp;lt; 0.001). VER-01 was well-tolerated, with no signs of dependence or withdrawal. VER-01 shows potential as a new, safe and effective treatment for CLBP. ClinicalTrials.gov registration: NCT04940741.
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03977-0
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03977-0-2025-10-06-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Progression to rheumatoid arthritis in at-risk individuals is defined by systemic inflammation and by T and B cell dysregulation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.adt7214</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 558
Autoren: Ziyuan He, Marla C. Glass, Pravina Venkatesan, Marie L. Feser, Leander Lazaro, Lauren Y. Okada, Nhung T. T. Tran, Yudong D. He, Samir Rachid Zaim, Christy E. Bennett, Padmapriyadarshini Ravisankar, Elisabeth M. Dornisch, Alexandra C. Ferrannini, Najeeb A. Arishi, Ashley G. Asamoah, Saman Barzideh, Lynne A. Becker, Elizabeth A. Bemis, Jane H. Buckner, Christopher E. Collora, Megan A. L. Criley, M. Kristen Demoruelle, Chelsie L. Fleischer, Jessica Garber, Palak C. Genge, Qiuyu Gong, Lucas T. Graybuck, Claire E. Gustafson, Brian C. Hattel, Veronica Hernandez, Alexander T. Heubeck, Erin K. Kawelo, Upaasana Krishnan, Emma L. Kuan, Kristine A. Kuhn, Christian M. LaFrance, Kevin J. Lee, Ruoxin Li, Cara Lord, Regina R. Mettey, Laura Moss, Blessing Musgrove, Katherine HY Nguyen, Andrea Ochoa, Vaishnavi Parthasarathy, Mark-Phillip Pebworth, Chong Pedrick, Tao Peng, Cole G. Phalen, Julian Reading, Charles R. Roll, Jennifer A. Seifert, Marguerite D. Siedschlag, Cate Speake, Christopher C. Striebich, Tyanna J. Stuckey, Elliott G. Swanson, Hideto Takada, Tylor Thai, Zachary J. Thomson, Nguyen Trieu, Vlad Tsaltskan, Wei Wang, Morgan D. A. Weiss, Amy Westermann, Fan Zhang, David L. Boyle, Ananda W. Goldrath, Thomas F. Bumol, Xiao-jun Li, V. Michael Holers, Peter J. Skene, Adam K. Savage, Gary S. Firestein, Kevin D. Deane, Troy R. Torgerson, Mark A. Gillespie
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-24
Abstract: 
            Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is preceded by an at-risk stage of disease that can be marked by the presence of anticitrullinated protein antibodies (ACPAs) but the absence of clinically apparent synovitis (clinical RA). Preemptive intervention in at-risk individuals could prevent or delay future tissue damage; however, the immunobiology of this stage is unclear. Using integrative multiomics, we longitudinally profiled at-risk individuals, where one-third of participants developed clinical RA on study. We found evidence of systemic inflammation and signatures of activation in naïve T and B cells of at-risk individuals. During progression to clinical RA, proinflammatory skewing of atypical B cells and expansion of memory CD4 T cells with signatures of activation and B cell help were present without elevations in circulating ACPA titers. Epigenetic changes in naïve CD4 T cells suggested a predisposition to differentiate into effector cells capable of B cell help. These findings characterize pathogenesis of the ACPA
            +
            at-risk stage and support the concept that the disease begins much earlier than clinical RA. Additionally, an extensive immune resource of the at-risk stage and progression to clinical RA with interactive tools was developed to enable further investigation.
          
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.adt7214
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.adt7214-2025-10-06-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Longitudinal antibody titers measured after COVID-19 mRNA vaccination can identify individuals at risk for subsequent infection</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.adv4214</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 388
Autoren: Hyeongki Park, Naotoshi Nakamura, Sho Miyamoto, Yoshitaka Sato, Kwang Su Kim, Kosaku Kitagawa, Yurie Kobashi, Yuta Tani, Yuzo Shimazu, Tianchen Zhao, Yoshitaka Nishikawa, Fumiya Omata, Moe Kawashima, Toshiki Abe, Yoshika Saito, Saori Nonaka, Morihito Takita, Chika Yamamoto, Hiroshi Morioka, Katsuhiro Kato, Ken Sagou, Tetsuya Yagi, Takeshi Kawamura, Akira Sugiyama, Aya Nakayama, Yudai Kaneko, Risa Yokokawa Shibata, Kazuyuki Aihara, Tatsuhiko Kodama, Akifumi Kamiyama, Tomokazu Tamura, Takasuke Fukuhara, Kenji Shibuya, Tadaki Suzuki, Shingo Iwami, Masaharu Tsubokura
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-17
Abstract: A key issue in the post–COVID-19 pandemic era is the ongoing administration of COVID-19 vaccines. Repeated vaccination is essential for preparing against currently circulating and newly emerging severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) variants. However, optimizing vaccination strategies is crucial to efficiently manage medical resources and establish an effective vaccination framework. Therefore, a strategy to identify poor responders with lower sustained antibody titers would be beneficial because these individuals should be considered high priority for revaccination. We investigated longitudinal antibody titer data in a cohort of 2526 people in Fukushima, Japan, collected between April 2021 and November 2022. Using mathematical modeling and machine learning, we stratified the time-course patterns of antibody titers after two primary doses and one booster dose of COVID-19 messenger RNA vaccines. We identified three populations, which we refer to as the durable, the vulnerable, and the rapid-decliner populations, and approximately half of the participants remained in the same population after the booster dose. The rapid-decliner population experienced earlier infections than the others. Furthermore, when comparing spike protein–specific immunoglobulin G (IgG) titers, spike protein–specific IgA titers, and SARS-CoV-2–specific T cell responses between participants who experienced subsequent infections after booster vaccination and those who did not, we found that spike protein–specific IgA titers were lower during the early stage after booster vaccination in participants who went on to become infected with SARS-CoV-2. This approach could be used to inform policy decisions on vaccine distribution to maximize population-level immunity both in future pandemics and in the post–COVID-19 pandemic era.
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.adv4214
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-06</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.adv4214-2025-10-06-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>