<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 01:06:01 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 01:06:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Impact of Preoperative Progressive Relaxation Exercises on Postoperative Pain, Comfort, and Recovery</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1097/hnp.0000000000000702</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 364
Autoren: Nurşen Kulakaç, Aylin Aydın Sayılan
Journal: Holistic Nursing Practice
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
Abstract: 
                    
                    
                      This randomized controlled trial aimed to investigate the impact of preoperative progressive relaxation exercises on postoperative pain, comfort, and quality of recovery. The study was conducted between June and November 2023, involving 68 patients undergoing surgical intervention and hospitalized in the surgical clinic. Data were collected using the Personal Information Form, the Visual Analog Scale (VAS)-Pain, the Perianesthesia Comfort Scale, and the Quality of Recovery Questionnaire. At the sixth postoperative hour, no significant difference was observed in pain levels between the experimental and control groups (
                      P
                      &amp;gt; .05). However, the VAS scores for the experimental group at the 12th and 24th postoperative hours were significantly lower than those of the control group (
                      P
                      &amp;lt; .001). Furthermore, 24 hours postoperatively, the experimental group demonstrated significantly higher quality of recovery (
                      P
                      &amp;lt; .001) and comfort levels (
                      P
                      &amp;lt; .001) than the control group. This study concludes that patients engaged in relaxation exercises exhibited lower VAS scores and higher levels of recovery and comfort.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1097/hnp.0000000000000702
ISSN: 0887-9311
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1097/hnp.0000000000000702-2025-11-12-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Differential oxido-reductive activities of aged garlic extract and S-allyl-cysteine in genetically modified Drosophila model of Alzheimer’s disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05093-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 25
Autoren: Olasunmbo Afolayan, Victor Nwaogu, Olumayowa Idowu, Olufunke Dosumu
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-21
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05093-5
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05093-5-2025-11-12-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Laboratory cultivated Cordyceps militaris modulates cockroach allergen-induced inflammation in keratinocytes and macrophages dual cell platforms</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Mey-Fann Lee, Jane-Yii Wu, Chi-Sheng Wu, Ching-Chun Lin, Yu-Wen Chu
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-15
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1-2025-11-12-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effectiveness and safety of turmeric for the treatment of COVID-19: An updated systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ctim.2025.103295</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Ratree Sawangjit, Saranrat Sadoyu, Siripong Manosanthipaibul, Nattawat Teerawattanapong, Panupong Puttarak, Kulthanit Wanaratna, Rawiwan Charoensup, Poonsit Hiransai, Thunyaluk Meetam, Nathorn Chaiyakunapruk
Journal: Complementary Therapies in Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ctim.2025.103295
ISSN: 0965-2299
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ctim.2025.103295-2025-11-12-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and safety of Shugan Jieyu capsules in combination with zolpidem for insomnia disorder with depressive symptoms: a double-blind randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Qianqian Xin, Dhirendra Paudel, Jiehan Zhang, Huafeng Wei, Yihong Cheng, Yan Xu, Ruichen Fang, Jinnong Jiang, Yuling Wang, Bin Zhang
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z-2025-11-12-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>