<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 01:09:00 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 01:09:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Undiagnosed G6PD Deficiency in Black and Asian Individuals Is Prevalent and Contributes to Health Inequalities in Type 2 Diabetes Diagnosis and Complications</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2337/dc25-0556</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 1137
Autoren: Susan Martin, Miriam Samuel, Daniel Stow, Alys M. Ridsdale, Ji Chen, Katherine G. Young, Harry D. Green, Andrew T. Hattersley, Veline L’Esperance, Trevelyan J. McKinley, Sarah Finer, Inês Barroso, Genes &amp; Health Research Team, Eamonn Maher, Shabana Chaudhary, Joseph Gafton, Karen A. Hunt, Shapna Hussain, Kamrul Islam, Hilary Martin, Mohammed Bodrul Mazid, Elizabeth Owor, Jessry Russell, Nishat Safa, John Solly, Marie Spreckley, David A. Van Heel, Jan Whalley, Ishevanhu Zengeya, Emily Mantle, Shaheen Akhtar, Samina Ashraf, Dan Mason, John Wright, Daniel MacArthur, Michael Simpson, Richard C. Trembath, Gerome Breen, Raymond Chung, Sang Hyuck Lee, Omar Asgar, Joanne Harvey, Karen Tricker, Caroline Winckley, Hanifa Khatun, Amna Asif, Claudia Langenberg, Grainne Colligan, Ceri Durham, Bill Newman, Ahsan Khan, Teng Heng, Matt Hurles, Vivek Iyer, Georgios Kalantzis, Vladimir Ovchinnikov, Iaroslav Popov, Klaudia Walter, Panos Deloukas, David Collier, Ana Angel, Saeed Bidi, Fabiola Eto, Sarah Finer, Chris Griffiths, Sam Hodgson, Benjamin M. Jacobs, Rohini Mathur, Caroline Morton, Asma Qureshi, Stuart Rison, Annum Salman, Miriam Samuel, Moneeza K. Siddiqui, Daniel Stow, Sabina Yasmin, Julia Zöllner, Sheik Dowlut
Journal: Diabetes Care
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-30
Abstract: 
                  OBJECTIVE
                  Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency presents silently and is not routinely screened. It is associated with markedly lower HbA1c for the prevailing glucose levels. Since HbA1c is internationally recommended to diagnose and manage type 2 diabetes (T2D), we investigated the population-level impact of undiagnosed G6PD deficiency on T2D diagnosis and complications in the U.K.
               
               
                  RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS
                  We used whole-exome sequencing and electronic health record data from UK Biobank (n = 467,368) and Genes &amp;amp; Health (n = 43,011) cohorts.
               
               
                  RESULTS
                  In the U.K., we estimated that ∼1 in 7 Black and 1 in 63 Asian males carry G6PD deficiency alleles, compared with fewer than 1 in 10,000 White males. Despite this, less than 1 in 50 G6PD-deficient men are clinically recognized. Male G6PD carriers have considerably lower average HbA1c (0.9% [International Federation of Clinical Chemistry and Laboratory Medicine: 10.0 mmol/mol]) compared with noncarriers, while differences in average glucose were negligible. G6PD-deficient men had 1.37 (95% CI: 1.01, 1.86) higher odds of developing diabetes-related microvascular complications than noncarriers. Although risk factors were similar prior to diagnosis, male G6PD carriers diagnosed with T2D since 2011 were, on average, 4.1 years (95% CI: 0.6, 7.7) older at diagnosis compared with noncarriers. In addition, lower mean HbA1c values in G6PD carriers falsely underestimated their 10-year T2D risk.
               
               
                  CONCLUSIONS
                  Undiagnosed G6PD deficiency has significant impact on T2D diagnosis with HbA1c and associates with increased risk of diabetes complications. This has major implications for global populations using HbA1c for diagnosis and monitoring, and could contribute significantly to inequalities in diabetes outcomes.
               
DOI: 10.2337/dc25-0556
ISSN: 0149-5992
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2337/dc25-0556-2025-10-19-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of ultra-processed food consumption on male reproductive and metabolic health</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.08.004</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 959
Autoren: Jessica M. Preston, Jo Iversen, Antonia Hufnagel, Line Hjort, Jodie Taylor, Clara Sanchez, Victoria George, Ann N. Hansen, Lars Ängquist, Susan Hermann, Jeffrey M. Craig, Signe Torekov, Christian Lindh, Karin S. Hougaard, Marcelo A. Nóbrega, Stephen J. Simpson, Romain Barrès
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.08.004
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.08.004-2025-10-19-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Fructose and glucose from sugary drinks enhance colorectal cancer metastasis via SORD</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s42255-025-01368-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 598
Autoren: Tianshi Feng, Qin Luo, Yanlin Liu, Zeyu Jin, David Skwarchuk, Rumi Lee, Miso Nam, John M. Asara, Daya R. Adye, Philip L. Lorenzi, Lin Tan, Guangsheng Pei, Zhongming Zhao, Neda Zarrin-Khameh, Adriana Paulucci-Holthauzen, Brian W. Simons, Ju-Seog Lee, Scott Kopetz, Jihye Yun
Journal: Nature Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-19
Abstract: Abstract
          The consumption of sugar-sweetened beverages (SSBs), which contain high levels of fructose and glucose, has been causally and mechanistically linked to an increased risk of colorectal cancer (CRC). However, the effects of SSB consumption on advanced stages of disease progression, including metastasis, remain poorly understood. Here we show that exposure of CRC cells to a glucose and fructose formulation—reflecting the composition of both high-fructose corn syrup and sucrose found in SSBs—enhances cellular motility and metastatic potential compared to glucose alone. Given that CRC cells grow poorly in fructose alone, and cells in vivo are not physiologically exposed to fructose without glucose, we excluded the fructose-only condition from our studies unless needed as a control. Mechanistically, the combination of glucose and fructose elevates the NAD⁺/NADH ratio by activation of the reverse reaction of sorbitol dehydrogenase in the polyol pathway. This redox shift relieves NAD⁺ limitations and accelerates glycolytic activity, which in turn fuels activation of the mevalonate pathway, ultimately promoting CRC cell motility and metastasis. Our findings highlight the detrimental impact of SSBs on CRC progression and suggest potential dietary and therapeutic strategies to mitigate metastasis in patients with CRC.
DOI: 10.1038/s42255-025-01368-w
ISSN: 2522-5812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s42255-025-01368-w-2025-10-19-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Once-weekly semaglutide 7·2 mg in adults with obesity (STEP UP): a randomised, controlled, phase 3b trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00226-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 587
Autoren: Sean Wharton, Paula Freitas, Jøran Hjelmesæth, Maria Kabisch, Kristian Kandler, Ildiko Lingvay, Maria Quiroga, Julio Rosenstock, W Timothy Garvey
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00226-8
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00226-8-2025-10-19-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Paternal exercise confers endurance capacity to offspring through sperm microRNAs</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.003</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 398
Autoren: Xin Yin, Azhar Anwar, Linbo Yan, Ranran Yu, Yang Luo, Liang Shi, Botao Li, Jiehao Chen, Gaoli Liang, Yongci Chen, Jie Tang, Jie Liang, Yansheng Kan, Zhihao Zhang, Xiahuan Zhou, Jizheng Ma, Chenbo Ji, Yanbo Wang, Qipeng Zhang, Jing Li, Liang Li, Xiaozhi Zhao, Feng Yin, Liyuan Sheng, Dijun Chen, Tao Zhang, Chen-Yu Zhang, Xi Chen
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.003
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.003-2025-10-19-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>