<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:59:52 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:59:52 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Pig-to-human lung xenotransplantation into a brain-dead recipient</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03861-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 1496
Autoren: Jianxing He, Jiang Shi, Chao Yang, Guilin Peng, Chunrong Ju, Yi Zhao, Hui Liu, Ping He, Xiaoqing Liu, Zuopeng Zhang, Chuanbao Chen, Dengke Pan, Zifeng Yang, Wenda Guang, Hongtao Li, Zhonghua Chen, Menyang Liu, Hengrui Liang, Weiqing Huang, Kyeongman Jeon, Toyofumi F. Chen-Yoshikawa, A. Justin Rucker, Amos Lal, Nanshan Zhong, Kang Zhang, Xiaoyou Liu, Xin Xu
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-25
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03861-x
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03861-x-2025-09-16-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Interplay of genetic predisposition, plasma metabolome and Mediterranean diet in dementia risk and cognitive function</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03891-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 945
Autoren: Yuxi Liu, Xiao Gu, Yanping Li, Fenglei Wang, Chirag M. Vyas, Cheng Peng, Danyue Dong, Yuhan Li, Yu Zhang, Yin Zhang, Oana A. Zeleznik, Jae H. Kang, Molin Wang, Frank B. Hu, Walter C. Willett, Olivia I. Okereke, A. Heather Eliassen, Peter Kraft, Meir J. Stampfer, Dong D. Wang
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-25
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03891-5
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03891-5-2025-09-16-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>An mRNA-based broad-spectrum antiviral inspired by ISG15 deficiency protects against viral infections in vitro and in vivo</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.adx5758</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 679
Autoren: Yemsratch T. Akalu, Roosheel S. Patel, Justin Taft, Rodrigo Canas-Arranz, Rachel Geltman, Ashley Richardson, Sofija Buta, Marta Martin-Fernandez, Christos Sazeides, Rebecca L. Pearl, Gayatri Mainkar, Andrew P. Kurland, Haylen Rosberger, Diana D. Kang, Ann Anu Kurian, Keerat Kaur, Jennie Altman, Yizhou Dong, Jeffrey R. Johnson, Lior Zangi, Jean K. Lim, Randy A. Albrecht, Adolfo García-Sastre, Brad R. Rosenberg, Dusan Bogunovic
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-13
Abstract: Type I interferons (IFN-Is) are cytokines with potent antiviral and inflammatory capacities. IFN-I signaling drives the expression of thousands of IFN-I–stimulated genes (ISGs), whose aggregate function results in the control of viral infections. A few of these ISGs are tasked with negatively regulating the IFN-I response to prevent overt inflammation. ISG15 is a negative regulator whose absence leads to persistent, low-grade elevation of ISG expression and concurrent, often self-resolving, mild autoinflammation. The limited breadth and low-grade persistence of ISGs expressed in ISG15 deficiency are sufficient to confer broad-spectrum antiviral resistance. Inspired by the antiviral state of humans with ISG15 deficiency, we identified a nominal collection of 10 ISGs that recapitulated the broad antiviral potential of the IFN-I system, which typically induces the expression of thousands of ISGs. The expression of this 10-ISG collection in an IFN-I–nonresponsive cell line increased cellular resistance to Zika virus, vesicular stomatitis virus, and severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). A lipid nanoparticle–encapsulated messenger RNA (mRNA) formulation of this 10-ISG collection reduced influenza A virus plaque size in samples collected from infected mice when given prophylactically. Moreover, when used collectively and delivered prophylactically, the 10-ISG collection was able to protect hamsters against a lethal SARS-CoV-2 challenge, in contrast with the lack of efficacy when mRNAs were delivered individually. These findings suggest that these 10 ISGs have potential as a broad-spectrum antiviral prophylactic.
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.adx5758
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.adx5758-2025-09-16-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Dietary saturated fatty acids promote lung myeloid cell inflammasome activation and IL-1β–mediated inflammation in mice and humans</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 441
Autoren: Sam J. McCright, Olivia Harding, Julia Chini, Nicole DeMarco, Li-Yin Hung, Christopher F. Pastore, Wenyun Lu, Joshua Rabinowitz, Jorge Henao-Mejia, De’Broski R. Herbert, Lisa R. Young, David A. Hill
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-27
Abstract: Resident tissue macrophages and monocytes (RTMs) integrate local and systemic signals to coordinate immune cell function at homeostasis and in response to inflammatory stimuli. Obesity-associated metabolic dysfunction drives the development of RTM populations that contribute to disease states in multiple tissues. However, the contribution of specific dietary components to innate immune cell activation and function, as opposed to the direct effects of obesity, is largely unknown. Here, we studied the mechanisms by which high-fat (HF) diets shape lung RTM phenotype and function at steady state and influence responses to inflammatory insults. We found that, during HF diet feeding, lung RTMs accumulate saturated long-chain fatty acids, specifically stearic acid (SA), and demonstrate features of NLRP3 inflammasome priming and activation. In vivo, increased dietary SA was sufficient to cause neutrophil-predominant lung inflammation in the steady state and exacerbate a model of innate airway inflammation, whereas increased dietary oleic acid, the monounsaturated counterpart of SA, was sufficient to reduce inflammasome activation in the steady state and attenuate airway inflammation. Depletion of interleukin-1β (IL-1β) or pharmacologic inhibition of the endonuclease inositol requiring enzyme 1α (IRE1α) protected against SA-induced exacerbated lung inflammation. Last, we identified a population of lung monocytes with hallmarks of HF diet–induced RTM activation that were present in samples from obese humans with asthma. Together, these results identify a class of dietary lipids that regulate lung RTM phenotype and function in the steady state and modulate the severity of inflammation in the lung.
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653-2025-09-16-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Steroid hormone biosynthesis and dietary related metabolites associated with excessive daytime sleepiness</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.105881</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 339
Autoren: Tariq Faquih, Kaitlin S. Potts, Pavithra Nagarajan, Bing Yu, Robert Kaplan, Carmen R. Isasi, Qibin Qi, Kent D. Taylor, Peter Y. Liu, Satu J. Strausz, Hanna M. Ollila, Tianyi Huang, Russell P. Tracy, Craig Johnson, Stephen S. Rich, Clary B. Clish, Jerome I. Rotter, Susan Redline, Tamar Sofer, Heming Wang
Journal: eBioMedicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.105881
ISSN: 2352-3964
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.105881-2025-09-16-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>