<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 01:18:03 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 01:18:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Personalized Spine Surgery in Adult Deformity: Reoperation Rates and Mechanical Complications Following Customized Planning and Interbody Implant Use</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/21925682251409696</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 46
Autoren: Justin S. Smith, Chun-Po Yen, Roland Kent, Sigurd Berven, Gregory M. Mundis, Robert Robinson, Rodrigo J. Nicolau, Joseph A. Osorio, Jahangir Asghar, J. Rush Fisher, Kelli M. Howell, Mark Tantorski, Donald Blaskiewicz, Jeffrey P. Mullin, Joseph Gjolaj, John Small, Christopher P. Ames
Journal: Global Spine Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-20
Abstract: 
                    Study Design
                    Retrospective cohort study.
                  
                  
                    Objectives
                    Prior studies have shown that adult spinal deformity (ASD) patients undergoing revision surgery due to mechanical complications had less radiographic improvement and worsening patient-reported outcomes scores. The combination of customized 3D planning and personalized implants has been shown to contribute to improved achievement of alignment goals. This study aimed to determine whether such improved correction also results in a correspondingly lower revision surgery rate due to mechanical complications.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Pre- and postoperative radiographic alignment measures, including lumbar lordosis (LL), distal lumbar lordosis (DLL), pelvic incidence (PI) – LL mismatch, and L1 pelvic angle (L1PA), as well as data on mechanical complications leading to reoperation were collected on 115 ASD patients with personalized interbody implants and minimum 2-year follow-up. This cohort was statistically compared to a multicenter dataset (ISSG) of 997 ASD patients treated using stock devices and using the same reoperation classifications.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Postoperatively achieved alignment measures correlated significantly with their respective preoperative alignment goals, with the following average offsets from plan: 2.4° LL, −0.2° DLL, −2.4° PI-LL, 0.3° L1PA. Compared to the ISSG cohort that utilized stock interbody implants, the cohort utilizing 3D preoperative planning and personalized interbody implants resulted in significantly fewer revisions for mechanical complications up to 2 years postoperatively: 5/115 (4.3%) vs 166/997 (16.6%),
                      P
                      &amp;lt; 0.001.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    These findings suggest that achieving planned alignment targets with personalized interbody devices is associated with reduced revision surgery for mechanical complications, a result which may have positive implications for improved patient outcomes and reduced cost.
                  
DOI: 10.1177/21925682251409696
ISSN: 2192-5682
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/21925682251409696-2026-01-11-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Patient Concerns Are Often Overlooked by Low Back Pain (LBP) Guidelines</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2026.9001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 24
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: Infographic illustrating the article “People With Acute Low Back Pain Have Concerns That May Not Be Addressed by Guideline-Recommended Advice: A Mixed-Methods Study”, which was published in the September 2024 issue of JOSPT.
                  J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2026;56(1):64. doi:10.2519/jospt.2026.9001
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2026.9001
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2026.9001-2026-01-11-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Pediatric virtual fracture clinic. Our first 10K!</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.injury.2025.112928</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 17
Autoren: Flavia Alberghina, Paula Kelly, Jacques Noël, Carol Blackburn, Turlough Bolger, Patrick Kiely, Jim Kennedy, Ciara Egan, David Moore, Patrick O'Toole
Journal: Injury
Veröffentlicht: 2026-02-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.injury.2025.112928
ISSN: 0020-1383
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.injury.2025.112928-2026-01-11-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Bridging the Gap: A Systematic Evidence and Gap Map of Risk Factors and Preventive Strategies for Patellofemoral Pain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13489</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 13
Autoren: Ronaldo Valdir Briani, Lisa Hoglund, Marina Cabral Waiteman, Gamze Arın Bal, Michelle Boling, Helder dos Santos Lopes, Saleh Alsaleh, Natanael Batista, Neal Glaviano, Volga Bayrakci Tunay, Joshua Stefanik, Kai-Yu Ho, Claudio Belvedere, Christopher Powers, David M. Bazett-Jones, Jessica Bell, Paulo Roberto Garcia Lucareli, Sinead Holden
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-15
Abstract: OBJECTIVE: To systematically review, map, and appraise the existing prospective evidence on risk factors for, and preventive strategies against, the development of patellofemoral pain (PFP), and to identify key gaps.
                  DESIGN: Systematic Evidence and Gap Map (EGM).
                  LITERATURE SEARCH: Nine electronic databases (PubMed, CINAHL, PEDro, Scopus, SPORTDiscus, Embase, Cochrane, Web of Science, CENTRAL) were searched from inception to the end of March 2024.
                  STUDY SELECTION CRITERIA: Published prospective observational studies and randomized controlled trials (RCTs) investigating the development of PFP in individuals without baseline PFP were included. Studies of other knee conditions, older adults (mean age &amp;gt;45), or retrospective designs were excluded.
                  DATA SYNTHESIS: Evidence was mapped across the following domains: sociodemographic, neurobiological, anthropometric, psychological, biomechanical, and behavioural.
                  RESULTS: From 57,897 identified records, 36 studies were included: 24 prospective observational studies and 12 RCTs. Most studies focused on biomechanical risk factors (n = 22), with limited exploration of psychological (n = 1), behavioural (n = 2), and neurobiological (n = 1) domains. Preventive interventions involved orthoses (n = 4), exercise (n = 3), bracing (n = 2), gait retraining (1), stretching (1), or running intensity/volume modification. Non-biomechanical strategies such as education or graded exposure were rarely tested. Risk of bias was low to moderate for most prospective observational studies and moderate to high for most RCTs.
                  CONCLUSION: This evidence and gap map reveals an over-reliance on biomechanical perspectives within the context of PFP risk factor research, with limited attention to psychosocial, behavioural, and load-related risk factors. Preventive trials are few, often low in quality, and narrowly focused. Addressing these evidence gaps is essential for developing effective, multifactorial prevention strategies for PFP.
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13489
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13489-2026-01-11-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effectiveness and Cost-effectiveness of an Internet-Based Self-management Program for People With Chronic Pain: A Randomized Controlled Trial With Economic Evaluation (the ReabilitaDOR Trial)</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13418</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 10
Autoren: Bruno T. Saragiotto, Iuri Fioratti, Felipe J. J. Reis, Junior V. Fandim, Vitor Vallio, Leonardo O.P. Costa, Chris G. Maher, Tiê P. Yamato, Gisela C. Miyamoto
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: OBJECTIVE: To investigate the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of an Internet-based self-management program compared with an online booklet for people with chronic musculoskeletal pain.
                  DESIGN: Parallel-group, randomized controlled superiority trial with economic evaluation conducted in Brazil.
                  METHODS: Patients with chronic musculoskeletal pain were randomly allocated to receive an Internet-based self-management program (ReabilitaDOR) or an online booklet. Participants were recruited from university- and community-based physical therapy clinics and through social media. The primary outcome was pain intensity at 8 weeks. The secondary outcomes were function; quality of life; kinesiophobia; global perceived effect; anxiety and depression; pain catastrophizing; pain-related attitudes and beliefs; self-efficacy; and adverse effects at 8 weeks, 6 months, and 12 months after randomization. The economic evaluation from the societal perspective was conducted for pain intensity and quality-adjusted life years (QALYs).
                  RESULTS: We included 162 participants (ReabilitaDOR, n = 83; online booklet, n = 79). There was no statistically significant difference in pain intensity between groups at 8 weeks (mean difference: −0.74; 95% confidence interval: −1.5, 0.04), and no significant differences in the secondary outcomes. From a societal perspective, the intervention had a 0.98 probability of being cost-effective at a willingness-to-pay threshold of $200 per point of improvement in pain intensity and 0.63 at a willingness-to-pay threshold of $50 000 per QALY gained compared to the control group.
                  CONCLUSION: An Internet-based self-management program was not superior to an online booklet for chronic musculoskeletal pain. The Internet-based self-management program seemed to be a cost-effective intervention for pain intensity, but not for QALYs. These findings should be interpreted with caution due to high dropout rates and the trial running during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2026;56(1):38-49. Epub 30 October 2025. doi:10.2519/jospt.2025.13418
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13418
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13418-2026-01-11-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>