<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 00:59:10 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 00:59:10 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Multi-institutional, randomized, controlled trial to assess the efficacy and tolerability of a reusable, self-contained cryotherapy delivery device</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00520-025-09795-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 59
Autoren: Richard Zuniga, Vikas Dembla, Naheed Alam, Chaitali Nangia, Thomas Guerrero-Garcia, Gina Chung, Ebenezer Kio, Mylene Go, Erev Tubb, Stephen Sonis, Frank Jacobucci
Journal: Supportive Care in Cancer
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-31
DOI: 10.1007/s00520-025-09795-x
ISSN: 0941-4355
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00520-025-09795-x-2025-08-30-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association of Long COVID With Vision Difficulties Among Adults in the United States</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/0145482x251365588</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 33
Autoren: Mona Pathak, Sophie Mitra, Chan Shen, Hao Wang, Patricia A. Findley, R. Constance Wiener, Usha Sambamoorthi
Journal: Journal of Visual Impairment &amp;amp; Blindness
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
Abstract: 
            Introduction:
            Emerging research associates long COVID with the ocular system, including vision difficulties. This study determines the association of long COVID with vision difficulties among U.S. adults.
            Methods:
            We used a cross-sectional observational study design of 2022 Census Household Pulse Survey adult data (
            N
             = 51,288). COVID status was defined as follows: “long COVID”: those with new symptoms 3 months or longer after COVID infection; “short-term COVID”: those who had COVID but no long COVID symptoms; and “no COVID”: those who have never had COVID. The vision categories were suggested by the Washington Group Short Set on Functioning: no difficulty, some difficulty, a lot of difficulty, and cannot do at all. Rao-Scott Chi-square tests and multinomial logistic regression (adjusted for COVID status, sex, age, race and ethnicity, marital status, poverty, education, food insecurity, health insurance, region, remote work, COVID vaccine, depression, and anxiety), with replicate weights were used.
            Results:
            The study included 51,288 respondents. There were 31.3% who had some vision difficulty, and 4.2% had a lot of difficulty or were unable to see. The proportion who reported that they had long COVID was 14.4%. A higher percentage of adults with long COVID reported vision difficulties than those without COVID (47.6% vs. 31.9%). Adults with long COVID had greater odds of reporting a lot of difficulty or cannot do at all (AOR = 1.47, 95%CI = 1.19, 1.81) and some difficulty seeing (AOR = 1.47, 95%CI = 1.27, 1.70) compared to adults without COVID. We did not observe a statistically significant association of short-term COVID with vision difficulties compared to adults without COVID.
            Discussion:
            One in seven U.S. adults had long COVID. Adults with long COVID had higher odds of vision difficulties than those without COVID. Further research is needed on long COVID and vision difficulties and subsequent vision care.
            Implications for Practitioners:
            A follow-up study of patients with long COVID needs to include screening for vision difficulties.
          
DOI: 10.1177/0145482x251365588
ISSN: 0145-482X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/0145482x251365588-2025-08-30-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cervical flexion posture during smartphone use was not a risk factor for neck pain, but low sleep quality and insufficient levels of physical activity were. A longitudinal investigation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 28
Autoren: Igor Macedo Tavares Correia, Arthur de Sá Ferreira, Jessica Fernandez Mosqueira Gomes, Felipe José Jandre Reis, Leandro Alberto Calazans Nogueira, Ney Meziat-Filho
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258-2025-08-30-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Traumatic Brain Injury and Accelerated Epigenetic Aging Among Post-9/11 Veterans</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1097/htr.0000000000001096</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 27
Autoren: Kyle J. Bourassa, Sarah L. Martindale, Melanie E. Garrett, Allison E. Ashley-Koch, Jean C. Beckham, Nathan A. Kimbrel, Jared A. Rowland
Journal: Journal of Head Trauma Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-19
Abstract: 
            Objective:
            Military service over the last several decades has been associated with an increased risk of injuries, including traumatic brain injury (TBI). Veterans with a history of TBI often experience poor health outcomes and have higher rates of premature mortality. In this study, we examined whether accelerated biological aging could help explain negative health outcomes following TBI.
          
          
            Setting, participants, and design:
            We evaluated the association between TBI and rate of epigenetic aging (assessed using DunedinPACE) using data from post-9/11 veterans (N = 1152) enrolled in the VA Mid-Atlantic (VISN 6) MIRECC Post-Deployment Mental Health cohort study.
          
          
            Main measures:
            TBI was assessed using self-report during a clinical interview categorized into three TBI groups (none, 1, 2 +), epigenetic aging was assessed using DunedinPACE derived from DNA methylation data.
          
          
            Results:
            Veterans who reported more lifetime TBI (β = 0.07, 95% CI [0.01, 0.14], P = .029) or deployment-related TBI (β = 0.09, 95% CI [0.01, 0.18], P = .046) had faster epigenetic aging. TBI during and after military service was more strongly associated with accelerated aging than TBI prior to military service, and deployment-related TBI was more strongly associated with accelerated aging for women veterans. Overall, associations were small to moderate in size.
          
          
            Conclusion:
            These findings show TBI could increase risk for accelerated aging and underscores its potential utility in identifying veterans who may face aging-related health issues. Early identification of TBI-related accelerated aging could inform interventions that mitigate long-term health risks as post-9/11 veterans transition into middle and older age.
          
DOI: 10.1097/htr.0000000000001096
ISSN: 0885-9701
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1097/htr.0000000000001096-2025-08-30-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Pain Science in Practice (Part 8): Nociceptive, Neuropathic, and Nociplastic Pain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13335</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 24
Autoren: Morten Hoegh, Paul Hodges
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract:  Synopsis: Identifying pain descriptors provides a way to tailor pain management based on presumed underlying mechanisms. The aim is to use mechanistic pain descriptors (nociceptive, neuropathic, and nociplastic pain) to guide clinical practice into an era of personalized medicine for people with pain. Clinicians should understand the concept of descriptors to improve their understanding of a mechanism-based management of chronic pain. Nonetheless, all treatment of individuals suffering from chronic pain should be holistic (ie, person-centered). Nociplastic pain already serves as an evidence-based explanation that can help make sense of pain without any known pathology, but is not ready to be considered as a target for treatment in itself, based on the current level of evidence. To summarize, treatment outcomes may improve when treatments are matched to patients according to mechanistic descriptors. Current research initiatives are working on bring this closer to the clinic. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2025;55(9):1-6. Epub 29 July 2025. doi:10.2519/jospt.2025.13335 
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13335
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13335-2025-08-30-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>