<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 01:14:19 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 01:14:19 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Weightlifting outperforms voluntary wheel running for improving adiposity and insulin sensitivity in obese mice</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101100</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 699
Autoren: Robert J. Shute, Ryan N. Montalvo, Wenqing Shen, Yuntian Guan, Qing Yu, Mei Zhang, Zhen Yan
Journal: Journal of Sport and Health Science
Veröffentlicht: 2026-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101100
ISSN: 2095-2546
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101100-2026-01-14-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Advancing Age Is Not Associated With Greater Exercise-Induced Muscle Damage: A Systematic Review, Meta-Analysis, and Meta-Regression</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1123/japa.2024-0165</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 213
Autoren: John F.T. Fernandes, Laura J. Wilson, Amelia F. Dingley, Andrew N. Hearn, Kelsie O. Johnson, Kirsty M. Hicks, Craig Twist, Lawrence D. Hayes
Journal: Journal of Aging and Physical Activity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
Abstract: 
                    
                      Objective
                      :
                    
                    The aim of this paper was to undertake a Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analysis-accordant meta-analysis comparing exercise-induced muscle damage (EIMD) in older and younger adults.
                    
                      Methods
                      :
                    
                    Google Scholar, PubMed, and SPORTDiscus were searched in June 2023 for the terms “ageing” OR “age” OR “middle-aged” OR “old” OR “older” OR “elderly” OR “masters” OR “veteran” AND “muscle damage” OR “exercise-induced muscle damage” OR “exercise-induced muscle injury” OR “contraction-induced injury” OR “muscle soreness” OR “delayed onset muscle soreness” OR “creatine kinase.” From 1,092 originally identified titles, 36 studies were included which had an exercise component comparing a younger against an older group. The outcome variables of EIMD were muscle function, muscle soreness, and creatine kinase. A meta-analysis was conducted on change to EIMD after exercise in older versus younger adults using standardized mean difference (SMD) and an inverse-variance random effects model.
                    
                      Results
                      :
                    
                    Change after 24 and 72 hr, and peak change, in muscle function was not different between old and young (SMD range = −0.16 to −0.35). Muscle soreness was greater in younger than older adults for all comparisons (SMD range = −0.34 to −0.62). Creatine kinase was greater in younger than older adults at 24 hr (SMD = −0.32), as was peak change (SMD = −0.32). A relationship between sex and peak muscle function change was evident for males (SMD = −0.45), but not females (SMD = −0.44). All other meta-regression was nonsignificant.
                    
                      Conclusion
                      :
                    
                    Advancing age is not associated with greater symptoms of EIMD. The implication of this study is that the older adults can pursue regular physical activity without concern for experiencing greater EIMD.
                  
DOI: 10.1123/japa.2024-0165
ISSN: 1063-8652
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1123/japa.2024-0165-2026-01-14-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>It is not all about strength: rethinking mechanistic assumptions in exercise-based rehabilitation for musculoskeletal pain relief</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2025-110372</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 94
Autoren: Jared Powell, Lianne Wood, Aidan Gregory Cashin, Jeremy S Lewis
Journal: British Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-31
DOI: 10.1136/bjsports-2025-110372
ISSN: 0306-3674
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bjsports-2025-110372-2026-01-14-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Impact of Biological Sex and Female Sex Hormone Concentration on the Maximal Metabolic Steady State</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1152/japplphysiol.00913.2025</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 75
Autoren: Mira I. Schoeberlein, Jake H. Hudgins, Olivia DeVelasco, Brad W. Wilkins
Journal: Journal of Applied Physiology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-29
Abstract: PURPOSE: The goal was to explore the impact of fluctuating female sex hormone concentrations on the work rate delineating sustainable from unsustainable work rates at the heavy–severe domain boundary or maximal metabolic steady state (MMSS).
                  
                    METHODS: Thirty endurance trained participants (15 F / 15 M; V̇O
                    2MAX
                    48.1 ± 5.2 vs 57.3 ± 5.3 ml·min
                    −1
                    ·kg
                    −1
                    ; P = 0.001) completed four MMSS estimation protocols at distinct sex hormone profiles. Serum sex hormone concentrations, specifically estradiol, progesterone, and testosterone, were determined during each study visit. To identify MMSS at each hormone profile, participants completed a muscle oxygenation (%SmO
                    2
                    ) zero-slope prediction cycling protocol once a week for four weeks. The %SmO
                    2
                    zero-slope protocol consisted of four, 4-min stages (2-min rest) spanning intensity domains. The work rate associated with MMSS was determined using linear regression analysis between workload and %SmO
                    2
                    signal slope during the final 2 min of each stage.
                  
                  RESULTS: Linear mixed models showed male sex to be a significant predictor of power at MMSS (p &amp;lt; 0.001), but changes in sex hormone concentrations were not associated with changes in MMSS work rate. No sex differences in MMSS were found when normalized to lean body mass (LBM) (P = 0.224) nor across the four visits (P = 0.074).
                  CONCLUSIONS: The LBM normalized work rate at MMSS was similar between men and women. Fluctuations in sex hormone profile in women were not associated with differences in the heavy–severe exercise domain boundary, nor were there any observed sex differences across distinct hormone profiles.
DOI: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00913.2025
ISSN: 8750-7587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1152/japplphysiol.00913.2025-2026-01-14-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Coronary artery calcification in type 1 diabetes after 10-year ketogenic diet</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1152/japplphysiol.00893.2025</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 62
Autoren: Andrew P. Koutnik, Belinda S. Lennerz, Larry C. Deeb, Joseph C. Watso
Journal: Journal of Applied Physiology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
Abstract: In males with type 1 diabetes (T1D), 30–70% have a coronary artery calcification (CAC) score &amp;gt;1 in their thirties. The data in this case report indicate zero detectable CAC in a 30–39-yr-old male with T1D who followed a ketogenic diet for 10 years despite having an elevated low-density lipoprotein and no lipid-lowering medication. This suggests an absence of atherosclerotic plaque formation, despite concerns about the long-term cardiovascular consequences of a ketogenic diet.
DOI: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00893.2025
ISSN: 8750-7587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1152/japplphysiol.00893.2025-2026-01-14-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>