<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 01:00:13 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 01:00:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Baseline individual factors associated with clinical outcomes in adults with non-specific low back pain following manual therapy: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Gaetan Barbier, Mathieu Picchiottino, Arnaud Delafontaine, Guillaume Goncalves, André Bussières, François Cottin, Arnaud Lardon
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y-2025-10-07-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Factors associated with acupuncture treatment use among middle-aged and older adults with low back pain in China</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05086-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Yifan Lei, Xinyu Xia, Xinyun Huang, Zhihua Jiao, Chunling Bao, Xiaopeng Ma
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-30
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05086-4
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05086-4-2025-10-07-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The effect of danshen ligustrazine injection as adjuvant therapy on serum levels of salusins, catestatin, MMP-2, MMP-9, and TIMP-1 in patients with primary hypertension</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05017-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Dezhi Hong, Changzhang He, Wenjie Dai, Mingchun Zhong, Chengwei Xu, Shengqiang Zeng, Changsheng Ouyang, Hengli Lai
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05017-3
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05017-3-2025-10-07-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Herbal medicines and blood pressure control among hypertensive individuals across two of trinidad’s regional health facilities</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05080-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: A. F. Williams-Persad, G. Carvalho, S. Baboolal, A. Brereton, K. Chinemilly, M. Premchand, R. Ramdial, A. Ramroop, P. Richards, T. Seepersad
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-30
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05080-w
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05080-w-2025-10-07-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Urinary oxytocin levels in children meeting a Hospital Dog®</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05076-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: A. Risberg, A. Larsson, U. Bodén, A. Edner
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-08
Abstract: 
            Abstract
            There has been growing interest in animal-assisted therapy (AAT) in recent decades due to increasing reports indicating its health benefits for adult patients. These benefits are partly attributed to changes, usually increased levels of the neuropeptide oxytocin. 
          
          
            Aim
            To investigate changes in oxytocin levels in hospitalized children meeting a certified Hospital Dog®.
          
          
            Method
            Urine samples were collected between 25/02/2016 and 24/05/2017 from 35 hospitalized children (3–17 years) before and after each participant had a session with the Hospital Dog®. Oxytocin levels were analysed with an acetylcholinesterase (AChE) competitive enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). Creatinine levels were measured to determine the subject’s fluid intake and then divided by the hormonal concentration (uOT pg/ml).
          
          
            Results
            The mean level of uOT was 186.0 ± 236.7 (51.5–1349.5) pg/ml before and 137.3 ± 121.5 (30.7–591.3) pg/ml after the dog session (p = 0.010).
          
          
            Conclusion
            Decreased levels of uOT were recorded during the study in which hospitalized children met a Hospital Dog®. The decreased OT levels are potentially the result of the intense activity the subject experienced with the dog during the interaction.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05076-6
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-07</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05076-6-2025-10-07-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>