<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 01:03:49 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 01:03:49 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Baseline individual factors associated with clinical outcomes in adults with non-specific low back pain following manual therapy: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Gaetan Barbier, Mathieu Picchiottino, Arnaud Delafontaine, Guillaume Goncalves, André Bussières, François Cottin, Arnaud Lardon
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y-2025-10-12-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The effect of danshen ligustrazine injection as adjuvant therapy on serum levels of salusins, catestatin, MMP-2, MMP-9, and TIMP-1 in patients with primary hypertension</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05017-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Dezhi Hong, Changzhang He, Wenjie Dai, Mingchun Zhong, Chengwei Xu, Shengqiang Zeng, Changsheng Ouyang, Hengli Lai
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05017-3
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05017-3-2025-10-12-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Herbal medicines and blood pressure control among hypertensive individuals across two of trinidad’s regional health facilities</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05080-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: A. F. Williams-Persad, G. Carvalho, S. Baboolal, A. Brereton, K. Chinemilly, M. Premchand, R. Ramdial, A. Ramroop, P. Richards, T. Seepersad
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-30
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05080-w
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05080-w-2025-10-12-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Antimalarial potential of Matricaria chamomilla-derived MgO nanoparticles against Plasmodium falciparum strains: an experimental study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05081-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Zahra Farzaneh, Haleh Hanifian, Mehdi Nateghpour, Gholamreza Hasanpour, Ahmad Raeisi, Mohammad Shabani, Leila Farivar, Aram Khezri, S. Ahmad Dehdast, Saeed Shahsavari
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-08
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05081-9
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05081-9-2025-10-12-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Chitosan nanocarriers loaded with Egyptian Calligonum comosum L'Hér. Extract: an eco-friendly approach for investigating triple-action biological activities</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Yasser I. Khedr, Soliman M. Toto, Salama M. El-Darier, Mostafa K. Hafez, Abdel-Hamid A. Sakr, Magdi A. Ali, Mohamed Zakaria El-Sayed, Aya M. Helal
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-24
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            
              Calligonum comosum L’Hér. is a large perennial shrub that grows in the desert. This plant inhabits much of the Egyptian desert, but has not yet been scientifically validated. Herein, we demonstrate the antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, and anticancer properties of the ethanolic extract of the Egyptian C. comosum (CE) and its novel eco-friendly chitosan nano-formula (CE/CsNPs), which is prepared using citrate as a crosslinker.
          
          
            Methods
            The produced plant ethanolic extract (CE) was chemically analyzed. The eco-friendly CE/CsNPs were successfully developed through the conjugation of CE with different concentrations (200, 350, and 400 mg/100 mL) within the chitosan nanoparticle; then, it was fully characterized for the determination of the optimum formula and followed by the assessment of the antioxidant effects, proinflammatory cytokines, evaluation of cytotoxicity against different types of cancer cell lines, and estimation of antimicrobial effects of CE and CE/CsNPs.
          
          
            Results
            The eco-friendly CE/CsNPs-2 encapsulating 350 mg of CE was selected for the in vitro studies, as it displayed NPs with a small size and a surface charge of 37.7 ± 1.91 mV with the best encapsulation efficiency (70.15 ± 1.58%) within the CsNPs, and it showed a good release profile. Transmission electron microscope (TEM) images confirmed the discrete spherical shape of CE/CsNPs-2, with no aggregations, and revealed a size range of 49.69 to 71.93 nm. FTIR displayed the successful incorporation of CE into the eco-friendly CsNPs. Regarding their biological activity, CE/CsNPs have superior efficacy with high cytotoxicity against cancer cell lines and antioxidant effects. RT-qPCR gene expression assessments displayed that CE/CsNPs resulted in a remarkable downregulation of the inflammatory cytokines’ mRNA transcript levels (p &amp;lt; 0.05). It enhanced the antimicrobial effect, with an inhibition zone of 12.34 ± 0.75 mm for Escherichia coli, 16.41 ± 1.01 mm for Staphylococcus aureus, and 18.74 ± 1.13 mm for Candida albicans.
          
          
            Conclusions
            The CE possesses various biological activities, and the developed CE/CsNPs could serve as an appealing formulation to be further investigated for use in anticancer regimens.
          
          
            Graphical Abstract
            Synthesis of eco-friendly chitosan nanoparticles loaded with ethanolic extract of C. comosum (CE/CsNPs) by using citrate as an organic cross-linker. The optimum CE/CsNPs formulation loaded with 350 mg/100 mL of the extract with the highest entrapment efficiency (EE)% is a promising anticancer candidate, displaying anticancer, antioxidant, and antimicrobial in vitro potencies.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x-2025-10-12-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>