<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 01:08:23 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 01:08:23 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Understanding the research landscape of over-the-counter herbal products, dietary supplements, and medications evaluated for depressive symptoms in adults: a scoping review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2025.1609605</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 300
Autoren: Rachael Frost, Aiman Zamri, Silvy Mathew, Adriana Salame, Cini Bhanu, Sukvinder K. Bhamra, Juan Carlos Bazo-Alvarez, Michael Heinrich, Kate Walters
Journal: Frontiers in Pharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-15
Abstract: BackgroundOver-the-counter (OTC) products such as herbal medical products (HMPs) or dietary supplements are a valued part of preventative and supportive self-care for depressive symptoms, but there is a wide array of products available, with differing levels of clinical evidence. It is unclear what the optimal directions for future research in this field are.AimWe aimed to explore the size and nature of the evidence base available for OTC products for depression in adults aged 18–60.MethodsWe carried out a scoping review following Joanna Briggs Institute guidance. We searched MEDLINE, Embase, PsycINFO, AMED, and CENTRAL from inception to December 2022, and 10% of the results were screened by two authors and the remainder by one author. We included randomised controlled trials of products commonly available OTC in multiple countries in participants with symptoms or a diagnosis of depression. Results were narratively summarised by the product and volume of evidence available.ResultsOut of 23,933 records found, we screened 1,367 full texts and included 209 trials. The largest volume of evidence was for omega-3s, St John’s Wort, saffron, probiotics, and vitamin D. Among a range of herbal medical products with promising evidence, those most commonly used and thus warranting further research were lavender, lemon balm, chamomile, and Echium. For 41 products, we found only single trials. Few products presented safety issues, whether used alone or adjunctively with antidepressants.ConclusionProducts with limited but promising evidence included folic acid, lavender, zinc, tryptophan, Rhodiola, and lemon balm, and future research should focus on these products. There is a need for further evaluation of herbal medical products as adjuncts to antidepressants and for exploring their potential benefits when used adjunctively with psychological therapies to support a more integrative approach. Safety reporting in these trials needs to be further improved.Systematic Review Registration:https://osf.io/rkm57/.
DOI: 10.3389/fphar.2025.1609605
ISSN: 1663-9812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fphar.2025.1609605-2025-08-13-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A Timeline of Reckoning: Tracking the Historical Rise of Antimicrobial Resistance Across HIV, TB, and Malaria</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jgar.2025.07.014</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 137
Autoren: Tayla Williamson, Jack Adderley, Kylie Quinn, Taane G Clark, Sharon R Lewin, Christian Doerig
Journal: Journal of Global Antimicrobial Resistance
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jgar.2025.07.014
ISSN: 2213-7165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jgar.2025.07.014-2025-08-13-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Investigating Zinc Migration from Rigid Needle Shield to Drug Formulation in Needle Tip of Pre-filled Syringe</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11095-025-03888-2</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 60
Autoren: Guangli Hu, Chengbei Li, Kaitlin Wang, Yongchao Su, William Forrest, Jeffrey Givand, Dario Ferreira Sanchez, Margie Olbinado, Matthias Wagner, Christian Grünzweig, Vladimir Novak
Journal: Pharmaceutical Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-29
DOI: 10.1007/s11095-025-03888-2
ISSN: 0724-8741
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s11095-025-03888-2-2025-08-13-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Oral apigenin prevents obesity-related muscular atrophy, but not obesity itself, in middle-aged rats fed a high-calorie diet</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118342</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 56
Autoren: Josimar Macedo de Castro, Alanis da Silva Melo, Beatriz Lima Silveira, Igor Antônio Souza Martins, Maielli Martins Marçal, Tenille Dal Bosco, Melina Belén Keingeski, Elisa Carolina Lange de Oliveira, Mario Reis Alvares-da-Silva, Patrick Türck, Alex Sander da Rosa Araujo, Layane Ramos Ayres, Lucas Stahlhöfer Kowalewski, Mariana Kras Borges Russo, Mauricio Krause, Dirson João Stein, Iraci L.S. Torres
Journal: Biomedicine &amp;amp; Pharmacotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118342
ISSN: 0753-3322
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118342-2025-08-13-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Static vs. cidal: it’s not complex; it’s simply incorrect</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.00513-25</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 54
Autoren: Brad Spellberg, Noah Wald-Dickler, Paul Holtom, Pascal Meyer-Sautter, Austin Camp, Alejandro Diaz Diaz, Ranya Buhamad, Ali Sebastian Meza Vazquez, Gloria Mayela Aguirre-Garcia, Matthew Stanton, Susan M. Butler-Wu, Isabelle Chiu, Zeynep Ergenc, Guru Bhoojhawon, Rita Murri, Alberto Enrico Maraolo, Gabriela Cabanilla, Niccolò Riccardi, Vhudzani Tshisevhe, Curtis Behenna, Karen S. Williams, Wesley D. Kufel, Natalia Wojciaczyk, Bernardo Vidal Pimentel, Ahmed Muyidi, Rodrigo P.L. Costa, Fabrizio Motta, Émilie Bortolussi-Courval, Todd C. Lee, Emily McDonald, Bassam Ghanem, Zachary Nelson
Journal: Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-21
DOI: 10.1128/aac.00513-25
ISSN: 0066-4804
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1128/aac.00513-25-2025-08-13-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>