<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:17:19 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:17:19 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Epstein-Barr virus reprograms autoreactive B cells as antigen-presenting cells in systemic lupus erythematosus</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.ady0210</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 1784
Autoren: Shady Younis, Salvinaz I. Moutusy, Sajede Rasouli, Shaghayegh Jahanbani, Mahesh Pandit, Xiaohao Wu, Suman Acharya, Orr Sharpe, Tilini U. Wijeratne, Marlayna L. Harris, Emily Y. Yang, Yashaar Chaichian, Shima Parsafar, Matthew C. Baker, John B. Harley, Eric Meffre, Lawrence Steinman, Ann Marshak-Rothstein, Judith A. James, Olivia M. Martinez, Paul J. Utz, Dana E. Orange, Tobias V. Lanz, William H. Robinson
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-12
Abstract: 
                    Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a systemic autoimmune disease characterized by antinuclear antibodies (ANAs). Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) infection has been epidemiologically associated with SLE, yet its role in pathogenesis remains incompletely defined. Here, we developed an EBV-specific single-cell RNA-sequencing platform and used it to demonstrate that EBV infection reprograms autoreactive antinuclear antigen B cells to drive autoimmunity in SLE. We demonstrated that, in SLE, EBV
                    +
                    B cells are predominantly CD27
                    +
                    CD21
                    low
                    memory B cells that are present at increased frequencies and express
                    ZEB2
                    ,
                    TBX21
                    (T-bet), and antigen-presenting cell transcriptional pathways. Integrative analysis of chromatin immunoprecipitation sequencing (ChIP-seq), assay for transposase-accessible chromatin sequencing (ATAC-seq), and RNA polymerase II occupancy data revealed EBV nuclear antigen 2 (EBNA2) binding at the transcriptional start sites and regulatory regions of 
                    CD27
                    , 
                    ZEB2
                    , and
                    TBX21
                    , as well as the antigen-presenting cell genes demonstrated to be up-regulated in SLE EBV
                    +
                    B cells. We expressed recombinant antibodies from SLE EBV
                    +
                    B cells and demonstrated that they bind prototypical SLE nuclear autoantigens, whereas those from healthy individuals do not. We further found that SLE EBV
                    +
                    B cells can serve as antigen-presenting cells to drive activation of T peripheral helper cells with concomitant activation of related EBV
                    −
                    antinuclear double-negative 2 B cells and plasmablasts. Our results provide a mechanistic basis for EBV being a driver of SLE through infecting and reprogramming nuclear antigen-reactive B cells to become activated antigen-presenting cells with the potential to promote systemic disease–driving autoimmune responses.
                  
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.ady0210
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.ady0210-2025-11-23-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Physical activity as a modifiable risk factor in preclinical Alzheimer’s disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 772
Autoren: Wai-Ying Wendy Yau, Dylan R. Kirn, Jennifer S. Rabin, Michael J. Properzi, Aaron P. Schultz, Zahra Shirzadi, Kailee Palmgren, Paola Matos, Courtney Maa, Jeremy J. Pruzin, Stephanie A. Schultz, Rachel F. Buckley, Dorene M. Rentz, Keith A. Johnson, Reisa A. Sperling, Jasmeer P. Chhatwal
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-03
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6-2025-11-23-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Successful endodontic treatment improves glucose and lipid metabolism: a longitudinal metabolomic study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12967-025-07110-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 509
Autoren: Yuchen Zhang, Adrien Le Guennec, Pirkko Pussinen, Gordon Proctor, Sadia Ambreen Niazi
Journal: Journal of Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-18
DOI: 10.1186/s12967-025-07110-0
ISSN: 1479-5876
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12967-025-07110-0-2025-11-23-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Microbial signals in primary and metastatic brain tumors</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03957-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 399
Autoren: Golnaz Morad, Ashish V. Damania, Brenda Melendez, Bharat B. Singh, Fabiana J. Veguilla, Rebecca A. Soto, Yasmine M. Hoballah, Pranoti V. Sahasrabhojane, Matthew C. Wong, Mona M. Ahmed, Rene N. Rico, Kaitlyn N. Lewis, Khalida Wani, Diana D. Shamsutdinova, Rossana N. Lazcano Segura, Davis R. Ingram, Eric A. Goethe, Abderrahman Day, Ivonne I. Flores, Lauren K. McDaniel, Manoj Chelvanambi, Sarah B. Johnson, Florentia Dimitriou, Pravesh Gupta, Shivangi Oberai, M. Anna Zal, Phoebe Doss, Mohamed A. Jamal, Eiko Hayase, Chetna Wathoo, Lisa M. Norberg, Stephanie L. Jenkins, Sara Nass, Joy Gumin, Lihong Long, Jing Yang, Gina R. Bradley, Mahesh Prasad Bekal, Antonio G. Dono, Pavel S. Pichardo-Rojas, Samuel W. Andrewes, Leomar Y. Ballester, Jillian S. Losh, Jiyong Liang, Longfei Huo, Douglas C. Nielsen, Brittany C. Parker Kerrigan, Priscilla K. Brastianos, Natalie Wall Fowlkes, Chia-Chi Chang, Robert R. Jenq, Candelaria Gomez-Manzano, Jason T. Huse, Michael A. Davies, Alexander J. Lazar, Krishna P. Bhat, Nitin Tandon, Yoshua Esquenazi, Christine B. Peterson, Vinay K. Puduvalli, Frederick F. Lang, Christopher D. Johnston, Susan Bullman, Nadim J. Ajami, Sherise D. Ferguson, Jennifer A. Wargo
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
Abstract: Abstract
                  Gliomas and brain metastases are associated with poor prognosis, necessitating a deeper understanding of brain tumor biology and the development of effective therapeutic strategies. Although our group and others have demonstrated microbial presence in various tumors, recent controversies regarding cancer-type-specific intratumoral microbiota emphasize the importance of rigorous, orthogonal validation. This prospective, multi-institutional study included a total of 243 samples from 221 patients, comprising 168 glioma and brain metastases samples and 75 non-cancerous or tumor-adjacent tissues. Using stringent fluorescence in situ hybridization, immunohistochemistry and high-resolution spatial imaging, we detected intracellular bacterial 16S rRNA and lipopolysaccharides in both glioma and brain metastases samples, localized to tumor, immune and stromal cells. Custom 16S and metagenomic sequencing workflows identified taxa associated with intratumoral bacterial signals in the tumor microenvironment; however, standard culture methods did not yield readily cultivable microbiota. Spatial analyses revealed significant correlations between bacterial 16S signals and antimicrobial and immunometabolic signatures at regional, neighborhood and cellular levels. Furthermore, intratumoral 16S bacterial signals showed sequence overlap with matched oral and gut microbiota, suggesting a possible connection with distant communities. Together, these findings introduce microbial elements as a component of the brain tumor microenvironment and lay the foundation for future mechanistic and translational studies.
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03957-4
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03957-4-2025-11-23-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cationic nanogel–based nasal therapeutic HPV vaccine prevents the development of cervical cancer</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.ado8840</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 301
Autoren: Rika Nakahashi-Ouchida, Hiromi Mori, Yoshikazu Yuki, Tomonori Machita, Yuko Katakai, Shingo Umemoto, Yohei Uchida, Tomoyuki Yamanoue, Shin-ichi Sawada, Kazuya Ishige, Takashi Miyazaki, Kohtaro Fujihashi, Kazunari Akiyoshi, Yasuhiro Yasutomi, Kei Kawana, Hiroshi Kiyono
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-12
Abstract: 
                    Therapeutic vaccines against cervical cancer caused by human papillomavirus (HPV) are still an unmet medical need, despite a prophylactic HPV vaccine being available, and the now-licensed systemic vaccines may have a limited effect on the reproductive tract. To specifically inhibit cervical cancer development, the concept of mucosal immunity based on the reproductive-respiratory axis was adopted to develop a nasal HPV therapeutic vaccine. We used a cationic nanogel for the nasal vaccine delivery system and targeted HPV16 E7, an oncoprotein in HPV-driven cervical cancer to demonstrate the feasibility of a nasal therapeutic vaccine. The vaccine was combined with cyclic di–adenosine monophosphate as a cell-mediated immunity-inducing adjuvant. Intranasal immunization with the nanogel vaccine induced E7-specific CD4
                    +
                    and CD8
                    +
                    T cells in mouse cervicovaginal tissue. An antitumor effect due to the infiltration of vaccine-induced E7-specific T cells was also observed in an orthotopic tumor model in mice. Furthermore, intranasal immunization of nonhuman primates with the nanogel vaccine using a spray device that is also applicable to humans induced E7-specific T cells in the reproductive tissues. Our findings demonstrated that this nasal therapeutic vaccine effectively controlled cervical cancer and will contribute to preclinical evidence for clinical testing in the near future.
                  
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.ado8840
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.ado8840-2025-11-23-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>