<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 01:10:50 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 01:10:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Understanding the research landscape of over-the-counter herbal products, dietary supplements, and medications evaluated for depressive symptoms in adults: a scoping review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2025.1609605</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 265
Autoren: Rachael Frost, Aiman Zamri, Silvy Mathew, Adriana Salame, Cini Bhanu, Sukvinder K. Bhamra, Juan Carlos Bazo-Alvarez, Michael Heinrich, Kate Walters
Journal: Frontiers in Pharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-15
Abstract: BackgroundOver-the-counter (OTC) products such as herbal medical products (HMPs) or dietary supplements are a valued part of preventative and supportive self-care for depressive symptoms, but there is a wide array of products available, with differing levels of clinical evidence. It is unclear what the optimal directions for future research in this field are.AimWe aimed to explore the size and nature of the evidence base available for OTC products for depression in adults aged 18–60.MethodsWe carried out a scoping review following Joanna Briggs Institute guidance. We searched MEDLINE, Embase, PsycINFO, AMED, and CENTRAL from inception to December 2022, and 10% of the results were screened by two authors and the remainder by one author. We included randomised controlled trials of products commonly available OTC in multiple countries in participants with symptoms or a diagnosis of depression. Results were narratively summarised by the product and volume of evidence available.ResultsOut of 23,933 records found, we screened 1,367 full texts and included 209 trials. The largest volume of evidence was for omega-3s, St John’s Wort, saffron, probiotics, and vitamin D. Among a range of herbal medical products with promising evidence, those most commonly used and thus warranting further research were lavender, lemon balm, chamomile, and Echium. For 41 products, we found only single trials. Few products presented safety issues, whether used alone or adjunctively with antidepressants.ConclusionProducts with limited but promising evidence included folic acid, lavender, zinc, tryptophan, Rhodiola, and lemon balm, and future research should focus on these products. There is a need for further evaluation of herbal medical products as adjuncts to antidepressants and for exploring their potential benefits when used adjunctively with psychological therapies to support a more integrative approach. Safety reporting in these trials needs to be further improved.Systematic Review Registration:https://osf.io/rkm57/.
DOI: 10.3389/fphar.2025.1609605
ISSN: 1663-9812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fphar.2025.1609605-2025-08-02-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and safety of omitting 5-fluorouracil bolus in combination chemotherapy regimens for gastrointestinal cancers: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/14740338.2025.2527962</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 80
Autoren: Yusuf Ilhan, Onur Yazdan Balcık, Elif Sahın, Aysegul Merc Cetınkaya, Elvina Almuradova, Murat Bardakcı, Cigdem Dınckal, Murat Karateke, Kadriye Bır Yucel, Arif Hakan Onder, Yakup Ergun
Journal: Expert Opinion on Drug Safety
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-02
DOI: 10.1080/14740338.2025.2527962
ISSN: 1474-0338
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/14740338.2025.2527962-2025-08-02-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Use of medroxyprogesterone acetate and risk of meningiomas: a comparative safety study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/14740338.2025.2526787</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 74
Autoren: Connor Frey, Mohit Sodhi, Mostafa Fatehi, Abbas Kezouh, Mahyar Etminan
Journal: Expert Opinion on Drug Safety
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-03
DOI: 10.1080/14740338.2025.2526787
ISSN: 1474-0338
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/14740338.2025.2526787-2025-08-02-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Impact of chemical flavorants on reinforcement-related behavior in an adolescent mouse model of vaping self-administration</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpet.2025.103651</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 68
Autoren: Sabrina M. Swenson, Sean P. Hill, Dami Adeshina, Gabrielle V. Hammers, Sydney M. McSweeney, M. Kyle Sword, Matthew O. Grooms, Sarah K. Maddox, Hannah D. Strcula, Nathan A. Olszewski, Samuel Tetteh-Quarshie, Brandon J. Henderson
Journal: The Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jpet.2025.103651
ISSN: 0022-3565
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jpet.2025.103651-2025-08-02-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Metabolites as agents and targets for cancer immunotherapy </title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41573-025-01227-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 67
Autoren: Marcel P. Trefny, Guido Kroemer, Laurence Zitvogel, Sebastian Kobold
Journal: Nature Reviews Drug Discovery
Veröffentlicht: 2025-06-26
DOI: 10.1038/s41573-025-01227-z
ISSN: 1474-1776
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41573-025-01227-z-2025-08-02-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>