<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:13:46 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:13:46 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Subretinal Photovoltaic Implant to Restore Vision in Geographic Atrophy Due to AMD</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2501396</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2840
Autoren: Frank G. Holz, Yannick Le Mer, Mahiul M.K. Muqit, Lars-Olof Hattenbach, Andrea Cusumano, Salvatore Grisanti, Laurent Kodjikian, Marco Andrea Pileri, Frederic Matonti, Eric Souied, Boris V. Stanzel, Peter Szurman, Michel Weber, Karl Ulrich Bartz-Schmidt, Nicole Eter, Marie Noelle Delyfer, Jean François Girmens, Koen A. van Overdam, Armin Wolf, Ralf Hornig, Martina Corazzol, Frank Brodie, Lisa Olmos de Koo, Daniel Palanker, José-Alain Sahel
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-15
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2501396
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2501396-2026-01-21-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Universal Base-Edited CAR7 T Cells for T-Cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2505478</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1930
Autoren: Robert Chiesa, Christos Georgiadis, Hebatalla Rashed, Roland Preece, Prudence Hardefeldt, Jan Chu, Jemma Selvage, Avijeet Mishra, Batoul Ahmed, Stuart Adams, Rebecca Thomas, Kimberly Gilmour, Annie Etuk, Deborah Yallop, David O’Connor, Waseem Qasim
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-08
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2505478
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2505478-2026-01-21-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Clinical Trials Affected by Research Grant Terminations at the National Institutes of Health</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1517
Autoren: Vishal R. Patel, Michael Liu, Anupam B. Jena
Journal: JAMA Internal Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: This cross-sectional study summarizes the number of trials with terminated grants from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and calculates the proportion of affected trials among those with previously active NIH funding, by trial status at time of grant termination and by trial characteristics.
DOI: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088
ISSN: 2168-6106
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088-2026-01-21-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Updated Labeling for Menopausal Hormone Therapy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2025.22259</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1166
Autoren: Martin A. Makary, Christine P. Nguyen, Tracy Beth Høeg, George F. Tidmarsh
Journal: JAMA
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-13
Abstract: This Viewpoint describes the US Food and Drug Administration’s intended label updates and removal of black box warnings for menopausal hormone therapy based on current evidence.
DOI: 10.1001/jama.2025.22259
ISSN: 0098-7484
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jama.2025.22259-2026-01-21-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Deaths potentially averted by small changes in physical activity and sedentary time: an individual participant data meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140-6736(25)02219-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 988
Autoren: Ulf Ekelund, Jakob Tarp, Ding Ding, Miguel Adriano Sanchez-Lastra, Knut Eirik Dalene, Sigmund A Anderssen, Jostein Steene-Johannessen, Bjorge H Hansen, Bente Morseth, Laila A Hopstock, Edvard Sagelv, Peter Nordström, Anna Nordström, Maria Hagströmer, Ing-Mari Dohrn, Keith M Diaz, Steven Hooker, Virginia J Howard, I-Min Lee, Morten W Fagerland
Journal: The Lancet
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1016/s0140-6736(25)02219-6
ISSN: 0140-6736
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s0140-6736(25)02219-6-2026-01-21-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>