<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:12:33 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:12:33 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi Games’ Affordance of Childlike Wonder and Reduced Burnout Risk in Young Adults: In-Depth Mixed Methods Cross-Sectional Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/84219</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 511
Autoren: Winze Tam, Congcong Hou, Andreas Benedikt Eisingerich
Journal: JMIR Serious Games
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-19
Abstract: 
                    Background
                    Unrelenting pressure and an “always-on” culture can leave no time for genuine rest among young adults. While playing video games has been noted to afford cognitive escapism and relaxation, critical questions remain about the influence of popular video games, such as Super Mario Bros., and their potential effects on young adults’ burnout risk.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    This study examined the extent to which, if at all, popular video games such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi could foster childlike wonder. It also investigated the potential of these games to reduce burnout risk among young adults.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    We used a mixed methods approach. First, qualitative data were collected through 41 exploratory, in-depth interviews (women: n=19, 46.3%; men: n=21, 51.2%; prefer not to disclose sex: n=11, 2.4%; mean age 22.51, SD 1.52 years) with university students who had experience playing Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi. Second, quantitative data were collected in a cross-sectional survey (N=336) of players of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi to examine the games’ affordance of childlike wonder, overall happiness in life, and burnout risk.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Insights from in-depth interviews showed that players appreciated the ability of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games to instill childlike wonder, enhance happiness in life, and reduce burnout risk. Quantitative analyses showed that the games’ affordance of childlike wonder positively affected young adults’ happiness (b=0.30, SE=0.04, t=6.80, 95% CI 0.21-0.38; P&amp;lt;.001). In turn, overall happiness significantly reduced the risk of burnout (b=–0.48, SE=0.05, t=–9.55, 95% CI –0.572 to –0.377). Results showed that happiness fully mediated the impact of childlike wonder on burnout, as the direct effect of childlike wonder on burnout risk became insignificant (b=–0.08, SE=0.04, t=–1.88, 95% CI –0.16 to 0.01; P=.06), while the indirect effect of childlike wonder on burnout risk was significant (b=–0.14, bootstrapped SE=0.03, 95% CI –0.20 to –0.09).
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    The findings showed the significant positive effect of popular video games such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi on fostering players’ childlike wonder, increasing happiness, and reducing burnout risk. This study was among the first to identify childlike wonder as an emotional pathway through which mainstream video games could enhance well-being and reduce burnout. By moving beyond escapism and nostalgia, it offers a new perspective on how well-designed, globally familiar games can function as accessible, resilience-building digital microenvironments. These findings contributed to research bridging gaming and mental health and have practical implications for game designers, educators, and health professionals interested in promoting mental wellness through everyday play.
                  
DOI: 10.2196/84219
ISSN: 2291-9279
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/84219-2026-01-16-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Examining the Association Between Internet Use and Perceived Stress in Adults: Longitudinal Observational Study Combining Web Tracking Data With Questionnaires</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/78775</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 369
Autoren: Mohammad Belal, Nguyen Luong, Talayeh Aledavood, Juhi Kulshrestha
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-09
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Background
                    In today’s digital era, the internet plays a pervasive role in daily life, influencing everyday activities such as communication, work, and leisure. This online engagement intertwines with offline experiences, shaping individuals’ overall well-being. Despite its significance, existing research often falls short in capturing the relationship between internet use and well-being, relying primarily on isolated studies and self-reported data. One major contributor to deteriorated well-being is stress. While some research has examined the relationship between internet use and stress, both positive and negative associations have been reported.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    This study aimed to identify the associations between an individual’s internet use and their stress.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    We conducted a 7-month longitudinal study. We combined fine-grained URL-level web browsing traces of 1490 German internet users with their sociodemographics and monthly measures of stress. Further, we developed a conceptual framework that allows us to simultaneously explore different contextual dimensions, including how, where, when, and by whom the internet is used. We applied linear mixed-effects models to examine these associations.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Our analysis revealed several associations between internet use and stress, varying by context. Increased time spent on social media, online shopping, and gaming platforms was associated with higher stress. For example, the time spent by individuals on shopping-related internet use (aggregated over the 30 days before their stress was measured via questionnaires) was positively associated with stress on both mobile (
                      β
                      =.04, 95% CI 0.00‐0.08;
                      P
                      =.04) and desktop devices (
                      β
                      =.03, 95% CI −0.00 to 0.06;
                      P
                      =.09). In contrast, time spent on productivity or news websites was associated with lower stress. Specifically, in the last 30 days of mobile usage, productivity-related use showed a negative association with stress (
                      β
                      =−.03, 95% CI −0.06 to −0.00;
                      P
                      =.04). In addition, in the last 2 days of data, news usage was negatively associated with stress on both mobile (
                      β
                      =−.54, 95% CI −1.08 to 0.00;
                      P
                      =.048) and desktop devices (
                      β
                      =−.50, 95% CI−0.90 to −0.11;
                      P
                      =.01). Further analysis showed that total time spent online (
                      β
                      =.01, 95% CI 0.00‐0.02;
                      P
                      &amp;lt;.001), social-media usage (
                      β
                      =.02, 95% CI 0.00‐0.03;
                      P
                      =.02), and gaming usage (
                      β
                      =.01, 95% CI 0.00‐0.02;
                      P
                      =.02) were all positively associated with stress in high-stress Perceived Stress Scale (PSS&amp;gt;26) individuals on mobile devices.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    The findings indicate that internet use is associated with stress, and these associations differ across various usage contexts. In the future, the behavioral markers we identified can pave the way for designing individualized tools for people to self-monitor and self-moderate their online behaviors to enhance their well-being, reducing the burden on already overburdened mental health services.
                  
DOI: 10.2196/78775
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/78775-2026-01-16-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Personalizing prostate cancer education for patients using an EHR-Integrated LLM agent</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-02166-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 59
Autoren: Yuexing Hao, Jason Holmes, Mark R. Waddle, Brian J. Davis, Nathan Y. Yu, Kristin S. Vickers, Heather Preston, Drew Margolin, Corinna E. Löckenhoff, Aditya Vashistha, Saleh Kalantari, Marzyeh Ghassemi, Wei Liu
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-18
Abstract: Abstract
                  Cancer patients often lack timely education and personalized support due to clinician workload. This quality improvement study develops and evaluates a Large Language Model (LLM) agent, MedEduChat, which is integrated with the clinic’s electronic health records (EHR) and designed to enhance prostate cancer patient education. Fifteen non-metastatic prostate cancer patients and three clinicians recruited from the Mayo Clinic interacted with the agent between May 2024 and April 2025. Findings showed that MedEduChat has a high usability score (UMUX = 83.7/100) and improves patients’ health confidence (Health Confidence Score rose from 9.9 to 13.9). Clinicians evaluated the patient-chat interaction history and rated MedEduChat as highly correct (2.9/3), complete (2.7/3), and safe (2.7/3), with moderate personalization (2.3/3). This study highlights the potential of LLM agents to improve patient engagement and health education.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-02166-0
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-02166-0-2026-01-16-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A Feature-Augmented Transformer Model to Recognize Functional Activities From in-the-Wild Smartwatch Data</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1109/jbhi.2025.3586074</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 40
Autoren: Bryan Minor, Colin Greeley, Ryan Holder, Brian Thomas, Lawrence B. Holder, Diane J. Cook
Journal: IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1109/jbhi.2025.3586074
ISSN: 2168-2194
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1109/jbhi.2025.3586074-2026-01-16-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Intervention in Health Misinformation Using Large Language Models for Automated Detection, Thematic Analysis, and Inoculation: Case Study on COVID-19</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/75500</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 24
Autoren: Samira Malek, Christopher Griffin, Robert D Fraleigh, Robert Lennon, Vishal Monga, Lijiang Shen
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-08
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Background
                    The rapid growth of social media as an information channel has enabled the swift spread of inaccurate or false health information, significantly impacting public health. This widespread dissemination of misinformation has caused confusion, eroded trust in health authorities, led to noncompliance with health guidelines, and encouraged risky health behaviors. Understanding the dynamics of misinformation on social media is essential for devising effective public health communication strategies.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    This study aims to present a comprehensive and automated approach that leverages large language models (LLMs) and machine learning techniques to detect misinformation on social media, uncover the underlying causes and themes, and generate refutation arguments, facilitating control of its spread and promoting public health outcomes by inoculating people against health misinformation.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    We use 2 datasets to train 3 LLMs, namely, BERT, T5, and GPT-2, to classify documents into 2 categories: misinformation and nonmisinformation. In addition, we use a separate dataset to identify misinformation topics. To analyze these topics, we applied 3 topic modeling algorithms—Latent Dirichlet Allocation, Top2Vec, and BERTopic—and selected the optimal model based on performance evaluated across 3 metrics. Using a prompting approach, we extract sentence-level representations for the topics to uncover their underlying themes. Finally, we design a prompt text capable of identifying misinformation themes effectively.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    The trained BERT model demonstrated exceptional performance, achieving 98% accuracy in classifying misinformation and nonmisinformation, with a 44% reduction in false-positive rates for artificial intelligence–generated misinformation. Among the 3 topic modeling approaches used, BERTopic outperformed the others, achieving the highest metrics with a Coherence Value of 0.41, Normalized Pointwise Mutual Information of −0.086, and Inverse Rank-Biased Overlap of 0.99. To address the issue of unclassified documents, we developed an algorithm to assign each document to its closest topic. In addition, we proposed a novel method using prompt engineering to generate sentence-level representations for each topic, achieving a 99.6% approval rate as “appropriate” or “somewhat appropriate” by 3 independent raters. We further designed a prompt text to identify themes of misinformation topics and developed another prompt capable of detecting misinformation themes with 82% accuracy.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    This study presents a comprehensive and automated approach to addressing health misinformation on social media using advanced machine learning and natural language processing techniques. By leveraging LLMs and prompt engineering, the system effectively detects misinformation, identifies underlying themes, and provides explanatory responses to combat its spread. The proposed method was tested on an English language COVID-19–related dataset and has not been evaluated on real-world online social media data; the experiments were conducted offline.
                  
DOI: 10.2196/75500
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/75500-2026-01-16-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>