<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 01:06:46 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 01:06:46 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Ultra-processed food intake is associated with altered glucose homeostasis in young adults with a history of overweight or obesity: a longitudinal study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12986-025-01036-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 349
Autoren: Yiping Li, Elizabeth Costello, Sarah Rock, William B. Patterson, Zhanghua Chen, Frank Gilliland, Michael I. Goran, Tanya L. Alderete, Jesse A. Goodrich, David V. Conti, Nikos Stratakis, Leda Chatzi
Journal: Nutrition &amp;amp; Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-10
DOI: 10.1186/s12986-025-01036-6
ISSN: 1743-7075
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12986-025-01036-6-2025-11-28-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Influence of Ultraprocessed Food Consumption on Energy Intake in Emerging Adulthood: A Controlled Feeding Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.70086</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 346
Autoren: Maria L. M. Rego, Emma Leslie, Emily Schmall, Bailey Capra, Summer Hudson, Monica L. Ahrens, Benjamin Katz, Kevin P. Davy, Valisa E. Hedrick, Alexandra G. DiFeliceantonio, Brenda M. Davy
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-19
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    Objective
                    This study examined the impact of a 2‐week eucaloric diet high in ultraprocessed foods (UPF) compared to a diet without UPF (non‐UPF) on ad libitum energy intake (EI) and food selection in individuals aged 18–25.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    In a randomized, crossover, proof‐of‐concept trial, participants completed two 14‐day controlled feeding periods (81% UPF vs. 0% UPF), with a 4‐week washout. Diets were matched for macronutrients, fiber, added sugar, diet quality, and energy density. Following each condition, participants consumed an ad libitum buffet meal including UPF and non‐UPF. Energy and food grams consumed were quantified. Statistical analyses were conducted for the full sample, late adolescents (aged 18–21), and young adults (aged 22–25).
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Twenty‐seven individuals aged 22 ± 2 years (mean BMI = 24 ± 3 kg/m
                      2
                      ) were included. Diet compliance was ~99% overall. There was no effect of diet condition on meal total kcal or grams consumed or UPF or non‐UPF consumption in the full sample (all
                      p
                       &amp;gt; 0.05). In the exploratory age subgroup analysis, an interaction between diet and age was observed for total EI (
                      p
                       &amp;lt; 0.001), where total EI increased among adolescents following the UPF diet (
                      p
                       = 0.03,
                      d
                       = 0.79), but not in young adults.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    Late adolescents may be susceptible to increased EI following a UPF diet. Future trials are warranted to evaluate this possibility.
                    
                      Trial Registration:
                      ClinicalTrials.gov
                      : NCT05550818.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/oby.70086
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.70086-2025-11-28-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cheese Consumption and Incidence of Dementia in Community-Dwelling Older Japanese Adults: The JAGES 2019–2022 Cohort Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17213363</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 328
Autoren: Seungwon Jeong, Takao Suzuki, Yusuke Inoue, Eunji Bang, Kentaro Nakamura, Mayuki Sasaki, Katsunori Kondo
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-25
Abstract: Background/Objectives: Dementia is a growing public health concern in rapidly aging Japan. Dietary factors, including dairy products, have been proposed as modifiable influences on cognitive health, although findings across studies remain inconsistent. This study aimed to examine the association between habitual cheese consumption and incident dementia in a large, population-based cohort of older Japanese adults, and to provide epidemiological evidence regarding its potential preventive role in populations with low baseline dairy intake. Methods: We analyzed data from the Japan Gerontological Evaluation Study (JAGES) 2019–2022 cohort, linking survey responses to long-term care insurance (LTCI) certification records. Participants aged ≥65 years without prior LTCI certification were included. Cheese consumption was assessed at baseline and categorized as ≥1 time/week vs. non-consumers. Propensity score matching (PSM) was applied on sociodemographic and health-related covariates. Cox proportional hazards models estimated hazard ratios (HRs) for incident dementia over three years. Results: After PSM, 7914 participants were analyzed (3957 consumers; 3957 non-consumers). Baseline covariates were well-balanced. Over 3 years, 134 consumers (3.4%) and 176 non-consumers (4.5%) developed dementia, corresponding to an absolute risk difference of 1.06 percentage points. Cheese consumption was associated with a lower hazard of dementia (HR = 0.76, 95% CI 0.60–0.95, p = 0.015). Conclusions: Habitual cheese consumption (≥1 time/week) was modestly associated with a reduced 3-year incidence of dementia in older Japanese adults. While the absolute risk reduction was small, these findings are consistent with prior observational evidence linking dairy intake to cognitive health. Further research is warranted to clarify dose–response relationships, cheese subtypes, and underlying mechanisms.
DOI: 10.3390/nu17213363
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu17213363-2025-11-28-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Nutrient adequacy and environmental foot-print of Mediterranean, pesco-, ovo-lacto-, and vegan menus: a modelling study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1681512</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 197
Autoren: Ángela Alcalá-Santiago, Noelia M. Rodríguez-Martín, Eduardo Casas-Albertos, José María Gálvez-Navas, Adela Castelló-Pastor, Belén García-Villanova, Esther Molina-Montes
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-11
Abstract: 
                    Background
                    Consumer food choices are changing towards a more plant-based diet (PBD) due to growing awareness of their less detrimental effects on health and the environment. However, PBDs—particularly vegan diets—may lead to nutritional deficiencies compared to non-PBDs. These differences may, in part, be influenced by the typically lower caloric content of PBDs.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    To compare the nutritional adequacy and environmental footprints of four 7-day menu models (~ 2,000 kcal/day) Mediterranean (omnivorous) diet, two vegetarian-like diets, and one vegan.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Menus were designed based on the recommendations of the Spanish Society for Community Nutrition (SENC) and Vegetarian Union (UVE), substituting animal-based foods with plant-based alternatives. Nutritional intake was assessed using the Spanish BEDCA food composition table (Base de Datos Española de Composición de Alimentos) and adequacy was evaluated using Dietary Reference Intakes (DRIs) and recommended intake levels. Daily environmental footprints were estimated with Agribalyse. Differences between the four diet models were evaluated by one-way ANOVA or Kruskal-Wallis tests, followed by post-hoc analyses to identify pairwise differences in nutrient intake (significance level: 95%).
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Daily macronutrient intake did not differ substantially across the diet groups. Furthermore, all four menus met protein needs and most micronutrient DRIs. Shortfalls were observed for vitamin D and iodine across all diets, and for vitamin B₁₂ in the vegan model;
                      ω
                      -3 PUFA were below the 250 mg/day target in all diets, while saturated fat remained &amp;amp;lt; 8% of total energy intake. Mean daily environmental footprints decreased progressively from omnivorous to vegan diets: −46% CO₂, −6.6% deprived water and −33% land use among others.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Well-planned PBDs can achieve comparable sustainability and nutritional adequacy to a healthy Mediterranean diet, although attention is required to ensure adequate intake of certain micronutrients.
                  
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1681512
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1681512-2025-11-28-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mushroom consumption impacts on biomarkers of cardiometabolic disease risk and immune function: a narrative review from a whole food perspective</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2025.2582603</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 155
Autoren: Luz M. Comboni, Cassi N. Uffelman, Charlotte B. Campbell, Matthew R. Olson, Wayne W. Campbell
Journal: Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-12
DOI: 10.1080/10408398.2025.2582603
ISSN: 1040-8398
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/10408398.2025.2582603-2025-11-28-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>