<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 01:06:13 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 01:06:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Association between frequency of meeting daily step thresholds and all-cause mortality and cardiovascular disease in older women</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2025-110311</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 1665
Autoren: Rikuta Hamaya, Kelly R Evenson, Daniel Lieberman, I-Min Lee
Journal: British Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-21
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    To examine the associations between the number of days per week achieving various daily step thresholds and all-cause mortality and cardiovascular disease (CVD) incidence in older women.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    We conducted a prospective cohort study of 13 547 women free of CVD and cancer (mean age 71.8 years). We included participants who wore an ActiGraph GT3X+ accelerometer for 7 consecutive days between 2011–2015 and were subsequently followed for mortality through 2024. Women were classified by the number of days per week achieving step thresholds of ≥4000, ≥5000, ≥6000 or ≥7000 steps/day. Cox proportional hazards regression estimated hazard ratios (HR) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) for all-cause mortality and CVD incidence, adjusting for lifestyle behaviours and comorbidities.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    During a median follow-up of 10.9 years, 1765 women (13.0%) died and 781 (5.1%) developed CVD. Achieving ≥4000 steps/day on 1–2 and ≥3 days/week was associated with lower mortality risk compared with 0 days/week (adjusted HR 0.74 (95% CI 0.65 to 0.86) and 0.60 (95% CI 0.53 to 0.68), respectively). For CVD, corresponding results were 0.73 (95% CI 0.58 to 0.92) and 0.73 (95% CI 60 to 0.89), respectively. An inverse curvilinear dose-response relationship was observed for mortality, such that with higher step thresholds (5000, 6000 or 7000), the risk of mortality further declined modestly. With additional adjustment for mean daily steps, associations were attenuated to the null.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    Among older women, achieving ≥4000 steps/day on even 1–2 days/week was associated with lower mortality and CVD, while more steps were associated with even better outcomes. A greater number of steps, regardless of daily patterns, is associated with better health outcomes.
                  
DOI: 10.1136/bjsports-2025-110311
ISSN: 0306-3674
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bjsports-2025-110311-2025-11-13-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Perineuromal Botulinum Toxin Injection for War-Related Postamputation Pain: A Pragmatic, Multicenter, Comparative Effectiveness Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 352
Autoren: Nadiya Segin, Roman Smolynets, Joana Barroso, Natalia Matolinets, Paul F. Pasquina, Steven P. Cohen
Journal: Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026
ISSN: 0003-9993
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.apmr.2025.09.026-2025-11-13-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Is “Zone 2 Training”?: Experts’ Viewpoint on Definition, Training Methods, and Expected Adaptations</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1123/ijspp.2024-0303</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 179
Autoren: Sebastian Sitko, Xabier Artetxe, Martin Bonnevie-Svendsen, Miguel Ángel Galán-Rioja, Gabriele Gallo, Frédéric Grappe, Peter Leo, Manuel Mateo, Iñigo Mujika, Dajo Sanders, Stephen Seiler, Mikel Zabala, Pedro L. Valenzuela, Aitor Viribay
Journal: International Journal of Sports Physiology and Performance
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
Abstract: 
                    
                      Background
                      :
                    
                    The role of high-volume low-intensity training for enhancing endurance performance has gained growing interest in recent years. Specifically, so-called “zone 2 training” is currently receiving much attention, and many propose that this is the target intensity at which a large proportion of total endurance training should be performed. However, despite the popularity of this concept, there is no clear consensus among coaches, athletes, and scientists regarding the definition of zone 2 training.
                    
                      Purpose
                      :
                    
                    This commentary summarizes the perspectives, experience, and knowledge of an expert panel of 14 applied sport scientists and professional coaches with the aim of providing insight and a basis for definitional consensus on zone 2 training. Moreover, potential training strategies at this intensity are proposed, and the expected physiological adaptations when exercising at this intensity and related research gaps are also discussed.
                    
                      Results
                      :
                    
                    Experts reached consensus that zone 2 training should preferably be performed at intensities located immediately below the first lactate or ventilatory threshold through continuous, variable, or interval-type sessions. Furthermore, experts expected a broad range of central and peripheral adaptations from zone 2 training. These expected adaptations might not be unique to zone 2 and could also be induced with sessions performed at slightly higher and lower intensities.
                    
                      Conclusions
                      :
                    
                    This commentary provides practical insight and unified criteria regarding the preferred intensity, duration, and session type for the optimization of zone 2 training based on the perspectives of acknowledged sport scientists and professional coaches.
                  
DOI: 10.1123/ijspp.2024-0303
ISSN: 1555-0265
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1123/ijspp.2024-0303-2025-11-13-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Human development and gender inequality are associated with cardiorespiratory fitness: A global systematic review of V̇O2peak</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101098</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 112
Autoren: Nicolas J. Pillon, Joaquin Ortiz de Zevallos, Juleen R. Zierath, Barbara E. Ainsworth
Journal: Journal of Sport and Health Science
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101098
ISSN: 2095-2546
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101098-2025-11-13-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Physical Activity and Exercise Intensity Terminology: A Joint American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM) Expert Statement and Exercise and Sport Science Australia (ESSA) Consensus Statement</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1249/mss.0000000000003795</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 80
Autoren: DAVID J. BISHOP, BELINDA BECK, STUART J. H. BIDDLE, KERI L. DENAY, ALESSANDRA FERRI, MARTIN J. GIBALA, SAMUEL HEADLEY, ANDREW M. JONES, MARY JUNG, MATTHEW J.-C. LEE, TRINE MOHOLDT, ROBERT U. NEWTON, SOPHIA NIMPHIUS, LINDA S. PESCATELLO, NICHOLAS J. SANER, CHRIS TZARIMAS
Journal: Medicine &amp;amp; Science in Sports &amp;amp; Exercise
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  The evidence supporting the many beneficial effects of physical activity, including exercise, is overwhelming. This has led to numerous publications, statements, and position stands providing evidence-based recommendations to realize the performance-enhancing and therapeutic benefits of exercise. However, one factor hampering research and limiting the adoption of these recommendations is the inconsistent use of terminology associated with different exercise intensities. The goal of this international group of researchers and practitioners, therefore, was to propose standardized physical activity and exercise intensity terminology that has utility across all ages, sexes, genders, physical abilities, conditions, applications, and activities. After much discussion, we propose a standard terminology for physical activity, exercise, and sport and human performance comprising five exercise intensities: very low, low, moderate, high, and very high. We also propose five different descriptors for the perception of effort that align with the five intensities we have suggested: very easy, easy, somewhat hard, hard, and very hard. To enable consistent use of these descriptors with both cardiorespiratory and resistance exercise, we suggest not using descriptors such as light, heavy, weak, or strong (which might be perceived as only being applicable to describing load). We appreciate that some fields have long-established terminology and may be reluctant to change. Nonetheless, at a minimum, the terminology proposed here allows for more clarity when comparing the different exercise intensity descriptors currently used by different fields. Finally, we hope this will be an important “first step” in harmonizing the descriptions of exercise intensity across the fields of physical activity for public health, exercise science, and sport science.
DOI: 10.1249/mss.0000000000003795
ISSN: 0195-9131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1249/mss.0000000000003795-2025-11-13-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>