<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 01:15:06 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 01:15:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and Safety of Subcutaneous Anifrolumab in Systemic Lupus Erythematosus: the Randomized, Phase 3, TULIP‐SC Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.70041</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 60
Autoren: Susan Manzi, Ian N. Bruce, Eric F. Morand, Richard Furie, Yoshiya Tanaka, Kenneth C. Kalunian, Anca Askanase, Patricia Puzio, Emon Khan, Jenny Wissmar, Michael Song, Catharina Lindholm, The TULIP‐SC investigators
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-29
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    The multinational, phase 3, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled TULIP‐SC trial evaluated the efficacy and safety of subcutaneous anifrolumab in adults who have moderate‐to‐severe SLE activity, despite receiving standard therapy.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Adults with SLE received subcutaneous anifrolumab 120 mg or placebo once weekly for 52 weeks (1:1 randomization). Only the primary endpoint (treatment difference in BILAG‐based Composite Lupus Assessment [BICLA] response at 52 weeks) was formally tested in a pre‐planned interim analysis; key secondary and other endpoints were tested in the full analysis.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      At the interim analysis (220 patients, anifrolumab: n=109; placebo: n=111), the primary endpoint was met (anifrolumab vs placebo: 59.4% vs 43.9%; BICLA response difference [95% confidence interval]=15.5% [2.3–28.6%],
                      p
                      =0.0211).
                    
                    
                      The full analysis included 367 patients (anifrolumab: n=184; placebo: n=183). Versus placebo, more patients treated with anifrolumab attained a BICLA response whilst maintaining low/reduced oral glucocorticoid doses through Week 52 (56.2% vs 34.0%; difference=22.3% [12.3−32.2]
                      p
                      &amp;lt;0.0001), and the time to first sustained BICLA response was reduced (Hazard ratio=2.2 [1.5−3.2];
                      p
                      &amp;lt;0.0001). Treatment differences in Week 52 DORIS remission and Low Lupus Disease Activity State attainment rates favored anifrolumab over placebo (14.2% [5.6−22.8%],
                      p
                      =0.0012, and 14.1% [4.6−23.6%],
                      p
                      =0.0038). The frequencies of serious adverse events were 11.9% with anifrolumab and 10.4% with placebo; the frequencies of herpes zoster were 3.8% and 1.1%, respectively.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Consistent with the well‐established profile of intravenous anifrolumab, subcutaneous anifrolumab demonstrated significant, clinically meaningful treatment benefits when added to standard therapy, and an acceptable safety profile in patients with moderate to severe SLE.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/art.70041
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.70041-2026-01-14-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Immunosuppressant use and adverse pregnancy outcomes in women with systemic lupus erythematosus: a retrospective cohort study in Korea</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/rheumatology/keaf651</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 50
Autoren: Yu-Seon Jung, Yeo-Jin Song, Eun Jin Jang, Soo-Kyung Cho, Yoon-Kyoung Sung, Sun-Young Jung
Journal: Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-12
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Objectives
                    This study aimed to estimate the incidence of adverse pregnancy outcomes (APO) in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) and to evaluate the risks associated with immunosuppressant use—including hydroxychloroquine and teratogenic agents such as mycophenolate mofetil, methotrexate and cyclophosphamide—across specific APO categories.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    A cohort study was conducted using the 2005–2018 National Health Information Database of the National Health Insurance Service in Korea, involving 4,880 pregnancies in 3,059 women with SLE. The incidences of preeclampsia/eclampsia, preterm birth, spontaneous abortion and stillbirth were estimated. Associations between APOs and medication patterns from preconception through pregnancy were analysed using univariate and multivariable models.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    The overall APO incidence among pregnant women with SLE was 45.0% (95% CI: 43.4, 46.5%). Compared with continuous hydroxychloroquine use, non-use (adjusted odds ratio [AOR]: 1.39; 95% CI: 1.05, 1.85), discontinuation (AOR: 2.18; 95% CI: 1.61, 2.95), and initiation during pregnancy (AOR: 2.17; 95% CI: 1.16, 4.06) were significantly associated with increased preterm birth risk. Exposure to teratogenic immunosuppressants within 3 months of preconception or during the first trimester was associated with increased spontaneous abortion risk (AOR: 2.59 and 3.18, respectively).
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Continuity of hydroxychloroquine use from preconception through pregnancy reduces preterm birth risk in SLE. Conversely, early exposure to teratogenic immunosuppressants heightens the risk of spontaneous abortion. These findings underscore the importance of preconception medication planning in women with SLE.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/rheumatology/keaf651
ISSN: 1462-0324
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/rheumatology/keaf651-2026-01-14-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Reactive Oxygen Species–Induced Modifications of Fibrin Clots as a Link Between Immune Responses and Atherothrombosis in Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43371</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 24
Autoren: Matteo Becatti, Giacomo Emmi, Alessandra Bettiol, Amanda Mannucci, Flavia Rita Argento, Eleonora Fini, Serena Borghi, Francesca Nencini, Maria Nicastro, Irene Mattioli, Elena Silvestri, Augusto Vaglio, Domenico Prisco, Claudia Fiorillo
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-28
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    Cardiovascular events are major determinants of morbidity and mortality in systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), particularly in patients with renal involvement. Although oxidative stress has been implicated in driving vascular and renal damage in SLE, the specific mechanisms remain unclear. This study investigated the potential role of oxidative stress‐induced alterations in fibrinogen structure and function in the pathogenesis of atherothrombosis in SLE.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    In this cross‐sectional study, we enrolled 144 adult patients with SLE and 90 matched controls. We measured blood leukocyte reactive oxygen species (ROS) production, systemic redox status, and the structural and functional features of purified fibrinogen. Correlations between these parameters and disease activity were also investigated. In vitro experiments to clarify the causal relationships among ROS levels, protein oxidation, and fibrin abnormalities provided mechanistic insights of the observed alterations.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Patients with SLE showed increased leukocyte ROS production, mainly due to neutrophil NADPH oxidase activation. Interestingly, renal biopsies from patients with SLE with active proliferative lupus nephritis exhibited overexpression of the NADPH oxidase enzyme complex p22phox. This was accompanied by plasma oxidative stress as indicated by elevated plasma lipid peroxidation and reduced antioxidant defenses. Fibrinogen oxidation was associated with structural and functional changes, leading to the formation of denser fibrin networks with lower clot porosity and reduced susceptibility to plasmin‐mediated fibrin lysis. Interestingly, these fibrinogen modifications correlated with alterations in redox status and disease activity.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Oxidative stress may drive structural and functional modifications of fibrinogen in SLE, potentially acting as a novel pathogenetic mechanism in atherothrombosis among these patients.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/art.43371
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43371-2026-01-14-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Glucagon‐Like Peptide‐1 Receptor Agonist Use and the Risk of Adverse Cardiac and Kidney Outcomes Among Patients With Systemic Lupus Erythematosus and Lupus Nephritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43403</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 20
Autoren: April Jorge, Aakash V. Patel, Baijun Zhou, Lingxiao Zhang, Hyon Choi
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-17
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    Glucagon‐like peptide‐1 receptor agonists (GLP‐1RAs) have cardioprotective and kidney‐protective benefits among patients with type 2 diabetes (T2D). We sought to determine whether GLP‐1RA use improves cardiovascular (CV) and kidney outcomes among patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) and lupus nephritis (LN).
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    We emulated a pragmatic target trial to evaluate the impact of GLP‐1RA versus comparator hypoglycemic agents, dipeptidyl peptidase 4 inhibitors (DPP4i), on CV and kidney outcomes among patients with SLE and T2D using a large, US multicenter electronic health record database. We used propensity score overlap weighting to emulate randomization among treatment groups. Outcomes included major adverse CV events, venous thromboembolism (VTE), kidney disease progression (estimated glomerular filtration rate decline ≥ 30% or new onset end‐stage kidney disease), and all‐cause mortality. We used Cox regression to compare hazard ratios (HR) based on the weighted populations. In a secondary analysis, we only included patients with LN.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    There were 910 and 1,004 initiators of GLP‐1RA and DPP4i, respectively, including 267 and 324 patients with LN, respectively. Baseline covariates were balanced after propensity score overlap weighting. The risks of major adverse cardiac events (MACEs; hazard ratio [HR] 0.66, 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.48–0.91), VTE (HR 0.49, 95% CI 0.24–0.97), kidney disease progression (HR 0.77, 95% CI 0.60–0.98), and all‐cause mortality (HR 0.26, 95% CI 0.10–0.68) were lower with GLP‐1RA versus DPP4i use. GLP‐1RA use was similarly associated with lower risks of MACE and kidney disease progression among patients with LN.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    We found lower risks of adverse CV and kidney outcomes and mortality with GLP‐1RA use compared with DPP4i use among patients with lupus and T2D.
                    
                      
                        
                          image
                        
                      
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/art.43403
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43403-2026-01-14-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Results from a pilot study of dusquetide for the treatment of aphthous ulcers associated with Behçet's syndrome</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/rheumatology/keaf682</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 18
Autoren: Oreola Donini, Bercemhan Sulu, Christopher Pullion, Adam Rumage, Richard Straube, Christopher Schaber, Gülen Hatemi
Journal: Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-16
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Objectives
                    The study was designed to obtain a preliminary assessment of the safety and efficacy of SGX945 (dusquetide) for the treatment of aphthous oral and genital ulcers in Behçet’s syndrome.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    This was an open-label pilot study of intravenous dusquetide in patients with Behçet’s syndrome who had at least two active oral and/or one active genital ulcer(s) at enrolment. Participants were treated twice weekly for 4 weeks and then followed for an additional 4 weeks. Efficacy assessments included number and pain of oral and genital ulcers, overall disease activity assessed using Behçet’s Syndrome Current Activity Form and Behçet’s Syndrome Activity Scale and health-related quality of life assessed using Behçet’s Syndrome Quality of Life Index.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Eight participants with oral ulcers were enrolled. Seven of eight participants reported a perceived benefit including reduction in number, duration and pain of oral ulcers. Comparison to historical placebo groups demonstrated a reduction in the number of ulcers, time to resolution of ulcers, area under the curve of the ulcer-days, oral pain and baseline quality of life metrics. The treatments were well-tolerated with no treatment-related AEs and no serious or severe adverse events recorded.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    This small pilot study illustrates the potential efficacy and tolerability of SGX945 in patients with Behçet’s syndrome who had ulcers despite being on colchicine maintenance therapy. The results justify further development of SGX945 for the treatment of Behçet’s syndrome.
                  
                  
                    Clinical trial registration
                    Clinicaltrials.gov, http://clinicaltrials.gov, NCT06386744.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/rheumatology/keaf682
ISSN: 1462-0324
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-14</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/rheumatology/keaf682-2026-01-14-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>