<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 01:02:49 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 01:02:49 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of Vitamin D2 Supplementation on 25-Hydroxyvitamin D3 Status: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/nutrit/nuaf166</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 244
Autoren: Emily I G Brown, Andrea L Darling, Tracey M Robertson, Kathryn H Hart, Jie Li, Cathie Martin, Martin J Warren, Colin P Smith, Susan A Lanham-New, Ruan M Elliott
Journal: Nutrition Reviews
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
Abstract: Abstract
               
                  Context
                  Researchers have identified differences in metabolic activity between vitamins D2 and D3. Moreover, it is suspected from randomized controlled trial data that vitamin D2 supplementation increases the metabolic clearance of 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 [25(OH)D3], but this effect has yet to be quantified.
               
               
                  Objective
                  This study sought to undertake a systematic review and meta-analysis of the effect of vitamin D2 supplementation on serum 25(OH)D3 concentrations.
               
               
                  Data Sources
                  PUBMED was searched for articles published from January 1, 1975, to February 1, 2023. Of the 202 articles retrieved, 20 were included in this review, and of those, 11 were suitable for meta-analysis.
               
               
                  Data Extraction
                  Randomized controlled trials reporting either baseline and postintervention serum 25(OH)D3 concentrations (nmol/L) or absolute changes in concentrations were included. Random-effects meta-analyses were calculated using Review Manager (version 5.3; The Cochrane Collaboration). Mean differences were reported with 95% CIs.
               
               
                  Data Analysis
                  In meta-analyses there was a reduction in serum 25(OH)D3 after vitamin D2 supplementation compared with control for end-of-trial between-groups data (random weighted mean difference [WMD] = −17.99 nmol/L; 95% CI, −25.86 to −10.12; P &amp;amp;lt; .00001) and absolute change over the trial (random WMD = −9.25 nmol/L; 95% CI, −14.40 to −4.10; P = .0004).
               
               
                  Conclusions
                  Study participants who received vitamin D2 supplementation showed statistically significant reductions in serum 25(OH)D3 concentrations, compared to controls without supplementation. An inverse relationship between vitamin D2 and D3 concentrations has been proposed in the literature. A regulatory mechanism that increases the disposal rate of 25(OH)D after an increase in vitamin D concentrations could explain these results. However, further research is needed to establish whether vitamins D2 and D3 elicit different changes in overall vitamin D metabolism that might influence clinical advice to recommend vitamin D3 supplements over vitamin D2 supplements, where appropriate.
               
DOI: 10.1093/nutrit/nuaf166
ISSN: 0029-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/nutrit/nuaf166-2025-10-15-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Young Children’s (Aged 3 to 8 Years) Food and Beverage Brand Exposure on YouTube and YouTube Kids: An Observational Study and Content Analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.010</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 228
Autoren: Frances Fleming-Milici, Haley Gershman, Hanako O. Agresta, Melissa McCann, Jennifer Harris
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.010
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.010-2025-10-15-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cold and hot consumption and health outcomes among US Asian and White populations</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1017/s000711452510514x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 154
Autoren: Tianying Wu, Neeraja Ramesh, Cassie Doyle, Fang-Chi Hsu
Journal: British Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
Abstract: Abstract
	  This study examined the associations between cold and hot food and beverage consumption and various health outcomes among Asians and Whites in the USA. Data were drawn from 212 Asian and 203 White adults (aged 18–65 years) in the Healthy Ageing Survey. Participants reported their frequency of cold and hot drink and meal intake, along with symptoms of depression, anxiety, insomnia and gastrointestinal issues (e.g. gas, abdominal fullness). Multivariable analyses adjusted for confounders were used to assess these associations. Among Asians, higher cold consumption in summer was associated with increased anxiety (β = 0·24, 95 % CI: 0·05, 0·44) and abdominal fullness (β = 0·05, 95 % CI: 0·01, 0·86). In contrast, among Whites, higher winter hot drink intake was linked to lower insomnia (β = –0·23, 95 % CI: –0·42, –0·04) and gas symptoms (β = –0·05, 95 % CI: –0·09, –0·01). Tertile analyses showed that, compared with tertile 1, Asians in the highest tertile of summer cold drink intake had higher insomnia scores (β = 1·26, 95 % CI: 0·19, 2·33), while Whites in the highest tertile of winter hot drink intake had lower depression scores (β = –1·73, 95 % CI: –3·28, –0·18). These associations were stronger among individuals with cold hands but not observed in those without. Findings suggest that the temperature of foods and beverages may influence mental and gut health, underscoring the need to consider temperature-related dietary habits in public health and nutrition strategies, particularly across diverse populations.
DOI: 10.1017/s000711452510514x
ISSN: 0007-1145
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1017/s000711452510514x-2025-10-15-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Relative associations of coffee, tea and plain water with all-cause and cause-specific mortality: a prospective cohort study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0007114525104248</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 140
Autoren: Chen Shi, Yu-Kun Wang, Min-Qian Yan, Zhen Peng, Jin-Lun Zhang, Yi-Ming Tao, Lin Yang, Li Li, Chun-Quan Ou
Journal: British Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-22
Abstract: Abstract
	  Previous studies highlighted the health benefits of coffee and tea, but they only focused on the comparisons between different consumptions. Consequently, the association estimate lacked a clear interpretation, as the substitution of beverages and distribution of doses were not explicitly prescribed. We focused on the ‘relative association’ to ascertain the optimal consumption strategy (including total intake and optimal allocation strategy) for coffee, tea and plain water associated with decreased mortality. Self-reported coffee, tea and plain water intake were used from the UK Biobank. Within a compositional data analysis framework, a multivariate Cox model was used to assess the relative associations after adjusting for a range of potential confounders. The lower mortality risk was observed with at least approximately 7–8 drinks/d of total consumption. When the total intake &amp;gt; 4 drinks/d, substituting plain water with coffee or tea was linked to reduced mortality; nevertheless, the benefit was not seen for ≤ 4 drinks/d. Besides, a balanced consumption of coffee and tea (roughly a ratio of 2:3) associated with the lowest hazard ratios of 0·55 (95 % CI 0·47, 0·64) for all-cause mortality, 0·59 (95 % CI 0·48, 0·72) for cancer mortality, 0·69 (95 % CI 0·49, 0·99) for CVD mortality, 0·28 (95 % CI 0·15, 0·52) for respiratory disease mortality and 0·35 (95 % CI 0·15, 0·82) for digestive disease mortality than other combinations. These results highlight the importance of the rational combination of coffee, tea and plain water, with particular emphasis on ensuring adequate total intake, offering more comprehensive and explicit guidance for individuals.
DOI: 10.1017/s0007114525104248
ISSN: 0007-1145
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1017/s0007114525104248-2025-10-15-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of tirzepatide on weight management in patients with and without diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41366-025-01920-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 106
Autoren: Eduardo Cerchi, Paula Arruda do Espírito Santo, Mariana Carvalho de Oliveira, Carolina Castro Porto Silva Janovsky, Bruno Halpern
Journal: International Journal of Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-27
DOI: 10.1038/s41366-025-01920-4
ISSN: 0307-0565
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41366-025-01920-4-2025-10-15-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>