<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 01:06:45 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 01:06:45 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Tech neck: the silent pandemic that is reshaping our spine</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00586-025-09444-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 86
Autoren: Andrew Savoia, John Streepy, Catherine Yuh, Arnold Wong, Dino Samartzis
Journal: European Spine Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-10
DOI: 10.1007/s00586-025-09444-1
ISSN: 0940-6719
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00586-025-09444-1-2025-10-30-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Collared fully hydroxyapatite-coated femoral components reduce early periprosthetic femoral fractures in total hip arthroplasty with the direct anterior approach</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1302/0301-620x.107b10.bjj-2024-1494.r1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 68
Autoren: Rui Hirasawa, Kazuhiro Oinuma, Shigeo Hagiwara, Takamitsu Sato, Yuya Kawarai, Yoko Miura, Junichi Nakamura, Seiji Ohtori
Journal: The Bone &amp;amp; Joint Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
Abstract: AimsThe purpose of this study was to investigate the difference in the incidence of early postoperative periprosthetic femoral fracture (POPFF) between flat-tapered wedge and collared fully hydroxyapatite (HA)-coated femoral components performed through the direct anterior approach (DAA).MethodsThis was a retrospective comparative study of 4,511 primary total hip arthroplasties (THAs), including 1,842 flat-tapered wedge and 2,669 collared fully HA-coated components, conducted by a single surgeon at a single institution using the DAA from August 2009 to June 2023. Propensity score matching was used to control confounding factors related to POPFF. After matching, 1,804 cases were selected for each group, and the incidence of early POPFF was compared between the two implant designs. An early POPFF was defined as a periprosthetic fracture undetected intraoperatively and on immediate postoperative radiographs that occurred within 90 days. The incidence of intraoperative periprosthetic femoral fracture (IOPFF) was also evaluated and compared between the two groups.ResultsEarly POPFF was significantly less frequent in the collared fully HA-coated designs (0.11%; n = 2) than in the flat-tapered wedge designs (0.72%; n = 13; p = 0.007). Regarding the details of early POPFFs, the median time to fracture was ten days and an injury mechanism was absent in 73% (n = 11). According to the Vancouver classification, two were fracture type A(G) and one was A(L), while B1 and B2 fractures comprised 33% (n = 5) and 47% (n = 7), respectively. Treatment methods included conservative management in 33% (n = 5), osteosynthesis in 53% (n = 8), and revision surgery in 13% (n = 2). IOPFF was significantly more frequent in the collared fully HA-coated designs (3.49%; n = 63) than in the flat-tapered wedge designs (2.00%; n = 36; p = 0.008).ConclusionThe results of this large-scale, propensity score-matched study implied that the incidence of early POPFFs with collared fully HA-coated femoral components was lower than flat-tapered wedge designs. However, the incidence of IOPFFs was higher with collared fully HA-coated femoral components. These findings highlight the importance of femoral component design, including broaching, in THA implant selection for POPFF and IOPFF.Cite this article: Bone Joint J 2025;107-B(10):1011–1019.
DOI: 10.1302/0301-620x.107b10.bjj-2024-1494.r1
ISSN: 2049-4394
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1302/0301-620x.107b10.bjj-2024-1494.r1-2025-10-30-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Characterizing Microstructural and Mechanical Properties of Dancer Achilles Tendon Using Ultrashort Echo Time MRI and Shear Wave Elastography Ultrasound</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/jor.70075</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 46
Autoren: Anna M. Horner, Felix M. Gonzalez, Courtney N. Gleason, Amanda Blackmon, Emma Faulkner, Damian Dyckman, Monica B. Umpierrez, Philip K.‐W. Wong, Vahid Khalilzad Sharghi, Pan Su, David A. Reiter
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-22
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    Previous observations of multi‐echo ultrashort echo time (UTE) magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) decay data from the Achilles tendon (AT) report an off‐resonance non‐water signal associated with non‐collagenous extracellular matrix (ECM) constituents. This cross‐sectional study investigates the relationship between this MRI‐derived tissue matrix signal and mechanical stiffness of the AT in professional ballet dancers and non‐dancer adults. Multiexponential analysis of multi‐echo UTE MRI was used to quantify water components and an off‐resonance AT matrix component. To compare AT structure with its functionality, shear wave elastography (SWE) ultrasound US was used to measure tendon stiffness along both longitudinal (V
                    L
                    ) and transverse (V
                    S
                    ) axes. 34 participants, including 15 ballet dancers and 19 non‐dancers, were studied. Dancers exhibited significantly larger V
                    S
                    (
                    p
                     = 0.013) compared to non‐dancers, consistent with prior observations of a training effect in tendon from repeated loading with exercise. UTE‐derived off‐resonance relaxation component amplitude, β
                    3
                    , was positively associated with V
                    L
                    in dancers (
                    p
                     = 0.029) and V
                    S
                    in non‐dancers (
                    p
                     = 0.024), suggesting a microstructural role of this matrix component. While additional work is needed to unambiguously assign this off‐resonance signal, these findings suggest its association with non‐collagenous ECM and show potential for combined use of UTE and SWE imaging to assess tendon structure‐function relationships and adaptations to mechanical loading in vivo.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/jor.70075
ISSN: 0736-0266
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/jor.70075-2025-10-30-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The changing face of acute low back pain management by physiotherapists, osteopaths and chiropractors in the UK: a 20-year comparison from 2003 to 2023</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 24
Autoren: David W. Evans, Nadine E. Foster, Alan C. Breen, Tamar Pincus, Martin Underwood, Steven Vogel
Journal: BMC Musculoskeletal Disorders
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-02
DOI: 10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9
ISSN: 1471-2474
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9-2025-10-30-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Time‐dependent wound management protocol prevents periprosthetic joint infection in total knee arthroplasty with persistent drainage</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/ksa.70077</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 16
Autoren: Filippo Leggieri, Francesco Ferriani, Enrico Di Benedetto, Enrick Miani, Enrico Festa, Giovanni Balato, Stefano M. P. Rossi, Francesco Benazzo, Andrea Baldini
Journal: Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-29
Abstract: AbstractPurposeThis study aimed to evaluate the success rate of a standardised protocol for managing persistent wound drainage following total knee arthroplasty (TKA).MethodsA prospective observational study was conducted at four institutions between January and June 2022 across primary and revision TKAs. Sixty‐two patients (mean age 71.5 ± 9.3 years; 45.2% male) who experienced postoperative wound drainage after primary (58.1%) or revision (41.9%) TKA were enrolled. The protocol included staged interventions: anticoagulation adjustments and dressing changes during Days 1–3, incisional negative pressure wound therapy during Days 3–5, and wound debridement above the joint capsule if drainage persisted beyond Day 7. Outcomes were evaluated using the ASEPSIS score. The primary outcome was defined as complete wound healing without progression to debridement, antibiotics and implant retention (DAIR) procedure or periprosthetic joint infection (PJI).ResultsThe mean follow‐up was 13.2 months (range, 11.7–15.1 months). The protocol achieved a 91.9% success rate in preventing progression to DAIR. The median number of visits required to achieve wound healing was 3.5 for the cohort. DAIR rate was 8.1% (n = 5), while PJI rate was 1.6% (n = 1). Primary TKA procedures demonstrated more efficient healing trajectories compared to revision cases, requiring fewer clinical visits (median 3 vs. 5, p &amp;lt; 0.001) and shorter hospital stays (mean 4.5 vs. 7.5 days, p = 0.017). Cox proportional hazards model identified intervention type (revision vs. primary, hazard ratio [HR] 0.24, p &amp;lt; 0.001), advanced age (HR: 0.95 per year, p = 0.006), and male gender (HR: 0.45, p = 0.020) as significant independent predictors of increased time required to achieve wound healing.ConclusionOur standardised wound management protocol achieved a high success rate in preventing progression to PJI following TKA. The time‐dependent approach to intervention escalation provides clear clinical decision‐making criteria and suggests that early identification and systematic management of wound complications are critical determinants of successful outcomes, particularly for primary TKA procedures.Level of EvidenceLevel II.
DOI: 10.1002/ksa.70077
ISSN: 0942-2056
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/ksa.70077-2025-10-30-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>