<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:59:08 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:59:08 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Habitual fluid intake and hydration status influence cortisol reactivity to acute psychosocial stress</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 1677
Autoren: Daniel S. Kashi, Marianne Hunter, Jason P. Edwards, Juliane Zemdegs, Jennifer Lourenço, Anne-Cécile Mille, Erica T. Perrier, Alberto Dolci, Neil P. Walsh
Journal: Journal of Applied Physiology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract:  Cortisol reactivity to acute stress predicts long-term health. Our novel findings show greater cortisol reactivity to acute stress in adults with habitual low fluid intake. Suboptimal hydration (e.g., darker morning urine) was associated with greater cortisol reactivity to acute stress. These findings provide one possible explanation for why habitual low fluid intake and suboptimal hydration are related to poor long-term health. Furthermore, researchers should account for hydration when assessing cortisol reactivity to acute stressors. 
DOI: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025
ISSN: 8750-7587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025-2025-09-04-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Trans* Athletes in Sport: Not Ceding to the Sex/Gender Binary of Gender Critical Feminism1</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1123/ssj.2024-0030</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 144
Autoren: Michael Burke, Matthew Klugman
Journal: Sociology of Sport Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract: Debates over the position(ing) of trans* athletes in sport have been reignited in the last decade because of the confluence of broader political debates over the provision of rights of self-identification for trans* people with the International Olympic Committee’s decision to place responsibility for transgender regulations in the hands of international sporting federations. The effect of this confluence has meant a regressive shift back toward hard essentialism with regard to sex categories in sport. This paper challenges the politically powerful, yet romanticized and historically inaccurate, narrative that so-called gender critical feminists have produced to support this regressive move.
DOI: 10.1123/ssj.2024-0030
ISSN: 0741-1235
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1123/ssj.2024-0030-2025-09-04-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of aerobic or resistance exercise during neoadjuvant chemotherapy on tumor response and therapy completion in women with breast cancer: The randomized controlled BENEFIT trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101064</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 54
Autoren: Martina E. Schmidt, Siri Goldschmidt, Charlotte Kreutz, Jana Müller, Andreas Schneeweiss, Anne M. May, Friederike Rosenberger, Joachim Wiskemann, Karen Steindorf
Journal: Journal of Sport and Health Science
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101064
ISSN: 2095-2546
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101064-2025-09-04-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Consensus Statements—Optimizing Performance of the Elite Athlete</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/sms.70112</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 45
Autoren: Jens Bangsbo, Morten Hostrup, Ylva Hellsten, Mette Hansen, Anna Melin, Michael Kjær, Jamie F. Burr, Lars Engebretsen, Brendan Egan, Anthony C. Hackney, Toby L. Chambers, Andrew M. Jones, Yannis Pitsiladis, Peter Magnusson, Jesper Petersen, Atul S. Deshmukh, Jose A. L. Calbet, Kirsty Elliott‐Sale, Mike Joyner, Jesper L. Andersen, Peter M. Christensen, Michael R. Dünweber, Tue Rømer, Kate A. Wickham, Søren K. Jessen, Julie Kissow, Jan S. Jeppesen, Lukas Moesgaard
Journal: Scandinavian Journal of Medicine &amp;amp; Science in Sports
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
Abstract: ABSTRACTThe International Consensus Conference “Optimising Performance of the Elite Athlete,” held in November 2024, brought together 29 scientists, some coaches, and athletes to establish evidence‐based consensus statements aimed at enhancing elite athletic performance and health. The conference addressed critical themes including training strategies, nutrition, female athlete considerations, injury management, and emerging technologies. Key conclusions emphasize individualized, sport‐specific approaches to training and nutrition, integrating concurrent training modalities to improve endurance, resilience, and efficiency. Nutrition strategies highlight the importance of tailored energy and macronutrient periodization, recognition of low energy availability risks, and cautious use of dietary supplements. Special attention was directed to female athletes, advocating for improved monitoring of menstrual cycles and hormonal status, while acknowledging current knowledge gaps in hormonal influences on performance and injury risk. Injury prevention remains a challenge, with tendon overuse and Achilles tendon ruptures significantly impacting athlete careers; rehabilitation should rely on criteria‐based progression and multidisciplinary input. Emerging technologies, including wearable sensors and multi‐omics analyses, hold promise for personalized training and nutrition but require further validation in elite contexts. Despite robust consensus, the panel identified substantial research gaps, particularly regarding female athletes, longitudinal training effects, and efficacy of novel interventions. This consensus provides a practical, scientifically grounded framework to optimize elite athlete performance and health, while underscoring the need for continued research to address outstanding questions and promote inclusive evidence‐based practices.
DOI: 10.1111/sms.70112
ISSN: 0905-7188
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/sms.70112-2025-09-04-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The role of adipose tissue in critical illness-induced skeletal muscle wasting—new considerations for treatment approaches</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1152/japplphysiol.00203.2025</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 41
Autoren: Casey L. Sexton, Selene Meza-Perez, Konstantinos Papanikolaou, Tomasz M. Kaminski, Marta Nowacka-Chmielewska, Piotr Rodak, Yi Lin, Thomas W. Buford, Peter E. Morris, Davis A. Englund, Robert T. Mankowski
Journal: Journal of Applied Physiology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
Abstract:  Critical illness-induced muscle wasting is associated with poor in-hospital and long-term outcomes, but prevention strategies are lacking. Critical illness elicits muscle wasting through upregulation of protein degradation and downregulation of protein synthesis via primary (i.e., modulation of ubiquitin-proteasome, autophagy-lysosome, calpain, and caspase-3 pathways) and secondary (i.e., bed rest/disuse, nutritional modulation, and accumulation of cellular damage) mechanisms. However, therapeutic targeting of these skeletal muscle mechanisms has not advanced the prevention of critical illness-induced muscle wasting, which may require exploring the roles of other peripheral organs. For example, recent research has demonstrated positive associations between whole-body adipose tissue mass, maintenance of muscle mass, and lower mortality rates in critically ill patients. However, having excess adiposity is often associated with impaired skeletal muscle remodeling due to blunted anabolic signaling, which has been tied to insulin resistance, lipid accumulation, and inflammation. Thus, the positive association between adiposity and beneficial outcomes in critical illness is paradoxical. This may be explained, at least partially, by an incomplete understanding of the processes by which adipose tissue influences skeletal muscle health and function in the context of critical illness. This review highlights the current evidence and key questions that warrant further investigations to improve understanding of the relationship between adipose tissue and skeletal muscle health. This knowledge may then be leveraged to facilitate new therapeutic approaches aimed at improving skeletal muscle health and functional outcomes in patients with critical illness. 
DOI: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00203.2025
ISSN: 8750-7587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1152/japplphysiol.00203.2025-2025-09-04-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>