<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 01:07:31 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 01:07:31 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Pain Science in Practice (Part 8): Nociceptive, Neuropathic and Nociplastic Pain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13335</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 24
Autoren: Morten Hoegh, Paul Hodges
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-29
Abstract:  Identification of pain descriptors provide a plausible method to consider personalisation of management of pain based on presumed underlying mechanisms. The aim is to use mechanistic pain descriptors (nociceptive, neuropathic and nociplastic pain) to guide clinical practice into an era of personalised medicine for people with pain. Clinicians should understand the concept of descriptors to improve their understanding of a mechanism-based management of chronic pain. Nonetheless, all treatment of individuals suffering from chronic pain should be holistic (i.e., person-centred). Nociplastic pain already serves as an evidence-based explanation that can help make sense of pain without any known pathology, but is not ready to be considered as a target for treatment in itself, based on the current level of evidence. To summarise, treatment outcomes may benefit when treatments are matched to patients according to mechanistic descriptors, and current research initiatives are working on bring this closer to the clinic. 
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13335
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13335-2025-08-09-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The content of diagnostic information has an immediate effect on pain with loading in people with midportion Achilles tendinopathy: a randomized clinical experiment</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101244</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 23
Autoren: Nigel J Travers, Mervyn J Travers, William Gibson, James R Debenham, Dana A Hince, Benedict M Wand
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101244
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101244-2025-08-09-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Physioethology: a post-humanist perspective on physiotherapy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/09593985.2025.2532572</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 23
Autoren: Matthew Low, Fiona H. Moffatt, Roger Kerry, David A. Nicholls
Journal: Physiotherapy Theory and Practice
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-18
DOI: 10.1080/09593985.2025.2532572
ISSN: 0959-3985
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/09593985.2025.2532572-2025-08-09-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Hip muscle strength in patients with chronic ankle instability: A systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ptsp.2025.07.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 23
Autoren: Jiawei Zheng, Bing Xu, Xinxin Xiong, Jian Chen
Journal: Physical Therapy in Sport
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ptsp.2025.07.007
ISSN: 1466-853X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ptsp.2025.07.007-2025-08-09-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Training on Childhood Apraxia of Speech: Experiences of Speech-Language Pathologists</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1044/2025_ajslp-24-00224</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 17
Autoren: Sydney Keller, Hannah Valentine, Daphna Harel, Maria I. Grigos
Journal: American Journal of Speech-Language Pathology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-29
Abstract: 
            Purpose:
            The diagnosis and treatment of childhood apraxia of speech (CAS) remains a clinical challenge for many speech-language pathologists (SLPs). Given this, it is imperative to understand how SLPs learn about CAS during graduate school and throughout their careers.
          
          
            Method:
            In the current study, American Speech-Language-Hearing Association–certified SLPs who practice in the United States and work with young children completed a 32-item online survey. Survey items aimed to understand SLPs' experiences learning about CAS during graduate school and through continuing education (CE). Respondents were evaluated on their knowledge of diagnosing and treating CAS (against an expert consensus). Finally, the survey sought to investigate how respondents' learning experiences related to their knowledge of diagnosing and treating CAS.
          
          
            Results:
            
              In total, 346 clinicians completed the survey. Reliance on CE (
              p
              &amp;lt; .001) and scientific literature in SLP (
              p
              &amp;lt; .01) were found to be the only positive significant predictors of CAS knowledge. No graduate school experiences positively predicted CAS knowledge. The majority of clinicians indicated being unprepared to diagnose and treat CAS based on their graduate-level education but reported high levels of satisfaction for CE resources for CAS.
            
          
          
            Conclusions:
            Results of this study highlight challenges in graduate program models for training on CAS. Implications for graduate program models are discussed.
          
DOI: 10.1044/2025_ajslp-24-00224
ISSN: 1058-0360
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1044/2025_ajslp-24-00224-2025-08-09-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>