<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 01:14:42 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 01:14:42 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Developmental Language Disorder as a Multidimensional Neurodevelopmental Spectrum: Implications for Diagnosis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00089</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 25
Autoren: Karla K. McGregor, Lisa Goffman, Elena Plante, Krystal Werfel
Journal: Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-10
Abstract: 
                    Purpose:
                    We aimed to create a comprehensive understanding of the dilemmas involved in the diagnosis of developmental language disorder (DLD) and to highlight the potential of a multidimensional spectral account of DLD for addressing these dilemmas.
                  
                  
                    Method:
                    We conducted an integrative literature review.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions:
                    Considerable gains in understanding the genetics and neurobiology of DLD provide new explanations for long-observed phenomena such as heterogeneity of presentation, phenotypic overlap with other neurodevelopmental conditions, and the challenges of diagnosis. Although categorical nosologies benefit diagnostic decision making, facilitate communication, and align well with bureaucratic systems, they offer overly simple ways of defining DLD. The presentation of DLD is broad rather than narrow, spectral rather than categorical, and dynamic rather than static; therefore, DLD is better described as a multidimensional spectral system than as a categorical entity. It is not practical or even advisable to abandon the traditional categorical framing of DLD at this point. However, maintaining awareness of the tension between the categorical framing and the spectral nature of DLD may improve diagnosis, prognosis, and alignment with the construct of neurodiversity.
                  
DOI: 10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00089
ISSN: 1092-4388
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1044/2025_jslhr-25-00089-2026-01-12-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Patient Concerns Are Often Overlooked by Low Back Pain (LBP) Guidelines</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2026.9001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 24
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: Infographic illustrating the article “People With Acute Low Back Pain Have Concerns That May Not Be Addressed by Guideline-Recommended Advice: A Mixed-Methods Study”, which was published in the September 2024 issue of JOSPT.
                  J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2026;56(1):64. doi:10.2519/jospt.2026.9001
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2026.9001
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2026.9001-2026-01-12-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The pain education paradox and validation gap</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103476</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 21
Autoren: Asaf Weisman, Monica Noy, Youssef Masharawi
Journal: Musculoskeletal Science and Practice
Veröffentlicht: 2026-02-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103476
ISSN: 2468-7812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.msksp.2025.103476-2026-01-12-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Intermittent theta-burst stimulation for post-stroke cognitive impairment: a double-blind randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/10749357.2025.2605295</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 18
Autoren: Yueying Wang, Huiyue Feng, Jingang Dai, Qin Wang
Journal: Topics in Stroke Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-25
DOI: 10.1080/10749357.2025.2605295
ISSN: 1074-9357
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/10749357.2025.2605295-2026-01-12-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Sequential Changes in Scapular Range of Motion After An Intervention Using the KOJI AWARENESS Original “Wall Angel Slider” Exercise</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1123/jsr.2024-0426</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 17
Autoren: Koji Murofushi, Sho Mitomo, Kenji Hirohata, Hidetaka Furuya, Hiroshi Akuzawa, Hiroki Katagiri, Koji Kaneoka, Kazuyoshi Yagishita
Journal: Journal of Sport Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: 
                    
                      Context
                      :
                    
                    We aimed to evaluate the sequential changes in the scapular range of motion (ROM) after an intervention using the KOJI AWARENESS Original Wall Angel Slider exercise in which reverse motion is applied.
                    
                      Design
                      :
                    
                    This study used a single-group, pretest–posttest design to evaluate changes in scapular ROM following an intervention.
                    
                      Methods
                      :
                    
                    Participants (n = 54) underwent a 2-week intervention in this study. Scapular mobility was screened using the KOJI AWARENESS Self-Screening Scapula Mobility test, and participants with scapular mobility restrictions were recruited (n = 48). The participants performed the Wall Angel Slider exercise involving reverse motion tasks with dynamic sliding movements against a wall. They performed 3 sets of 8 repetitions for 6 sessions in 2 weeks, and adherence to the exercise regimen was monitored using a checklist. The scapular upward rotation and glenohumeral joint external rotation ROM were measured before the intervention, immediately after the first session, and after 2 weeks of the intervention.
                    
                      Results
                      :
                    
                    The participants exhibited significant improvements in scapular upward rotation and glenohumeral external rotation ROM after the first session of an intervention using the Wall Angel Slider exercise and after 2 weeks of the intervention.
                    
                      Conclusion
                      :
                    
                    The KOJI AWARENESS Original Wall Angel Slider exercise effectively improves scapular upward rotation and glenohumeral joint external rotation ROM over a 2-week intervention period, suggesting its potential utility in enhancing scapular mobility and function in clinical practice.
                  
DOI: 10.1123/jsr.2024-0426
ISSN: 1056-6716
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1123/jsr.2024-0426-2026-01-12-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>