<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 01:03:08 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 01:03:08 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Prevalence and severity of symptoms across the menopause transition: cross-sectional findings from the Australian Women's Midlife Years (AMY) Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00138-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 558
Autoren: Rakibul M Islam, Molly Bond, Aida Ghalebeigi, Yuanyuan Wang, Karen Walker-Bone, Susan R Davis
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00138-x
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00138-x-2025-08-20-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Protective effect of metformin against dementia in patients with obesity: Results from a global federated health network analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/dom.16647</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 377
Autoren: Yu‐Liang Lin, Yi‐Jui Hung, Jin‐Hua Chen, Jia‐Ying Sung, Min‐Huei Hsu, Hoang Khanh Dinh, Kee‐Hsin Chen, Chiehfeng Chen
Journal: Diabetes, Obesity and Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-06
Abstract: AbstractAimsMetformin, a first‐line medication for Type 2 diabetes (T2D), has been suggested to reduce dementia risk. We investigated whether metformin use was associated with lower long‐term incidence of dementia and all‐cause mortality in obese patients.Materials and MethodsWe analysed electronic health record data from the TriNetX network. Patients were categorised into four body mass index (BMI) groups (25–29.9, 30–34.9, 35–39.9 and over 40). In each group, those prescribed metformin were compared with matched controls who were not prescribed metformin, using propensity score matching. Kaplan–Meier survival analysis was used to estimate dementia incidence and all‐cause mortality over a 10‐year follow‐up.ResultsThe matched cohorts included 132 920 (BMI 25–29.9), 142 723 (30–34.9), 94 402 (35–39.9) and 82 732 (over 40) patients per group. After 10 years of follow‐up, metformin users exhibited significantly lower risks of both dementia and all‐cause mortality compared to controls. Specifically, the hazard ratios for dementia across each BMI group were 0.875 (95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.848–0.904), 0.917 (0.885–0.951), 0.878 (0.834–0.924) and 0.891 (0.834–0.953), respectively. For all‐cause mortality, the corresponding hazard ratios were 0.719 (0.701–0.737), 0.727 (0.708–0.746), 0.717 (0.694–0.741) and 0.743 (0.717–0.771).ConclusionsIn this large, multi‐centre cohort study, metformin use was associated with reduced risks of dementia and all‐cause mortality in obese patients. The protective effect was observed across all BMI groups, with variations noted by population. These findings support the potential of metformin in lowering dementia risk in patients with obesity. Further studies are needed to explore the underlying mechanisms.
DOI: 10.1111/dom.16647
ISSN: 1462-8902
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/dom.16647-2025-08-20-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Non-autoimmune, insulin-deficient diabetes in children and young adults in Africa: evidence from the Young-Onset Diabetes in sub-Saharan Africa (YODA) cross-sectional study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00120-2</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 350
Autoren: Jean Claude Katte, Steven Squires, Mesmin Y Dehayem, Priscilla A Balungi, Carolyn J Padoa, Dhriti Sengupta, Segun Fatumo, Thereza Piloya, Catherine Nyangabyaki-Twesigye, Silver Bahendeka, Edna Majaliwa, Kandi C Muze, Kaushik Ramaiya, Suzanne Sap, Ayesha A Motala, Fraser J Pirie, Paul Rheeder, Jacobus C Van Dyk, Jean Claude Mbanya, Beverley M Shields, Amy S Shah, Catherine Pihoker, Jasmin Divers, Kashyap A Patel, Richard A Oram, Dana Dabelea, Andrew T Hattersley, Timothy J McDonald, Nigel J Crowther, Moffat J Nyirenda, Eugene Sobngwi, Angus G Jones
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00120-2
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00120-2-2025-08-20-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Unexpected effects of semaglutide on skeletal muscle mass and force-generating capacity in mice</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.004</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 335
Autoren: Takuya Karasawa, Ran Hee Choi, Cesar A. Meza, Subhasmita Rout, Micah J. Drummond, Amandine Chaix, Katsuhiko Funai
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.004
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.004-2025-08-20-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The source of dietary fat influences anti-tumour immunity in obese mice</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s42255-025-01330-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 283
Autoren: Britta Kunkemoeller, Hannah Prendeville, Claire McIntyre, Ayantu Temesgen, Rόisín M. Loftus, Conghui Yao, Lydia Dyck, Linda V. Sinclair, Christina Rollings, Aaron Douglas, Gerard Pernes, Kathleen A. J. Mitchelson, Cathal Harmon, Mathilde Raverdeau, Ross Ward, Harry Kane, Jaclyn Kline, Katie L. O’Brien, Martin Brennan, Frances Smith, Brenneth Stevens, Helen M. Roche, Ed C. Lavelle, David K. Finlay, Doreen A. Cantrell, Edward T. Chouchani, Susan Kaech, Evanna L. Mills, Marcia Haigis, Lydia Lynch
Journal: Nature Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-25
DOI: 10.1038/s42255-025-01330-w
ISSN: 2522-5812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s42255-025-01330-w-2025-08-20-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>