<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 01:13:45 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 01:13:45 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Agreement between high-quality clinical practice guidelines in their treatment recommendations for low back pain: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.spinee.2025.07.015</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 43
Autoren: Bayden J. McKenzie, Romi Haas, Giovanni E. Ferreira, Alexandra Gorelik, Sheila Cyril, Jia Xi Han, Stephen Gilbert, Liesl Grobler, Chris G. Maher, Rachelle Buchbinder
Journal: The Spine Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.spinee.2025.07.015
ISSN: 1529-9430
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.spinee.2025.07.015-2025-11-30-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Physiotherapy Compared With Shockwave Therapy for the Treatment of Proximal Hamstring Tendinopathy: A Randomized Controlled Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/03635465251391134</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 21
Autoren: Aidan Rich, Jon Ford, Jilliane Cook, Andrew Hahne
Journal: The American Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-16
Abstract: 
                    Background:
                    Proximal hamstring tendinopathy (PHT) presents as localized lower buttock pain with tasks such as running and sitting.
                  
                  
                    Purpose:
                    To investigate the effectiveness of individualized physiotherapy compared with shockwave therapy on pain and function in PHT.
                  
                  
                    Methods:
                    This prospective parallel-group, assessor-blinded randomized controlled trial (RCT) was set in 10 primary care physiotherapy practices in Victoria, Australia. A total of 100 participants with PHT were randomly assigned to receive 6 sessions of either individualized physiotherapy or shockwave therapy, with both groups receiving standardized advice and education. Primary outcomes were global rating of change on a 7-point Likert scale and the Victorian Institute of Sport Assessment Scale for Proximal Hamstring Tendinopathy at 4, 12, 26, and 52 weeks postrandomization. Analyses were by intention-to-treat using linear mixed models.
                  
                  
                    Results:
                    All except 1 patient received the allocated intervention, and the participant follow-up rate was 88% at 12 months. There were no significant differences between groups in primary outcomes at any time point. For secondary outcome measures, participants in the shockwave group had statistically significantly greater satisfaction with treatment at 26 weeks, satisfaction with results of treatment at 4 and 26 weeks, and general health at 52 weeks. Responder analyses of participants achieving clinically significant improvements showed no significant differences between groups at any time point.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion:
                    This RCT found no difference in effectiveness of individualized physiotherapy compared with shockwave therapy on global effect or function in PHT. Future trials on PHT appear feasible but could explore a different sample population or other intervention and/or comparison groups.
                  
                  
                    Registration:
                    ACTRN12621000846820 (Australian New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry).
                  
DOI: 10.1177/03635465251391134
ISSN: 0363-5465
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/03635465251391134-2025-11-30-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of seven types of exercise in the treatment of rotator cuff-related shoulder pain (RCRSP): a systematic review and Bayesian network meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13018-025-06514-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 16
Autoren: Wei Zhang, Minghui Du, Liang Xia, Fengqi Hao, Meihong Tian
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic Surgery and Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-23
DOI: 10.1186/s13018-025-06514-4
ISSN: 1749-799X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s13018-025-06514-4-2025-11-30-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Pain Catastrophizing Beliefs and Neuropathic Symptoms Are Associated With a Poorer Long-Term Recovery in Chronic Plantar Heel Pain: A Cohort Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/ptj/pzaf134</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 14
Autoren: Jason Rogers, Graeme Jones, Karen Wills, Tania Winzenberg
Journal: Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-07
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Importance
                    Chronic plantar heel pain is common and often recalcitrant yet understanding of modifiable risk factors that influence its trajectory of recovery is limited.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    The objective of this study was to describe associations of changes in physical and psychological measures and symptom descriptors over 12 months with changes in pain, function, and quality of life in people with chronic plantar heel pain.
                  
                  
                    Design
                    A prospective cohort with longitudinal follow-up was used.
                  
                  
                    Setting
                    A community setting in southern Tasmania was used.
                  
                  
                    Participants
                    The participants were 220 people with a clinical diagnosis of chronic plantar heel pain.
                  
                  
                    Exposures
                    The exposures were body mass index (kg/m2), waist circumference (centimeters), ankle plantarflexor strength (kilograms), ankle and first metatarsophalangeal joint dorsiflexion mobility (degrees), pain catastrophizing beliefs (Pain Catastrophizing Scale), depression (9-item Patient Health Questionnaire), multisite pain, morning stiffness, neuropathic symptoms (painDETECT), and physical activity (accelerometry).
                  
                  
                    Main Outcomes and Measures
                    The Foot Health Status Questionnaire pain and function domains and the 6-dimension Assessment of Quality of Life Scale were used. Outcomes and exposures were assessed at baseline and 12 months. Data were analyzed using linear mixed-effects models with exposure × time interactions.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Increasing pain catastrophizing and neuropathic painDETECT scores over 12 months were associated with a poorer trajectory of pain recovery (pain catastrophizing interaction β = −0.39 [95% CI = −0.01 to −0.77]; painDETECT interaction β = −0.79 [95% CI = −0.10 to −1.48]). In full multivariable models, there were no other significant associations between any other variable and pain. The only associations with foot function and quality of life were weak negative associations of steps per day and sedentary time with function and quality of life, respectively.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions and Relevance
                    Increasing pain catastrophizing and neuropathic symptoms were associated with poorer pain outcomes over 12 months in individuals with chronic plantar heel pain. These findings highlight the importance of pain beliefs and neurogenic factors in the prognosis of chronic plantar heel pain. Interventions targeting pain beliefs and neuropathic mechanisms may improve outcomes in subgroups with these characteristics.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/ptj/pzaf134
ISSN: 0031-9023
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/ptj/pzaf134-2025-11-30-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Ankle dorsiflexion range of motion is associated with compression stiffness of gastrocnemius and soleus muscles, foot structures, and hallux extension range of motion</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fas.2025.11.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 14
Autoren: Yuta Koshino, Tomoya Takabayashi, Takumi Kobayashi, Shintarou Kudo, Mutsuaki Edama
Journal: Foot and Ankle Surgery
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.fas.2025.11.007
ISSN: 1268-7731
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-30</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.fas.2025.11.007-2025-11-30-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>