<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:11:08 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:11:08 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Subretinal Photovoltaic Implant to Restore Vision in Geographic Atrophy Due to AMD</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2501396</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2811
Autoren: Frank G. Holz, Yannick Le Mer, Mahiul M.K. Muqit, Lars-Olof Hattenbach, Andrea Cusumano, Salvatore Grisanti, Laurent Kodjikian, Marco Andrea Pileri, Frederic Matonti, Eric Souied, Boris V. Stanzel, Peter Szurman, Michel Weber, Karl Ulrich Bartz-Schmidt, Nicole Eter, Marie Noelle Delyfer, Jean François Girmens, Koen A. van Overdam, Armin Wolf, Ralf Hornig, Martina Corazzol, Frank Brodie, Lisa Olmos de Koo, Daniel Palanker, José-Alain Sahel
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-15
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2501396
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2501396-2026-01-20-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Universal Base-Edited CAR7 T Cells for T-Cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2505478</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1931
Autoren: Robert Chiesa, Christos Georgiadis, Hebatalla Rashed, Roland Preece, Prudence Hardefeldt, Jan Chu, Jemma Selvage, Avijeet Mishra, Batoul Ahmed, Stuart Adams, Rebecca Thomas, Kimberly Gilmour, Annie Etuk, Deborah Yallop, David O’Connor, Waseem Qasim
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-08
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2505478
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2505478-2026-01-20-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Clinical Trials Affected by Research Grant Terminations at the National Institutes of Health</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1517
Autoren: Vishal R. Patel, Michael Liu, Anupam B. Jena
Journal: JAMA Internal Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: This cross-sectional study summarizes the number of trials with terminated grants from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and calculates the proportion of affected trials among those with previously active NIH funding, by trial status at time of grant termination and by trial characteristics.
DOI: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088
ISSN: 2168-6106
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088-2026-01-20-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Updated Labeling for Menopausal Hormone Therapy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2025.22259</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1166
Autoren: Martin A. Makary, Christine P. Nguyen, Tracy Beth Høeg, George F. Tidmarsh
Journal: JAMA
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-13
Abstract: This Viewpoint describes the US Food and Drug Administration’s intended label updates and removal of black box warnings for menopausal hormone therapy based on current evidence.
DOI: 10.1001/jama.2025.22259
ISSN: 0098-7484
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jama.2025.22259-2026-01-20-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Role of Vaccination in Maternal and Perinatal Outcomes Associated With COVID-19 in Pregnancy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2025.21001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1141
Autoren: Elisabeth McClymont, Sandra Blitz, Lucia Forward, Sara Cole, Gillian D. Alton, Isabelle Boucoiran, Krista Cassell, Eliana Castillo, Joan Crane, Verena Kuret, Gaetane LeBlanc Cormier, Phil A. Murphy, Vanessa Poliquin, Sarah Saunders, Heather Scott, Prakeshkumar Shah, John W. Snelgrove, Ann E. Sprague, Mark H. Yudin, Deborah Money, CANCOVID-Preg Team, Haim Abenhaim, Arianne Albert, Gal Av-Gay, Jon Barrett, Marc Beltempo, Rachelle Blais, Kathryn Bocking, Cindy Breitkreutz, Richard Brown, Emmanuel Bujold, Marguerite Cameron, George Carson, Jeannette Comeau, Susan Crawford, Natalie Dayan, Tina Delaney, Suzanne Demers, Kerry Dust, Darine El-Chaar, Chelsea Elwood, Arnaud Gagneur, Pascale Guerin, JoAnn Harrold, Chloe Joynt, Fatima Kakkar, Emma Karlsen, France Leduc, Carla Loeppky, Evelyn Maan, Isabelle Malhamé, Ann Kinga Malinowski, Jocelyne Martel, Ayman Abou Mehrem, Andrea Morrissey, Ali Nabeel, Maha Othman, Jean-Charles Pasquier, Bruno Piedboeuf, Tiffany Reeve, Catherine Riddell, Ashley Roberts, Greg Ryan, Manish Sadarangani, Laura Sauvé, Marie-Claude Tanguay, Joseph Ting, Laurent Tordjman, Isabelle Vachon, Julie van Schalkwyk, Mark Walker, Julie Warren, Heather Watson, Wendy Whittle, Bi Lan Wo
Journal: JAMA
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-13
Abstract: 
                    Importance
                    Gaps in knowledge exist about the impact of COVID-19 and vaccination on pregnancy outcomes.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    To investigate the impact of vaccination on maternal and perinatal outcomes associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection in pregnancy.
                  
                  
                    Design, Setting, and Population
                    Population-level surveillance of pregnant individuals infected with SARS-CoV-2 and their infants using the CANCOVID-Preg database between April 5, 2021 (beginning of the Delta variant time period and initiation of recommendations for vaccination in pregnancy in Canada), and December 31, 2022. Cases were identified based on COVID-19 diagnoses in pregnancy in 9 of 13 Canadian provinces/territories. Cases occurring through 2022 were followed up into 2023 for pregnancy conclusion and infant outcomes.
                  
                  
                    Exposure
                    SARS-CoV-2 infection in pregnancy, with or without prior vaccination.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcomes and Measures
                    COVID-19–associated hospitalization, critical care unit admission, and preterm birth.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Of 26 584 cases identified, 19 899 cases were eligible for analysis. Among these, most infections occurred among those aged 30 to 35 years (46.3%) and among those of White race (55.9%). A total of 72% (n = 14 367) of cases were vaccinated and 28% (n = 5532) were unvaccinated prior to their COVID-19 diagnosis. Among those vaccinated prior to COVID-19 diagnosis, 80% (n = 11 425) were vaccinated prior to pregnancy and 20% (n = 2942) were vaccinated during pregnancy. Cases occurred during both Delta (n = 6120) and Omicron (n = 13 799) variant time periods. Vaccination was associated with lower risk of hospitalization (Delta: relative risk [RR], 0.38 [95% CI, 0.30-0.48]; absolute risk difference [ARD], 8.7% [95% CI, 7.3%-10.2%]; Omicron: RR, 0.38 [95% CI, 0.27-0.53]; ARD, 3.8% [95% CI, 2.4%-5.2%]), critical care unit admission (Delta: RR, 0.10 [95% CI, 0.04-0.26]; ARD, 2.4% [95% CI, 1.8%-2.9%]; Omicron: RR, 0.10 [95% CI, 0.03-0.29]; ARD, 0.85% [95% CI, 0.27%-1.44%]), and preterm birth (Delta: RR, 0.80 [95% CI, 0.66-0.98]; ARD, 1.8% [95% CI, 0.3%-3.4%]; Omicron: RR, 0.64 [95% CI, 0.52-0.77]; ARD, 4.1% [95% CI, 2.0%-6.2%]). In multivariable analyses, vaccination was still associated with lower hospitalization risk in both variant time periods after controlling for comorbid conditions. In Omicron, compared with the vaccinated group, those unvaccinated had an adjusted RR of hospitalization of 2.43 (95% CI, 1.72-3.43). In Delta, those unvaccinated had an adjusted RR of hospitalization of 3.82 (95% CI, 2.38-6.14).
                  
                  
                    Conclusions and Relevance
                    Vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 prior to and during pregnancy, before COVID-19 diagnosis, was associated with a lower risk of severe maternal disease and preterm birth regardless of variant time period.
                  
DOI: 10.1001/jama.2025.21001
ISSN: 0098-7484
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jama.2025.21001-2026-01-20-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>