<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 01:07:31 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 01:07:31 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>PEPITEM and its tripeptide pharmacophores: Mechanisms of bone regulation and therapeutic potential in health and disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118489</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 117
Autoren: Kathryn Frost, Alyssa Urbanowski, Georgiana Neag, Jonathan W. Lewis, Ellie Northall, Samuel Kemble, Emily Powell, Adam P. Croft, Asif J. Iqbal, G. Ed Rainger, James R. Edwards, Amy J. Naylor, Helen M. McGettrick
Journal: Biomedicine &amp;amp; Pharmacotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118489
ISSN: 0753-3322
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.biopha.2025.118489-2025-09-28-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Investigating the safety and tolerability of single-dose psilocybin for post-traumatic stress disorder: A nonrandomized open-label clinical trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/02698811251362390</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 79
Autoren: Niall M. McGowan, James J. Rucker, Rachel Yehuda, Manish Agrawal, Nadav Liam Modlin, Hollie Simmons, Agata Tofil-Kaluza, Shriya Das, Guy M. Goodwin
Journal: Journal of Psychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-29
Abstract: 
            Background:
            Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is a debilitating condition for which there are few efficacious treatments. Psilocybin is being studied for use in treatment-resistant depression but has not yet been investigated in PTSD.
          
          
            Aims:
            The trial’s primary outcome was to investigate the safety and tolerability of single-dose psilocybin in participants with PTSD.
          
          
            Methods:
            This was a Phase 2, nonrandomized, open-label, multicenter trial. Secondary outcomes were changes in PTSD symptoms (Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale for DSM-5 (CAPS-5); PTSD Checklist for DSM-5 (PCL-5)), functional impairment (Sheehan Disability Scale; SDS) and quality of life (EQ-5D-5L index score).
          
          
            Results:
            
              Amongst the 22 participants enrolled (63.6% female; mean (SD) age, 39.0 (7.91) years), there was a total of 117 treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs); 70 (59.8%) were reported on administration day, of which 64/70 (91.4%) resolved by the end of the next day. TEAEs commonly included headache (
              n
               = 11; 50.0%), nausea (
              n
               = 8; 36.4%), crying (
              n
               = 6; 27.3%) and fatigue (
              n
               = 6; 27.3%). There were no serious TEAEs or TEAEs leading to study withdrawal. Pre-post comparisons indicated a clinically meaningful change from Baseline in mean CAPS-5 total score at Week 4 (−29.9 (14.06)) and Week 12 (−29.5 (15.43)), which was associated with the intensity of psychedelic experience on Day 1. PCL-5 scores showed symptom reduction was rapid and sustained until Week 12. SDS total score and EQ-5D-5L index score showed similar improvements.
            
          
          
            Conclusions:
            Psilocybin at a dose of 25 mg, administered with psychological support, may be safe, well-tolerated and associated with symptomatic improvement in adults with PTSD. Further investigation is warranted.
          
          
            Clinical trial registration:
            ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT05312151
            (https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT05312151)
          
DOI: 10.1177/02698811251362390
ISSN: 0269-8811
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/02698811251362390-2025-09-28-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A New Ashwagandha Formulation (Zenroot™) Alleviates Stress and Anxiety Symptoms While Improving Mood and Sleep Quality: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12325-025-03327-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 65
Autoren: Manasvi Mahadevan, Kumarpillai Gopukumar, Ruchi Gupta, Abhijeet Morde, Paras Patni, Sahitya Sarvamangala Srinivas, Arun Bhuvanendran, Abhijith Phanindra
Journal: Advances in Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-28
DOI: 10.1007/s12325-025-03327-z
ISSN: 0741-238X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s12325-025-03327-z-2025-09-28-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Chronic treatment with fluoxetine regulates mitochondrial features and plasticity-associated transcriptomic pathways in parvalbumin-positive interneurons of prefrontal cortex</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-025-02219-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 63
Autoren: Elias Jetsonen, Giuliano Didio, Ilida Suleymanova, Indrek Teino, Eero Castrén, Juzoh Umemori
Journal: Neuropsychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-08
Abstract: Abstract
          Chronic treatment with fluoxetine, a widely prescribed selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI), is known to promote neural plasticity. The role of fluoxetine in plasticity has been particularly tied to parvalbumin-positive interneurons, a key population of GABAergic neurons that regulate inhibitory tone and network stability. While our previous studies have highlighted fluoxetine-induced plasticity in the visual cortex and hippocampus, its cell-type-specific effects in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) remain unclear. This study aims to investigate the effects of chronic fluoxetine treatment on PV-positive (PV+) cells, identified using PV-IRES-Cre-driven reporter expression in the PFC. Using Translating Ribosome Affinity Purification (TRAP), we found that fluoxetine treatment altered the expression of 50 distinct biological pathways. Downregulated pathways are involved in mitochondrial ATP production, including components of the electron transport chain, and ribosomes. Upregulated pathways were associated with phosphatase activity, ion channel function, and cytoskeletal remodeling —molecules broadly implicated in synaptic signaling and plasticity-related processes. In FACS-sorted cells, mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) expression was significantly increased in PV+ cells of the PFC, while intracellular ATP levels remained unchanged. Immunohistochemical analyses demonstrated reduced PV expression and weakened perineuronal nets in specific PFC subregions, suggesting a plasticity-permissive state in PV+ cells. TOMM22 signal intensity in PV+ cells showed a slight but significant increase in the prelimbic region, suggesting potential compensatory mitochondrial biogenesis despite transcriptomic downregulation of mitochondrial genes. Our findings reveal that chronic fluoxetine induces coordinated transcriptional, structural alterations in PV+ cells of the PFC, including shifts in mitochondrial-related gene expression and plasticity-associated pathways. These changes may contribute to region-specific shifts in cortical inhibition and plasticity, complementing previous reports of fluoxetine-mediated behavioral modulation.
DOI: 10.1038/s41386-025-02219-8
ISSN: 0893-133X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41386-025-02219-8-2025-09-28-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Non-invasive pharmacological advances in early retinopathy treatment: bioactive herbal compounds, polymer delivery systems, and computational bioprospecting of functional targets</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s43440-025-00778-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 63
Autoren: Christopher Busayo Olowosoke, Thilini Thrimawithana, Tien Huynh
Journal: Pharmacological Reports
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-28
Abstract: Abstract
          Anti-vascular endothelial growth factor (anti-VEGF), laser, and vitrectomy therapy are commonly used for the management of vision-threatening posterior eye disease (PED), but non-invasive alternatives have garnered increasing popularity as proactive preventative strategies for early retinopathy, such as targeted plant-based diets or herbal supplements. However, only some plants contain bioactive compounds that specifically target retinal degeneration and demonstrate potent pharmacological benefits that are cost-effective, safe, and accessible for at-risk individuals. This review pinpoints plant bioactive compounds, specifically polyphenols and carotenoids, that target retinopathy, with a focus on apoptotic, angiogenesis, inflammation, and oxidative pathways leading to visible, functional, and vascular macula improvements. Innovations accelerating therapeutic applications of these botanicals for ocular delivery were then explored. Finally, advancements in disease assessments and the computational methods for early retinopathy biomarker diagnosis and treatment, particularly designed to bio-prospect plant-based therapies, were also reviewed to guide future developments and address translational limitations.
DOI: 10.1007/s43440-025-00778-7
ISSN: 1734-1140
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-28</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s43440-025-00778-7-2025-09-28-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>