<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:13:57 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:13:57 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Challenges in Dietary Therapy in Pediatric Eosinophilic Esophagitis (EoE)—A Narrative Review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu18010082</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 80
Autoren: A. Stochel-Gaudyn, A. Kozioł-Kozakowska, K. Kowalska-Duplaga
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-26
Abstract: Eosinophilic esophagitis (EoE) is a chronic, allergic, immune-mediated inflammation of the esophagus caused by food antigens. The prevalence in pediatric population is approximately 34 to 57 cases per 100,000 children, with a male to female ration 3:1. This number may be underestimated due to diagnostic challenges and variety of clinical presentations in different age groups. Diagnosis of EoE requires histopathological assessment of esophageal biopsies retrieved during gastroscopy, with at least 15 eosinophils per high-power field (HPF) in the esophageal tissue being the cut off value. According to recommendations, treatment options of EoE include dietary interventions (elimination diets), medical treatment (inhibitors of proton pump, steroids, biologics), and in some cases surgical intervention (dilation). Dietary intervention, such as elimination diets, target the triggering factors of the disease and, if supervised by professional nutritionist, have the least systemic side effects. On the other hand, depending on the number of allergens eliminated from the pediatric patients’ diet, the quality of life both of the child and their caretakers may be compromised. Additional challenges such as nutritional risks, feeding disorders, financial burden, and social life impairment also have to be taken into consideration. On top of this, an effectiveness assessment of chosen therapy requires repeated endoscopic examination with several biopsies of the esophagus, further increasing diseases burden in EoE patients. Taking all of this factors into consideration, the main objective of this narrative review was to address challenges that pediatric patients with EoE on dietary treatment face with reference to current research and daily practice.
DOI: 10.3390/nu18010082
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu18010082-2026-01-21-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Weekly Subcutaneous
                    VK2735
                    , a
                    GIP
                    /
                    GLP
                    ‐1 Receptor Dual Agonist, for Weight Management: Phase 2, Randomized, 13‐Week
                    VENTURE
                    Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.70106</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 75
Autoren: Harold E. Bays, Phillip Toth, Naim Alkhouri, John Pullman, Bradley Freilich, Joel Neutel, Summer Ji, Scott Stubbe, Parke Hedges, Brian Lian
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-08
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    Objective
                    This study aimed to determine doses of VK2735, a novel glucagon‐like peptide‐1/glucose‐dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GLP‐1/GIP) receptor dual agonist, that are effective for weight loss over 13 weeks of treatment.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    VENTURE was a phase 2, randomized, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled, dose‐ranging study of weekly subcutaneous VK2735 in adults with obesity or overweight and ≥ 1 weight‐related comorbidity. Participants with diabetes mellitus were ineligible. The primary endpoint was percent change from baseline in body weight at Week 13. Secondary efficacy endpoints were observed and change from baseline weight loss and the proportion of participants losing ≥ 5% and ≥ 10% of baseline weight.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Study was conducted between August 2023 and February 2024. Mean weight reduction with active treatment ranged from 9.2 kg (2.5 mg dose) to 14.6 kg (15 mg dose), corresponding to 9.1% and 14.7% weight reductions, respectively; the placebo group had a 1.8 kg (1.7%) reduction. In the active treatment groups, 93% (130/140) of participants had a ≥ 5% weight reduction, compared with 12% (4/34) of participants with placebo treatment. The common adverse events (AEs) were gastrointestinal, which decreased in reported frequency after dose titration to steady state.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    All subcutaneous doses of VK2735 significantly reduced body weight. The AE profile of VK2735 was primarily gastrointestinal, with decreased reported frequency upon continued use.
                  
                  
                    Trial Registration
                    
                      ClinicalTrials.gov
                      identifier NCT06068946
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/oby.70106
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.70106-2026-01-21-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Ubiquinol in Fertility and Reproduction: A Conditionally Essential Nutrient for Critical Early-Life Stages</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu18010156</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 62
Autoren: Emma J. Derbyshire, Sergej M. Ostojic, Ahmed T. Alahmar
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-02
Abstract: Background/Objectives: Infertility is a multifactorial condition with an etiopathology that remains largely unclear. Although substantial evidence implicates oxidative stress (OS) as a key contributor to both male and female infertility, targeted strategies for OS-mediated reproductive dysfunction are still not well defined and require further investigation. Ubiquinol is the reduced form of Coenzyme Q10 involved in mitochondrial bioenergetics. It can be synthesized by humans endogenously or provided by dietary sources—typically egg yolks, oily fish, organ meats, and in smaller amounts in nuts and seeds and leafy green vegetables. The present article reviews possible mechanisms through which Ubiquinol plays a role in the regulation of fertility and reproduction, discussing why it could be positioned as a conditionally essential nutrient. Several questions and areas for further inquiry are also proposed. Methods: The present position paper narratively summarizes evidence related to Ubiquinol fertility and reproduction, focusing on the literature from PubMed, Science Direct, and Semantic Scholar. Results: Research advancements suggest that when physiological demands rise during certain life stages, e.g., the reproductive years, the amount of Ubiquinol produced internally may not be enough to meet heightened needs, particularly with advanced maternal/paternal age. This places a heavier reliance on obtaining Ubiquinol from the diet, thus presenting itself as a conditionally essential nutrient during certain life stages. Conclusions: Overall, Ubiquinol appears to enhance mitochondrial energy production and antioxidant defense in gametes, a process that appears to aid sperm function, oocyte quality, and early embryo development. Collectively, these data indicate a key physiological role for Ubiquinol in male and female fertility, especially given its age-related decline.
DOI: 10.3390/nu18010156
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu18010156-2026-01-21-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>An evaluation of changes in the sodium content of processed foods in Spain: assessing compliance with the 2025 WHO targets</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00394-025-03861-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 44
Autoren: Manel C. Hadid, Marta Beltrá, Fernando Borrás, Ana B. Ropero
Journal: European Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-19
DOI: 10.1007/s00394-025-03861-0
ISSN: 1436-6207
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00394-025-03861-0-2026-01-21-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Exploring the potential association between dietary factors and autism spectrum disorder: a Mendelian randomization analysis and retrospective study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1716044</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 30
Autoren: Yan-Shuo Guo, Yu Wang, Meng-Na Zhu, Chao Che, Xiao-Xiao Yu, Zhi-Feng Cai, Juan Leng, Kun-Ping Chen, Ai-Hua Cao
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-12
Abstract: 
                    Background
                    Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a neurodevelopmental condition involving complex genetic and environmental interactions. This study aimed to investigate the causal relationships between dietary factors, ketones, food allergy, and the risk of ASD using Mendelian randomization (MR) and clinical research.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    
                      We used two-sample MR to analyze the causal associations between 199 dietary factors, ketones, food allergy, and ASD risk using genome-wide association study (GWAS) data. Validity was assessed using sensitivity analyses. Additionally, a retrospective study (
                      n
                       = 78, age range 2–7 years) evaluated the clinical effects of a gluten-free casein-free (GFCF) diet on ASD symptoms, as measured by the Childhood Autism Rating Scale (CARS) and the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule, Second Edition (ADOS-2).
                    
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      MR analysis identified significant positive causal effects on ASD risk for wholemeal pasta (OR: 16.0, 95% CI 2.86–89.4,
                      p
                       = 0.002) and cheese spread (OR: 9.53, 95% CI 1.64–55.4,
                      p
                       = 0.020). It is crucial to emphasize that these estimates represent the lifetime effect of a genetic predisposition to a higher intake level, not the risk from short-term consumption. The very wide confidence intervals indicate substantial uncertainty in the point estimates. Banana had a protective effect (OR: 0.50, 95% CI: 0.30–0.83,
                      p
                       = 0.008). No causal links were identified for the other factors. Mediation analysis suggested that cheese spread intake increased ASD risk partly by lowering HLA-DR + T cell CD45 levels (10.2% mediation) and increasing anti-Epstein–Barr virus IgG seropositivity (12.9% mediation). Clinically, Although the GFCF diet did not significantly improve ADOS-2 and CARS scores, it showed greater improvement compared to the normal diet group. This diet significantly reduced milk- and wheat-specific IgG levels, indicating its ability to effectively modulate immune responses.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    This study provides genetic evidence of causal relationships between specific dietary factors and ASD risk. Clinical data indicate that adhering to a gluten-free, casein-free diet and avoiding related allergenic foods can effectively modulate food-specific immune responses and may also improve ASD symptoms. These findings contribute to deepening our understanding of ASD etiology and optimizing nutritional treatment protocols.
                  
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1716044
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-21</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1716044-2026-01-21-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>