<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 01:13:22 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 01:13:22 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Expanding the rheumatology lens: should we embrace POTS and post-infectious syndromes?</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 59
Autoren: Brittany L Adler
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-07-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0-2025-07-31-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Long‐term lignan intake, whole grain foods, and the risk of gout: results from two prospective cohort studies</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25596</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 24
Autoren: Sharan K. Rai, Yang Hu, Ming Ding, Frank B. Hu, Molin Wang, Jorge E. Chavarro, Natalie McCormick, Hyon K. Choi, Qi Sun
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-07
Abstract: ObjectiveMultiple plant‐based dietary patterns are inversely associated with gout, although the individual constituents driving this association remain unclear. Dietary lignans, a major group of phytoestrogens abundant in plant foods, are metabolized by the gut microflora and may modulate gout risk. We examined the associations between dietary lignan intake, certain whole grain foods rich in lignans, and incident gout.MethodsWe analyzed data from 122,680 individuals in the Health Professionals Follow‐up Study and Nurses’ Health Study. We administered a food frequency questionnaire every 2‐4 years. We used Cox models to evaluate associations between dietary lignans, whole grain foods, and confirmed gout.ResultsHigher intakes of matairesinol (hazard ratio [HR] and 95% confidence interval [CI] comparing extreme quintiles: 0.78 [0.69, 0.90]; P trend=0.002) and secoisolariciresinol (0.78 [0.68, 0.89]; P trend=0.002) were both associated with lower gout risk, while pinoresinol and lariciresinol were not associated with gout. We found inverse associations of whole grain cold breakfast cereals (HR for those consuming ≥1 serving/day 0.62 [0.53, 0.73]), cooked oatmeal/oat bran (HR for those consuming ≥2 servings/week 0.78 [0.70, 0.86]), and bran added to food (HR for those consuming ≥2 servings/week 0.84 [0.74, 0.95]), but not dark breads or other cooked breakfast cereals, with gout.ConclusionHigher intakes of matairesinol and secoisolariciresinol, as well as whole grain cold breakfast cereals, oatmeal, and added bran, were each significantly associated with lower gout risk. These findings support adherence to healthful plant‐based diets for gout and suggest a potential role of the gut microbiome in gout pathogenesis.
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25596
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-07-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25596-2025-07-31-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Real‐World Cost‐Effectiveness of a Standardized Education and Exercise Therapy Program for Hip and Knee Osteoarthritis Compared to Usual Care</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25555</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 19
Autoren: Darren R. Mazzei, Jackie L. Whittaker, Peter Faris, Tracy Wasylak, Deborah A. Marshall
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-12
Abstract: ObjectiveWe estimated the real‐world cost‐effectiveness of a standardized education and exercise therapy program (GLA:D) compared to usual care (UC) for people managing hip and/or knee osteoarthritis (HKOA).MethodsWe used a prospective matched cohort design to recruit people (aged &amp;gt;45 years) diagnosed with HKOA who used GLA:D or UC (not on a surgical waitlist) throughout Alberta, Canada. Demographics, pain, function, quality of life, and an HKOA‐related cost questionnaire were administered over 12 months. The primary Ministry of Health (MOH) perspective used administrative data to estimate all public health care costs. The secondary health care perspective included MOH, private insurance, and out‐of‐pocket costs. We calculated our cost‐effectiveness measure, incremental net monetary benefit (INMB) in Canadian dollars, over 12 months with a $30,000/quality‐adjusted life years (QALY) willingness to pay threshold and adjusted for the differences between cohorts. A Markov model was used to extend INMB over a lifetime time horizon (3% discounting). Model uncertainty was explored by probabilistic sensitivity analyses.ResultsA total of 254 participants (GLA:D n = 127, UC n = 127; 72% female), with a mean age of 64.3 years (95% confidence interval [CI]: 63.1–65.5), diagnosed with knee osteoarthritis (63%), hip osteoarthritis (24%), or both (13%) were observed for a mean of 5.5 years (95% CI: 4.8–6.3). The adjusted INMB of GLA:D compared to UC was $6,065 (95% CI: $3,648–$8,482) and $499 (95% CI: −$2,913 to $3,912) from an MOH and health care perspective over 12 months and $6,574 and $1,775 over a lifetime with 54% and 51% probability of being cost‐effective using a threshold of willingness to pay of $30,000 per QALY.ConclusionsGLA:D had a positive INMB compared to UC from the MOH perspective over 12 months. The INMB remained positive but was less certain over a lifetime or when out‐of‐pocket and private insurance costs were considered.
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25555
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-07-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25555-2025-07-31-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The therapeutic potential for JAK inhibitors for immune-related adverse events from checkpoint inhibitors: a review of the literature</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/rheumatology/keaf356</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 19
Autoren: Deepak Nagra, Kaiyang Song, Joy Odia, Chris Wincup, Arti Mahto, Chamith Rosa, Ganesh Kasavkar, Maryam A Adas, Zijing Yang, Mark D Russell, Katie Bechman, Tim Blake, Siwalik Banerjee, Nicola Gullick, James B Galloway
Journal: Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-06-30
Abstract: Abstract
               
                  Objectives
                  The role of JAK inhibitors in immune-mediated adverse events was not included in the EULAR 2021 guidance on the management of rheumatic immune-related adverse events (irAE) from checkpoint inhibitors or the society of immunotherapy of cancer guidelines on this topic. We aim to describe the role of JAK inhibitors for the management of immune-mediated adverse events with a review of case reports.
               
               
                  Methods
                  Pubmed, EMBASE and MEDLINE searches were performed from inception until 25 May 2025 for case reports/series of the use of JAK inhibitors to treat checkpoint inhibitor-induced immune adverse events. Five EMA-licensed JAK inhibitors (tofacitinib, baritinib, upadacitinib, filgotinib and ruxolitinib) were included in addition to peficitinib. The 11 FDA-approved checkpoint inhibitors were included.
               
               
                  Results
                  Published case reports, case series and cohort data included 104 patients. Most patients received tofacitinib (82%). Pembrolizumab monotherapy represented the most common immune checkpoint inhibitor. The commonest cancers were lung (20%), followed by gastric (17%) and metastatic melanoma (16%). The indication for JAK inhibitor therapy for irAEs was predominantly myocarditis (70%), followed by myositis (33%) and hepatitis (24%). Tumour progression was observed in 38% of patients, with 14% remaining in remission. Across all patients, 4% died due to progression of their cancer.
               
               
                  Conclusion
                  JAK inhibitors are emerging as a promising option for the treatment of immune checkpoint inhibitor-related toxicities. The currently published evidence, primarily from case reports and case series, suggests they have efficacy, particularly in patients who have failed to respond to other cytokine inhibition strategies.
               
DOI: 10.1093/rheumatology/keaf356
ISSN: 1462-0324
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-07-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/rheumatology/keaf356-2025-07-31-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Gastrointestinal manifestations of systemic sclerosis: current approaches and emerging therapies</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1097/bor.0000000000001110</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 17
Autoren: Luis G. Alcala-Gonzalez, Monique Hinchcliff, Zsuzsanna H. McMahan
Journal: Current Opinion in Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-15
Abstract: 
            Purpose of review
            This review highlights recent advances in the understanding and management of gastrointestinal manifestations in systemic sclerosis (SSc). It is intended for clinicians and researchers aiming to improve diagnostic accuracy and therapeutic strategies in managing SSc-related gastrointestinal disease.
          
          
            Recent findings
            Gastrointestinal involvement in SSc is highly variable in terms of clinical presentation, symptom severity, progression, timing of onset, and response to treatment. Emerging research highlights early immune-mediated damage to neural and muscular gastrointestinal tissues, microbiome alterations, and vascular dysfunction – particularly in patients with late-onset gastrointestinal disease – as key factors guiding the development of personalized, precision-based approaches for well defined patient subgroups. Recent studies underscore the value of early, objective assessment of gastrointestinal motility using tools like whole-gut transit scintigraphy and abdominal vascular ultrasound. New treatment strategies are also being explored for severe manifestations, including investigating mechanisms behind acid-suppressive therapy-resistant gastroesophageal reflux disease and implementing adjunctive therapies for gastrointestinal dysmotility.
          
          
            Summary
            Gastrointestinal involvement in SSc poses a complex clinical challenge, particularly in patients with severe dysmotility and symptoms refractory to standard management strategies. This review offers timely, evidence-based insights to support clinicians in delivering more personalized and effective patient care and highlights critical gaps to address in future research.
          
DOI: 10.1097/bor.0000000000001110
ISSN: 1040-8711
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-07-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1097/bor.0000000000001110-2025-07-31-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>