<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 01:04:11 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 01:04:11 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Laboratory cultivated Cordyceps militaris modulates cockroach allergen-induced inflammation in keratinocytes and macrophages dual cell platforms</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Mey-Fann Lee, Jane-Yii Wu, Chi-Sheng Wu, Ching-Chun Lin, Yu-Wen Chu
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-15
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05132-1-2025-10-22-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and safety of Shugan Jieyu capsules in combination with zolpidem for insomnia disorder with depressive symptoms: a double-blind randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Qianqian Xin, Dhirendra Paudel, Jiehan Zhang, Huafeng Wei, Yihong Cheng, Yan Xu, Ruichen Fang, Jinnong Jiang, Yuling Wang, Bin Zhang
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05142-z-2025-10-22-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Inhibitory effect of [6]-shogaol against 3CLpro activity and SARS-CoV-2 infection</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05094-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 21
Autoren: Takashi Tanikawa, Tsuyoshi Hayashi, Yuka Kiba, Hitoshi Kamauchi, Yuichi Someya, Masashi Kitamura
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05094-4
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05094-4-2025-10-22-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Changji’an formula alleviates visceral hypersensitivity of a post-inflammatory IBS-D mouse model via NGF/TrkA signaling pathway</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05095-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Wei Ke, Siyu Huang, He Zhu, Qinglong Tan, Huaiguo Li, Dongwen Liu, Fanghao Zheng, Shuncong Zhang, Kaijun Lei, Hongmei Tang
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Changji’an Formula (CJAF) is an effective Chinese herbal prescription to treat irritable bowel syndrome with predominant diarrhea (IBS-D), which is derived from two famous classical prescription: Sijunzi decoction and Tong-Xie-Yao-Fang. However, the molecular mechanism has not been well defined. This study aims to illustrate the molecular mechanism of CJAF in the treatment of IBS-D.
          
          
            Methods
            Chemical components of CJAF were determined by ultrahigh performance liquid chromatography-quadrupole/orbitrap high resolution mass spectrometry (UPLC-Q-Orbitrap HRMS) and further verified by reference standards. IBS-D model was induced in C57BL/6J mice by a single edema with colonic infusion of 0.1 mL trinitrobenzene sulfonic acid (TNBS, 50 mg/mL) combined with 7 days of restraint stress, 2 h/d. The treatment group was given rifaximin (100 mg/kg) and high, moderate and low doses of CJAF by gavage for 7 days, respectively (n = 7). After administration, the main symptoms of IBS-D were tested, and behavioral tests were conducted using sucrose preference test and open field test. The colonic tissues of mice were obtained. Gene and protein expression of mast cell tryptase, nerve growth factor (NGF), tyrosine kinase receptor A (TrkA), phosphorylated TrkA, growth associated protein 43(GAP43) and neuro-specific enolase (NSE) were determined by RT-PCR, western blot and immunohistochemistry.
          
          
            Results
            36 compounds were identified by UPLC-Q-Orbitrap HRMS, and the determined components can be categorized into 7 chemical types, including 16 flavonoids, 7 triterpenoids, 4 alkaloids, 3 sesquiterpenoids, 2 monoterpene glycosides, 2 organic acids, 1 phenylpropanoids and 1 tannin. Animal experiment showed that the abdominal pain and diarrhea symptoms of IBS-D mice were alleviated by CJAF. The sucrose preference, total translocation distance and average velocity of movement in the open field test was upregulated. The mRNA and protein expression of mast cell marker tryptase, as well as NGF, phosphorylated TrkA, GAP43 and NSE in IBS-D mice colonic tissues were down-regulated by CJAF.
          
          
            Conclusions
            CJAF could effectively alleviate abdominal pain and diarrhea symptoms of IBS-D by inhibiting the activation of colonic mast cells and the resultant activation of NGF/TrkA signal pathway. Therefore, CJAF affords a potential candidate for the treatment of IBS-D.
          
          
            Graphical Abstract
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05095-3
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05095-3-2025-10-22-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cerebellar transcranial direct current stimulation combined with virtual reality training for the balance of older adults: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05114-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Mengjie Zhang, Ting He, Yidi Xu, Chenrui Ma, Xindi Guo, Yuning Shen, Wenxin Niu
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-10
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05114-3
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05114-3-2025-10-22-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>