<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 01:04:00 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 01:04:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Cognitive functional therapy with or without movement sensor biofeedback versus usual care for chronic, disabling low back pain (RESTORE): 3-year follow-up of a randomised, controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00135-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 290
Autoren: Mark Hancock, Anne Smith, Peter O'Sullivan, Robert Schütze, J P Caneiro, Robert Laird, Kieran O'Sullivan, Jan Hartvigsen, Amity Campbell, Deborah Wareham, Ruth Chang, Peter Kent
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00135-3
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00135-3-2025-08-20-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Expanding the rheumatology lens: should we embrace POTS and post-infectious syndromes?</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 64
Autoren: Brittany L Adler
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0-2025-08-20-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Global recruitment patterns and placebo responses in clinical trials of rheumatoid arthritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.010</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 50
Autoren: Andreas Kerschbaumer, Marlene Steiner, Pascale Pruckner, Brigitte Wildner, Magdalena Maad, Josef S. Smolen, Daniel Aletaha
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.010
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.010-2025-08-20-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>American College of Rheumatology Guidance Statement for Diagnosis and Management of VEXAS Developed by the International VEXAS Working Group Expert Panel</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43287</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 37
Autoren: Arsene M. Mekinian, Sophie Georgin‐Lavaille, Marcela A. Ferrada, Sinisa Savic, Matthew J. Koster, Olivier Kosmider, Thibault Comont, Mael Heilblig, Juan I. Arostegui, Annmarie Bosco, Rim Bourguiba, Katherine R. Calvo, Catherine Cargo, Chiara Cattaneo, François Chasset, Henrique Coelho, Corrado Campochiaro, Francesca Crisafulli, Stephanie Ducharme‐Benard, Raquel Faria, Franco Franceschini, Micol Frassi, Emma M. Groarke, Carmelo Gurnari, Yervand Hakobyan, Yvan Jamilloux, Ciprian Jurcut, Yohei Kirino, Austin Kulasekararaj, Hiroyoshi Kunimoto, Lauren M. Madigan, Heřman F. Mann, Chiara Marvisi, Marcin Milchert, Sara Morais, Katja Sockel, Francesco Muratore, Hideaki Nakajima, Mrinal M. Patnaik, Luísa Regadas, Marie Robin, Abraham Rutgers, Carlo Salvarani, Anthony M. Sammel, Joerg Seebach, Pierre Sujobert, Alessandro Tomelleri, Geoffrey Urbanski, Frédéric Vandergheynst, Romana Vieira, David S. Viswanatha, Ewa Więsik‐Szewczyk, Elisa Diral, Benjamin Terrier, Bhavisha A. Patel, Pierre Fenaux, Peter C. Grayson, David B. Beck, the International VEXAS working group, and with endorsement of EuroBloodNet, the European Reference Network in Rare Hematological Diseases
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-11
Abstract: ObjectiveVacuoles E1 enzyme X‐linked autoinflammatory somatic syndrome (VEXAS) is a recently identified rare genetic disorder associated with somatic mutations in the UBA1 gene. VEXAS presents with a combination of inflammatory and hematologic manifestations, leading to increased morbidity and mortality.MethodsGiven the variability in disease presentation and the limited number of studies to date, no clinical documents currently exist to provide guidance to health care providers about the management of VEXAS. To address this gap, we formed an international multidisciplinary panel of VEXAS experts.ResultsThrough formalized meetings and a voting process, the group developed consensus clinical guidance considerations for the management of VEXAS. These considerations offer practical advice on several key topics: (1) clinical features of VEXAS, (2) UBA1 screening methods, (3) the diagnosis of myelodysplastic syndromes (MDSs) in patients with VEXAS, and (4) prognosis and management. The aim is to provide expert guidance on which patients to test, how to test for VEXAS, how to approach MDS in the context of VEXAS, and considerations for management.ConclusionThis work marks the first formal international consensus guidance for VEXAS and is intended to be used as a resource for clinicians seeking to understand the disease and its management.
DOI: 10.1002/art.43287
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43287-2025-08-20-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Treating lupus nephritis patients to lupus low disease activity reduces renal relapse and preserves long‐term kidney function</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25611</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 37
Autoren: Chak Kwan Cheung, Desmond YH Yap, KL Lee, Philip H Li, Iris YK Tang, Chak Sing Lau, Shirley CW Chan
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-20
Abstract: ObjectiveLupus low disease activity state (LLDAS) is a validated treatment target in systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) but limited studies have explored the role of LLDAS in lupus nephritis (LN). This study aims to investigate the frequency and predictors of LLDAS attainment, and its benefit on LN relapse and renal function preservation in patients with LN.MethodsPatients with LN during 2010‐2020 in Queen Mary Hospital and Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital were included in the discovery cohort and validation cohort, respectively. Complete renal response (CRR), partial renal response (PRR), LLDAS, and DORIS remission were assessed at 12 months. Regression analysis was performed to identify risk factors of LN relapse. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves were used to evaluate target attainment and long‐term kidney function.ResultsA total of 245 LN patients (discovery cohort N=143, validation cohort N=102) were included. At 12 months, 57/143 (40%), 14/143 (10%), 70/143 (49%), 15/143 (10%) patients achieved CRR, PRR, LLDAS, and DORIS remission respectively. Attainment of both CRR/ PRR and LLDAS at 12 months was associated with best relapse‐free survival (p&amp;lt;0.001). Multivariate analysis showed independent association of CRR/PRR and LLDAS with LN relapse risk reduction (CRR/PRR: HR=0.31, p = 0.007; LLDAS: HR=0.38, p = 0.029). LLDAS attainment predicts renal function preservation with satisfactory performance in both discovery and validation cohorts (AUC‐ROC=0.71).ConclusionLLDAS is an attainable target in LN comparable to CRR/PRR. Attainment of both targets is associated with additional benefit on relapse risk reduction. Early LLDAS attainment is associated with renal function preservation.image
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25611
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25611-2025-08-20-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>