<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 14:17:00 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 14:17:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Development and validation of blood-based diagnostic biomarkers for Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome (ME/CFS) using EpiSwitch® 3-dimensional genomic regulatory immuno-genetic profiling</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12967-025-07203-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 1703
Autoren: Ewan Hunter, Heba Alshaker, Oliver Bundock, Cicely Weston, Shekinah Bautista, Abel Gebregzabhar, Anya Virdi, Joseph Croxford, Ann Dring, Ryan Powell, Dominik Vugrinec, Caroline Kingdon, Carol Wilson, Sarah Dowrick, Jayne Green, Alexandre Akoulitchev, Dmitri Pchejetski
Journal: Journal of Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-08
DOI: 10.1186/s12967-025-07203-w
ISSN: 1479-5876
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12967-025-07203-w-2025-11-11-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Poor sleep health is associated with older brain age: the role of systemic inflammation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.105941</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 1006
Autoren: Yuyang Miao, Jiao Wang, Xuerui Li, Jie Guo, Maria M. Ekblom, Shireen Sindi, Qiang Zhang, Abigail Dove
Journal: eBioMedicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.105941
ISSN: 2352-3964
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.105941-2025-11-11-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Physical activity as a modifiable risk factor in preclinical Alzheimer’s disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 434
Autoren: Wai-Ying Wendy Yau, Dylan R. Kirn, Jennifer S. Rabin, Michael J. Properzi, Aaron P. Schultz, Zahra Shirzadi, Kailee Palmgren, Paola Matos, Courtney Maa, Jeremy J. Pruzin, Stephanie A. Schultz, Rachel F. Buckley, Dorene M. Rentz, Keith A. Johnson, Reisa A. Sperling, Jasmeer P. Chhatwal
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-03
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6-2025-11-11-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Myelin injury precedes axonal injury and symptomatic onset in multiple sclerosis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-04014-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 325
Autoren: Ahmed Abdelhak, Gabriel Cerono, Fahime Sheikhzadeh, Adil Harroud, Kiarra Ning, Colin R. Zamecnik, Gavin M. Sowa, John Boscardin, Christian Cordano, Asritha Tubati, Camille Fouassier, Eric D. Chow, Refujia Gomez, Adam Santaniello, Kelsey C. Zorn, Jill A. Hollenbach, Jorge R. Oksenberg, Bruce A. C. Cree, Stephen L. Hauser, Jonah R. Chan, Sergio E. Baranzini, Mitchell T. Wallin, Michael R. Wilson, Ari J. Green
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-20
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-04014-w
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-04014-w-2025-11-11-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Macrovascular tumor infiltration and circulating tumor cell cluster dynamics in patients with cancer approaching the end of life</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03966-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 313
Autoren: Kelley Newcomer, Alessandro Bifolco, Sarah Reeves, Giada Pontecorvi, Simran Asawa, Magdalena K. Sznurkowska, Manuel Nüesch, Lauren L. Ozimski, Louisa Bolm, Malte Maria Sieren, Lukas Müller, Zhikai Chi, William Gasper, Megan B. Wachsmann, William Moore, Xue Zheng, Angelique Fokkema, Alexander Ring, Bich Doan Nguyen-Sträuli, Selina Budinjas, Meike ten Winkel, Benedikt Färber, Abbas Zaki, Nafeesah Fatimah, Elena Crecca, John D. Karalis, Raghav Chandra, Hillary Prince, Kristina L. Goff, Sung-hee Choi, Carol Abousaab, Song Zhang, Suzanne Cole, Kathryn Naumann, Tobias Keck, Patricio M. Polanco, Ana Gvozdenovic, Ilona Krol, Francesc Castro-Giner, Carlos Arteaga, Herbert J. Zeh, Roman Kloeckner, Dario Ghersi, Nicola Aceto, Matteo Ligorio
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-16
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03966-3
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03966-3-2025-11-11-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>