<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 01:12:50 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 01:12:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Evenamide reverses schizophrenia-related dysfunction in a neurodevelopmental animal model</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-025-02188-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 218
Autoren: Daniela L. Uliana, Rachel A. Walsh, Debora Fabris, Anthony A. Grace
Journal: Neuropsychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-05
DOI: 10.1038/s41386-025-02188-y
ISSN: 0893-133X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41386-025-02188-y-2025-09-01-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cyclodextrin-mediated Enhancement of Haloperidol Solubility: Physicochemical Studies and In Vivo Investigation Using Planaria Worms</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11095-025-03909-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 143
Autoren: Yuehuai Xiong, Kenneth Shankland, Vitaliy V. Khutoryanskiy
Journal: Pharmaceutical Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-15
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Purpose
            This study aims to evaluate the ability of various cyclodextrins (CDs) to enhance the aqueous solubility of haloperidol (HAL), through the formation of inclusion complexes. It also investigates the pharmacological activity of CD/HAL complexes using a planaria model.
          
          
            Methods
            Inclusion complexes were prepared using α-CD, β-CD, methyl-β-CD, hydroxypropyl-β-CD and γ-CD. The solubility of HAL in the presence of CDs was assessed, and the stoichiometry of the complexes was determined using Job’s method. Physicochemical interactions between HAL and CDs were characterized by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), differential scanning calorimetry (DSC), and powder X-ray diffraction (PXRD). The in vivo pharmacological activity was tested in planaria worms following exposure to HAL in the presence or absence of CDs.
          
          
            Results
            HAL’s aqueous solubility was significantly enhanced in the presence of α-CD, methyl-β-CD, and hydroxypropyl-β-CD, while γ-CD showed no effect. Only modest solubility improvements were observed with increasing β-CD concentrations up to 8 mg/mL. Stoichiometric analysis confirmed a 1:1 ratio of HAL to CD in the inclusion complexes. In vivo studies demonstrated that HAL reduced planaria mobility, mimicking cataleptic effects seen in mammals, whereas the presence of CDs reduced this pharmacological effect.
          
          
            Conclusion
            Cyclodextrins, particularly α-CD, methyl-β-CD, and hydroxypropyl-β-CD, effectively enhance the solubility of haloperidol by forming 1:1 inclusion complexes. The reduction in haloperidol-induced behavioral changes in planaria by CDs suggests a potential impact on drug bioavailability and supports the use of planaria as a simple in vivo model for screening neuroactive compounds and formulations.
          
DOI: 10.1007/s11095-025-03909-0
ISSN: 0724-8741
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s11095-025-03909-0-2025-09-01-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Methylphenidate (Ritalin) does not improve exam performance in an experimental setting</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00213-025-06864-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 106
Autoren: Anke Sambeth, Monika Toth, Arjan Blokland
Journal: Psychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-05
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Rationale
            Surveys indicate that about 10–20% of students use medicinal drugs to improve their exam performance. Whether these drugs really improve exam performance has not been examined in an experimental setting yet. This study tested the effects of methylphenidate (MPH; 20 mg) on exam performance either by giving the drug before studying for an exam (day 1, acquiring new information) or before the exam was taken (day 2, retrieving the information).
          
          
            Method
            For this study, a double-blind placebo controlled between-subjects design was applied. The participants were randomly assigned to three groups that were given treatment on the two days: Placebo-Placebo (n = 25), MPH (n = 24), Placebo-MPH (n = 26). The exam contained multiple-choice questions (factual knowledge and inference questions) and open questions (inference).
          
          
            Results
            The data showed that MPH did not improve the exam performance on the three types of questions. In addition, the average grade did not differ between the three groups and the number of participants failing or passing the exam did not differ.
          
          
            Conclusion
            This is a first experimental study showing that MPH does not improve exam performance and should discourage students to take MPH during exam periods.
          
DOI: 10.1007/s00213-025-06864-1
ISSN: 0033-3158
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00213-025-06864-1-2025-09-01-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>‘Exploiting PP2A dependent and independent effects of forskolin for therapeutic targeting of KMT2A (MLL)‐rearranged acute leukaemia’</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/bph.70158</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 73
Autoren: Yoana Arroyo‐Berdugo, Antonella Di Mambro, Volker Behrends, Michelle A. Sahai, Luca Cozzuto, Immacolata Zollo, Julia Ponomarenko, Owen Williams, John Gribben, Yolanda Calle, Bela Patel, Maria Teresa Esposito
Journal: British Journal of Pharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-20
Abstract: Background and PurposeActivation of Protein Phosphatase 2A (PP2A), via genetic and pharmacologic modulation of SET, has recently being identified as a promising strategy to therapeutically target acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) carrying KMT2A (MLL) chromosomal translocations (KMT2A‐r AML).Experimental ApproachIn this study, we investigated the expression of PP2A subunits and the therapeutic potential of forskolin, a cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) elevating natural compound that has been reported as a PP2A activator.Key ResultsOur data show that PPP2CA encoding protein phosphatase 2 catalytic subunit α is abundantly expressed in KMT2A‐r AML cells. Treatment with forskolin arrests proliferation; induces cell death; represses the expression of MYC, HOXA9 and HOXA10; stimulates PP2A activity; and attenuates the activity of ERK1/2 in KMT2A‐r AML cells. Forskolin increases sensitivity to standard‐of‐care daunorubicin in KMT2A‐AML cell lines and PDX. Silencing PPP2CA partially rescues the cytotoxic effect of forskolin, stimulates ERK1/2, inhibits GSK3β, and abolishes the forskolin‐mediated repression of c‐MYC and HOXA10, but it did not affect the potentiation of response to daunorubicin. This effect was also not dependent on increase of cAMP, but it was because of increase in the intracellular accumulation of daunorubicin, through inhibition of drug efflux pump P‐glycoprotein 1 (multidrug resistance protein).Conclusions and ImplicationsIn conclusion, our findings highlight a novel mechanism of action for forskolin and support a potential role of this natural compound in combination with current conventional agent daunorubicin in the treatment of KMT2A‐r AML.
DOI: 10.1111/bph.70158
ISSN: 0007-1188
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/bph.70158-2025-09-01-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>FDA grants first US approval for decades-old eye drug</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41573-025-00138-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 70
Autoren: Asher Mullard
Journal: Nature Reviews Drug Discovery
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-07
DOI: 10.1038/d41573-025-00138-3
ISSN: 1474-1776
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/d41573-025-00138-3-2025-09-01-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>