<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 01:13:12 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 01:13:12 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Cognitive functional therapy with or without movement sensor biofeedback versus usual care for chronic, disabling low back pain (RESTORE): 3-year follow-up of a randomised, controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00135-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 283
Autoren: Mark Hancock, Anne Smith, Peter O'Sullivan, Robert Schütze, J P Caneiro, Robert Laird, Kieran O'Sullivan, Jan Hartvigsen, Amity Campbell, Deborah Wareham, Ruth Chang, Peter Kent
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00135-3
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00135-3-2025-08-18-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Expanding the rheumatology lens: should we embrace POTS and post-infectious syndromes?</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 64
Autoren: Brittany L Adler
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0-2025-08-18-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Global recruitment patterns and placebo responses in clinical trials of rheumatoid arthritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.010</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 50
Autoren: Andreas Kerschbaumer, Marlene Steiner, Pascale Pruckner, Brigitte Wildner, Magdalena Maad, Josef S. Smolen, Daniel Aletaha
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.010
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.07.010-2025-08-18-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Treating lupus nephritis patients to lupus low disease activity reduces renal relapse and preserves long‐term kidney function</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25611</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 32
Autoren: Chak Kwan Cheung, Desmond YH Yap, KL Lee, Philip H Li, Iris YK Tang, Chak Sing Lau, Shirley CW Chan
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-20
Abstract: ObjectiveLupus low disease activity state (LLDAS) is a validated treatment target in systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) but limited studies have explored the role of LLDAS in lupus nephritis (LN). This study aims to investigate the frequency and predictors of LLDAS attainment, and its benefit on LN relapse and renal function preservation in patients with LN.MethodsPatients with LN during 2010‐2020 in Queen Mary Hospital and Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital were included in the discovery cohort and validation cohort, respectively. Complete renal response (CRR), partial renal response (PRR), LLDAS, and DORIS remission were assessed at 12 months. Regression analysis was performed to identify risk factors of LN relapse. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves were used to evaluate target attainment and long‐term kidney function.ResultsA total of 245 LN patients (discovery cohort N=143, validation cohort N=102) were included. At 12 months, 57/143 (40%), 14/143 (10%), 70/143 (49%), 15/143 (10%) patients achieved CRR, PRR, LLDAS, and DORIS remission respectively. Attainment of both CRR/ PRR and LLDAS at 12 months was associated with best relapse‐free survival (p&amp;lt;0.001). Multivariate analysis showed independent association of CRR/PRR and LLDAS with LN relapse risk reduction (CRR/PRR: HR=0.31, p = 0.007; LLDAS: HR=0.38, p = 0.029). LLDAS attainment predicts renal function preservation with satisfactory performance in both discovery and validation cohorts (AUC‐ROC=0.71).ConclusionLLDAS is an attainable target in LN comparable to CRR/PRR. Attainment of both targets is associated with additional benefit on relapse risk reduction. Early LLDAS attainment is associated with renal function preservation.image
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25611
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25611-2025-08-18-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Associations of specific pesticides and incident rheumatoid arthritis among female spouses in the Agricultural Health Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43318</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 31
Autoren: Christine G. Parks, Darya Leyzarovich, Ghassan B. Hamra, Karen H. Costenbader, Dazhe Chen, Jonathan N. Hofmann, Laura E. Beane Freeman, Dale P. Sandler
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-16
Abstract: ObjectivesGrowing evidence suggests farming and agricultural pesticide use may be associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA), but few studies have examined specific pesticides and RA among farm women, who may personally use pesticides or be indirectly exposed. We investigated pesticide use and RA risk among female spouses of licensed pesticide applicators in the Agricultural Health Study.MethodsParticipants enrolled in 1993‐1997 in North Carolina and Iowa (N=32,126). Incident RA cases were identified in follow‐up questionnaires (1999‐2021) and confirmed by medical records, relevant medication use, or Medicare claims data (1999‐2016), or from Medicare claims if lacking questionnaire data on RA. Non‐cases reported no RA and had no RA Medicare claims. Among those with complete covariate data (N=410 cases and 21,850 non‐cases), we examined associations with pesticide classes and 32 specific pesticides (personal lifetime use reported at enrollment, updated in 1999‐2003). We calculated odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI), adjusting for age, state, education, smoking pack‐years smoking, body mass index, and correlated pesticides (rho&amp;gt;0.35).ResultsIncident RA was associated with use of organochlorine [DDT (1.89;1.30‐2.75), lindane (1.97;1.12‐3.47)] and organophosphate insecticides [coumaphos (2.32;1.29‐4.19), malathion (1.21;0.91‐1.62)], the carbamate insecticide carbofuran (1.87;0.97‐3.63), and permethrin or pyrethroid insecticides use on crops (1.56;0.92‐2.64) or livestock (1.69;1.07‐2.68). RA was not associated with using herbicides, except for metribuzin (1.88;0.94‐3.79). The fungicides captan (1.78;1.13‐2.83) and metalaxyl (2.49;1.41‐4.40) were also associated with RA.DiscussionThese findings indicate that persistent organochlorine insecticides and some pesticides also used in public health or residential settings may increase RA risk in women.
DOI: 10.1002/art.43318
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43318-2025-08-18-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>