<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:59:49 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:59:49 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Rhotic Acquisition Is More Rapid in Biofeedback Than Motor-Based Treatment for Residual Speech Sound Disorder: Primary Outcome of a RandomizeeechResearch Articlesd Controlled Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00909</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 60
Autoren: Tara McAllister, Jonathan L. Preston, Nina R. Benway, Jennifer Hill, Marcela P. Lara, Megan C. Leece, Wendy Liang, Elaine R. Hitchcock
Journal: Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-08
Abstract: 
            Purpose:
            Residual speech sound disorder (RSSD) is a high-prevalence condition that can limit children's academic and social participation, with negative consequences for overall well-being. Previous studies have described visual biofeedback as a promising option for RSSD, but results have been inconclusive due to study design limitations and small sample sizes.
          
          
            Method:
            In a preregistered randomized controlled trial, 108 children aged 9–15 years with RSSD affecting American English /ɹ/ were randomly assigned to receive treatment incorporating visual biofeedback (subdivided into ultrasound and visual-acoustic types) or a comparison condition of motor-based treatment consistent with current best practices in speech therapy. An acoustic measure (the distance between the second and third formants, which is smaller in perceptually accurate /ɹ/) was used to quantify progress in the first three sessions of treatment in participants' assigned condition. The focus on the early stages of treatment was grounded in principles of motor learning: As a type of knowledge of performance feedback, biofeedback is expected to have its greatest impact during initial acquisition of a new speech-motor plan.
          
          
            Results:
            A linear mixed-effects regression model revealed a statistically significant interaction between treatment type and session: While both groups made progress over time, the rate of progress was significantly faster in the biofeedback condition compared to motor-based treatment. No statistically significant difference was observed between the ultrasound and visual-acoustic types of biofeedback.
          
          
            Discussion:
            This large-scale randomized controlled trial supports previous small-scale research in finding that biofeedback can help children with RSSD acquire American English /ɹ/. A companion study will compare participants' generalization learning after the end of all treatment.
          
          
            Supplemental Material:
            
              https://doi.org/10.23641/asha.29971501
            
          
DOI: 10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00909
ISSN: 1092-4388
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1044/2025_jslhr-24-00909-2025-09-18-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scapular kinematics variability in individuals with and without rotator cuff-related shoulder pain: A systematic review with multilevel meta-regression</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 48
Autoren: Rubén Fernández-Matías, Jorge Ballesteros-Frutos, Pablo Gallardo-Zamora, Néstor Requejo-Salinas, Iván Caballero-Pozo, Paula Ludewig, Enrique Lluch-Girbés
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101261-2025-09-18-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of sitting posture and duration on lumbosacral nerve root function: A case-control study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/10538127251371635</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 32
Autoren: Hamad S Al Amer, Shahul Hameed Pakkir Mohamed, Sharon L Olson
Journal: Journal of Back and Musculoskeletal Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-26
Abstract: 
            Purpose
            This study aimed to investigate the effects of different sitting postures and prolonged sitting on lumbosacral nerve root function by measuring the amplitude of the soleus (SOL) Hoffmann reflex (H-reflex).
          
          
            Methods
            This study included 30 healthy individuals who were selected through convenience sampling and divided according to daily sitting duration over the past year into a prolonged sitting group (≥6 h/day) and a control group (≤4 h/day). The SOL H-reflex amplitude was recorded in erect, slumped, slouched, and supine positions. Ischial pressure was evaluated in all sitting postures to assess spinal loading.
          
          
            Results
            
              Slouched sitting significantly lowered ischial pressure (
              p
               
              &amp;lt;
               
              0.0005
              ) and produced higher H-reflex amplitudes (
              p
               
              &amp;lt;
               
              0.0005
              ), which were not significantly different from those in the supine position (
              p
               
              =
               
              0.362
              ). In contrast, (
              p
               
              &amp;lt;
               
              0.0005
              ) erect and slumped (
              p &amp;lt; 0.0005
              ) postures showed increased ischial pressure and significantly reduced H-reflex amplitudes (
              p
               
              &amp;lt;
               
              0.0005
              for both postures). Participants in the prolonged sitting group demonstrated significantly lower SOL H-reflex amplitudes than those in the control group (
              p
               
              =
               
              0.008, ηp²
               
              =
               
              0.23
              ).
            
          
          
            Conclusion
            Various sitting postures and durations exert different effects on the lumbosacral spine and nerve roots. Slouched sitting reduces spinal stress and lower nerve root compression compared to erect and slumped seated positions. Extended sitting duration may partially compress the lumbosacral nerve root, thereby potentially contributing to postural low back pain over time.
          
DOI: 10.1177/10538127251371635
ISSN: 1053-8127
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/10538127251371635-2025-09-18-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association of Long COVID With Vision Difficulties Among Adults in the United States</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/0145482x251365588</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 32
Autoren: Mona Pathak, Sophie Mitra, Chan Shen, Hao Wang, Patricia A. Findley, R. Constance Wiener, Usha Sambamoorthi
Journal: Journal of Visual Impairment &amp;amp; Blindness
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
Abstract: 
            Introduction:
            Emerging research associates long COVID with the ocular system, including vision difficulties. This study determines the association of long COVID with vision difficulties among U.S. adults.
            Methods:
            We used a cross-sectional observational study design of 2022 Census Household Pulse Survey adult data (
            N
             = 51,288). COVID status was defined as follows: “long COVID”: those with new symptoms 3 months or longer after COVID infection; “short-term COVID”: those who had COVID but no long COVID symptoms; and “no COVID”: those who have never had COVID. The vision categories were suggested by the Washington Group Short Set on Functioning: no difficulty, some difficulty, a lot of difficulty, and cannot do at all. Rao-Scott Chi-square tests and multinomial logistic regression (adjusted for COVID status, sex, age, race and ethnicity, marital status, poverty, education, food insecurity, health insurance, region, remote work, COVID vaccine, depression, and anxiety), with replicate weights were used.
            Results:
            The study included 51,288 respondents. There were 31.3% who had some vision difficulty, and 4.2% had a lot of difficulty or were unable to see. The proportion who reported that they had long COVID was 14.4%. A higher percentage of adults with long COVID reported vision difficulties than those without COVID (47.6% vs. 31.9%). Adults with long COVID had greater odds of reporting a lot of difficulty or cannot do at all (AOR = 1.47, 95%CI = 1.19, 1.81) and some difficulty seeing (AOR = 1.47, 95%CI = 1.27, 1.70) compared to adults without COVID. We did not observe a statistically significant association of short-term COVID with vision difficulties compared to adults without COVID.
            Discussion:
            One in seven U.S. adults had long COVID. Adults with long COVID had higher odds of vision difficulties than those without COVID. Further research is needed on long COVID and vision difficulties and subsequent vision care.
            Implications for Practitioners:
            A follow-up study of patients with long COVID needs to include screening for vision difficulties.
          
DOI: 10.1177/0145482x251365588
ISSN: 0145-482X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/0145482x251365588-2025-09-18-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cervical flexion posture during smartphone use was not a risk factor for neck pain, but low sleep quality and insufficient levels of physical activity were. A longitudinal investigation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 28
Autoren: Igor Macedo Tavares Correia, Arthur de Sá Ferreira, Jessica Fernandez Mosqueira Gomes, Felipe José Jandre Reis, Leandro Alberto Calazans Nogueira, Ney Meziat-Filho
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101258-2025-09-18-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>