<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:16:42 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:16:42 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Durability of the benefit of vagus nerve stimulation in markedly treatment-resistant major depression: a RECOVER trial report</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/ijnp/pyaf080</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 198
Autoren: Charles R Conway, Augustus John Rush, Scott T Aaronson, Mark T Bunker, Charles Gordon, Mark S George, Patricio Riva-Posse, Rebecca M Allen, Ziad Nahas, Christopher L Kriedt, John Zajecka, David L Dunner, João Quevedo, Yvette Sheline, Walter Duffy, Brian J Mickey, Mary Stedman, Gustavo Alva, Lucian Manu, Quyen Tran, Charles F Zorumski, Matthew Macaluso, Michael Banov, Cristina Cusin, Jeffrey I Bennett, Hunter Brown, Jeffrey Way, Olivia Shy, Ying-Chieh (Lisa) Lee, Richard Hamish McAllister-Williams, Roger S McIntyre, Harold A Sackeim
Journal: International Journal of Neuropsychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Importance
                    Greater levels of treatment resistance in major depressive disorder (MDD) are associated with lower rates of initial benefit and higher rates of relapse (lower durability).
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    Characterize depressive symptoms, function, and quality of life (QoL) over 24 months of adjunctive vagus nerve stimulation (VNS) in participants with markedly treatment-resistant depression.
                  
                  
                    Design
                    Prospective, open-label, single-arm, long-term extension study (RECOVER) conducted from September 2019 to April 2025.
                  
                  
                    Setting
                    Outpatient.
                  
                  
                    Participants
                    Adults with moderate–severe MDD with ≥ 4 failed antidepressant trials in the current episode, randomized to blinded, adjunctive VNS for 12 months, who subsequently received open-label, adjunctive VNS for 12 additional months (n = 214).
                  
                  
                    Interventions
                    Vagus nerve stimulation and concomitant psychotropic medications and interventional psychiatric modalities (electroconvulsive therapy, transcranial magnetic stimulation, and ketamine/esketamine) were characterized over the 12-month extension.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcomes and Measures
                    The durability of benefit achieved at 12 months was assessed at 18 and 24 months for depressive symptoms (3 scales), daily function, QoL, a tripartite composite of all 3 domains, and the Clinical Global Impression–Improvement (CGI-I) scale (overall improvement). Loss of benefit and relapse were assessed, along with the emergence of meaningful benefit in participants without benefit at 12 months. Substantial benefit (at least 50% symptom reduction from baseline; CGI-I of 1 or 2; tripartite measures with at least 2 of 3 subscales evidencing benefit) and meaningful benefit thresholds for symptoms (at least 30% reduction from baseline), function, QoL, CGI-I, and the tripartite measure were set a priori.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Most participants with substantial benefit maintained their benefit (18-month median = 78.8%; 24-month median = 79.0% across 5 measures), as did participants with at least meaningful benefit at 12 months (18-month median = 83.1%; 24-month median = 81.3% across 7 measures). Furthermore, many participants with no meaningful benefit at 12 months achieved it at 18 (median = 30.6%) and 24 (median = 37.8%) months. The strong maintenance of benefit was not accounted for by changes in psychotropic medications or interventional psychiatric modalities.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions and Relevance
                    Depressive symptom, daily function, and QoL benefits obtained after 12 months of adjunctive VNS were sustained in about 80% of participants continuing VNS. Approximately 30% with no meaningful benefit at 12 months accrued increased benefit over the subsequent year.
                  
                  
                    Highlights
                  
DOI: 10.1093/ijnp/pyaf080
ISSN: 1461-1457
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/ijnp/pyaf080-2026-01-19-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>2025 FDA approvals</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41573-026-00001-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 123
Autoren: Asher Mullard
Journal: Nature Reviews Drug Discovery
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-02
DOI: 10.1038/d41573-026-00001-z
ISSN: 1474-1776
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/d41573-026-00001-z-2026-01-19-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Advances and updates in antibiotic combination therapy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/14787210.2025.2595462</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 93
Autoren: Claudia Bartalucci, Chiara Sepulcri, Federica Portunato, Federica Briano, Chiara Dentone, Matteo Bassetti
Journal: Expert Review of Anti-infective Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-25
DOI: 10.1080/14787210.2025.2595462
ISSN: 1478-7210
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/14787210.2025.2595462-2026-01-19-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Drugs anticipated to be selected for Medicare price negotiation in 2026 for implementation in 2028</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.18553/jmcp.2025.25253</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 92
Autoren: Emma M. Cousin, Kristi Martin, Ryan N. Hansen, John Coster, Sean D. Sullivan
Journal: Journal of Managed Care &amp;amp; Specialty Pharmacy
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.18553/jmcp.2025.25253
ISSN: 2376-0540
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.18553/jmcp.2025.25253-2026-01-19-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>National trends in pharmacist and pharmacy technician suicide: Incidence and associated features</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/ajhp/zxag006</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 87
Autoren: Hirsh Makhija, Judy E Davidson, Arianna Barnes, Sidney Zisook, Amanda Choflet, Nam Nguyen, Kelly C Lee
Journal: American Journal of Health-System Pharmacy
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-08
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Purpose
                    Pharmacists and pharmacy technicians are essential healthcare professionals with limited data on their risk for suicide.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Using the National Violent Death Reporting System, pharmacist, pharmacy technician, and general population suicides (for individuals 25 years of age or older) were identified. Suicide incidence was estimated from 2011 to 2022 due to data limitations, while suicide characteristics (preceding circumstances, method, and toxicology) were analyzed in adjusted Firth logistic regression models from 2005 to 2022.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    A total of 369 pharmacist (87 [24%] female), 243 pharmacy technician (149 [61%] female), and 245,114 general population (52,890 [22%] female) suicides were found for the period from 2011 to 2022. When data were standardized by sex, pharmacists had a higher risk of suicide (incidence rate ratio [IRR], 1.21; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.09-1.34) while pharmacy technicians had a lower risk (IRR, 0.86; 95% CI, 0.74-0.99) than individuals in the general population during the 2011-2022 study period. Male pharmacists had a higher risk of suicide than other males (IRR, 1.25; 95% CI, 1.11-1.41) while female technicians had a higher risk than other females (IRR, 1.22; 95% CI, 1.04-1.44) during the 2011-2022 study period. In terms of the features associated with suicide, compared to the general population, pharmacists had higher odds of preceding job problems, while pharmacy technicians had higher odds of mental health problems. Pharmacists also had higher odds of using poisoning as a method.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Our findings suggest that pharmacists and female pharmacy technicians are at higher risk of suicide than their counterparts from the general population, possibly indicating that increased awareness and prevention are warranted.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/ajhp/zxag006
ISSN: 1079-2082
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/ajhp/zxag006-2026-01-19-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>