<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 01:10:30 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 01:10:30 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Lacto-ovo-vegetarian and vegan diets in children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analysis of nutritional and health outcomes</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2025.2572983</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 343
Autoren: Sofia Lotti, Giona Panizza, Daniela Martini, Wolfgang Marx, Jeannette M. Beasley, Barbara Colombini, Monica Dinu
Journal: Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-11
DOI: 10.1080/10408398.2025.2572983
ISSN: 1040-8398
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/10408398.2025.2572983-2026-01-15-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Challenges in Dietary Therapy in Pediatric Eosinophilic Esophagitis (EoE)—A Narrative Review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu18010082</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 72
Autoren: A. Stochel-Gaudyn, A. Kozioł-Kozakowska, K. Kowalska-Duplaga
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-26
Abstract: Eosinophilic esophagitis (EoE) is a chronic, allergic, immune-mediated inflammation of the esophagus caused by food antigens. The prevalence in pediatric population is approximately 34 to 57 cases per 100,000 children, with a male to female ration 3:1. This number may be underestimated due to diagnostic challenges and variety of clinical presentations in different age groups. Diagnosis of EoE requires histopathological assessment of esophageal biopsies retrieved during gastroscopy, with at least 15 eosinophils per high-power field (HPF) in the esophageal tissue being the cut off value. According to recommendations, treatment options of EoE include dietary interventions (elimination diets), medical treatment (inhibitors of proton pump, steroids, biologics), and in some cases surgical intervention (dilation). Dietary intervention, such as elimination diets, target the triggering factors of the disease and, if supervised by professional nutritionist, have the least systemic side effects. On the other hand, depending on the number of allergens eliminated from the pediatric patients’ diet, the quality of life both of the child and their caretakers may be compromised. Additional challenges such as nutritional risks, feeding disorders, financial burden, and social life impairment also have to be taken into consideration. On top of this, an effectiveness assessment of chosen therapy requires repeated endoscopic examination with several biopsies of the esophagus, further increasing diseases burden in EoE patients. Taking all of this factors into consideration, the main objective of this narrative review was to address challenges that pediatric patients with EoE on dietary treatment face with reference to current research and daily practice.
DOI: 10.3390/nu18010082
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu18010082-2026-01-15-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Lycopene, Race and Periodontitis: Disparities in Older Adults</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jnha.2025.100759</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 69
Autoren: Katherine Kwong, You Lu, ZhuoHuan Li, Susu Luo, Zhaoyu Huang, Zhong Chen, Na Zhao, Tung-Sung Tseng
Journal: The Journal of nutrition, health and aging
Veröffentlicht: 2026-02-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jnha.2025.100759
ISSN: 1279-7707
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jnha.2025.100759-2026-01-15-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Carbohydrate Reduction and a Holistic Model of Care in Diabetes Management: Insights from a Retrospective Multi-Year Audit in New Zealand</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17243953</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 66
Autoren: Caryn Zinn, Jessica L. Campbell, Lily Fraser, Glen Davies, Marcus Hawkins, Olivia Currie, Jared Cannons, David Unwin, Catherine Crofts, Tom Stewart, Grant Schofield
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-17
Abstract: Background/Objectives: The global epidemic of type 2 diabetes (T2D) is a critical public health issue, particularly in New Zealand, where prevalence rates are high, especially among Māori and Pacific people. Recent research indicates that dietary interventions, particularly carbohydrate reduction, can lead to the remission or reversal of T2D. However, little is known about how such approaches perform when implemented in routine New Zealand primary care, particularly within high-risk and underserved populations. This study aimed to evaluate changes in HbA1c, diabetes status, and cardiometabolic outcomes among adults with prediabetes and T2D engaged in such a model of care. Methods: This study reports findings from a retrospective, observational, real-world, multi-site clinical audit (service evaluation) of a holistic model of care implemented in three primary care practices in New Zealand. The model of care is characterised by a three-pronged approach: whole food, carbohydrate reduction; a health-coach, behaviour-change-based delivery approach; and community- or peer-based initiatives. Audit data from 106 patients with prediabetes (PD) and T2D were analysed (median follow-up 19 months; IQR 6–32) to assess changes in glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c) levels, diabetes status, and cardiometabolic outcomes. Results: We observed an overall reduction in HbA1c (median change −3 mmol/mol (IQR: −7 to 3), p = 0.004), with 32% of patients with T2D at baseline achieving reversal and 44% of those with PD attaining normoglycaemia at final follow-up. Weight loss was associated with greater HbA1c reduction (0.56 mmol/mol decrease per kg lost) and additional improvements seen in lowered alanine aminotransferase (ALT). HDL cholesterol showed a small decline (r = 0.31), and triglycerides and blood pressure showed no significant change, indicating that these measures remained broadly stable over the evaluation period. Conclusions: Given the retrospective and uncontrolled audit design, findings should be interpreted with appropriate caution. However, the consistent improvements observed across multiple practices suggest that carbohydrate-reduction strategies within holistic models of care can meaningfully improve diabetes outcomes in real-world primary care settings. Future research should evaluate longer-term sustainability, implementation fidelity, and the applicability of this model at scale, particularly for Māori and Pacific communities.
DOI: 10.3390/nu17243953
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu17243953-2026-01-15-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Impact of α-linolenic acid supplementation on long-chain n-3 fatty acid profiles in Western, flexitarian, vegetarian, and vegan diets</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1727308</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 53
Autoren: Lea Klein, Kristin Kipp, Stefan Lorkowski, Fabian Eichelmann, Christine Dawczynski
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-15
Abstract: 
                    Introduction
                    
                      Long-chain (LC)
                      n
                      -3 polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) are critical nutrients in vegetarian and vegan diets due to the absence of fish and other animal products.
                      α
                      -Linolenic acid (ALA) is the main plant derived precursor for eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA), docosapentaenoic acid (DPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA), yet conversion efficiency is limited and influenced by several dietary and metabolic factors. Therefore, the NuEva Study aimed to investigate the impact of flaxseed oil on fatty acid profiles depending on age, sex, body mass index (BMI), dietary pattern (Western diet (omnivores), flexitarian, vegetarian, vegan), and status of relevant nutrients.
                    
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    
                      The NuEva study is a prospective non-randomized intervention with parallel diet groups (Western diet (omnivores), flexitarian, vegetarian, vegan;
                      n
                       = 168), which includes nutrient-optimized menu plans (12 months) combined with flaxseed oil supplementation (3 g/d ALA for 9 months). Fatty acids were analyzed at baseline and repeatedly throughout the intervention period focusing on
                      n
                      -6 and
                      n
                      -3 PUFA in plasma and erythrocytes lipids. Furthermore, potential modulators of ALA conversion (age, sex, BMI, linoleic acid, arachidonic acid, and EPA status) were investigated.
                    
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      In Western diet participants, erythrocyte
                      n
                      -6 PUFA increased by 5.5%, mainly due to arachidonic acid. In contrast, ALA (+22.5–38.4%), EPA (+27.3–40.7%), DPA (+27.2–40.7%) and DHA (+12.8–26.0%) increased significantly across all dietary patterns. Conversion efficiency was unaffected by sex, BMI, age, linoleic acid, or arachidonic acid, but individuals with low baseline EPA showed markedly greater increases in EPA (+62.9% vs. +12.9%), DPA (+41.9% vs. +22.3%), and DHA (+27.0% vs. +7.6%) compared to subjects with higher EPA status.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    
                      In conclusion, flaxseed oil supplementation combined with a controlled diet effectively improves
                      n
                      -3 LCPUFA status irrespective of habitual diet. The extent of relative improvement was primarily determined by baseline EPA concentrations.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1727308
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1727308-2026-01-15-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>