<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:15:55 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:15:55 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Differential oxido-reductive activities of aged garlic extract and S-allyl-cysteine in genetically modified Drosophila model of Alzheimer’s disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05093-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 25
Autoren: Olasunmbo Afolayan, Victor Nwaogu, Olumayowa Idowu, Olufunke Dosumu
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-21
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05093-5
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05093-5-2025-11-23-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effectiveness and safety of turmeric for the treatment of COVID-19: An updated systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ctim.2025.103295</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 23
Autoren: Ratree Sawangjit, Saranrat Sadoyu, Siripong Manosanthipaibul, Nattawat Teerawattanapong, Panupong Puttarak, Kulthanit Wanaratna, Rawiwan Charoensup, Poonsit Hiransai, Thunyaluk Meetam, Nathorn Chaiyakunapruk
Journal: Complementary Therapies in Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ctim.2025.103295
ISSN: 0965-2299
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ctim.2025.103295-2025-11-23-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Retraction Note: Inhibition of alpha-synuclein seeded fibril formation and toxicity by herbal medicinal extracts</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05176-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Mustafa T. Ardah, Simona S. Ghanem, Sara A. Abdulla, Guohua Lv, Mohamed M. Emara, Katerina E. Paleologou, Nishant N. Vaikath, Jia-Hong Lu, Min Li, Konstantinos Vekrellis, David Eliezer, Omar M. A. El-Agnaf
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-08
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05176-3
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05176-3-2025-11-23-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Evaluation of integrative oncology modalities for symptom management: a MASCC/SIO global survey</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05157-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 20
Autoren: Alexandre Chan, Reem Nasr, Daniela Arcos, Dalia Kagramanov, Chioma Asuzu, Ting Bao, Yin Ting Cheung, Jung Hye Kwon, Judith Lacey, Richard T. Lee, Maryam Lustberg, Beatrice M. Ohaeri, Santosh Rao, Enrique Soto-Perez-de-Celis, Claudia M. Witt, Ana Maria Lopez
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-03
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Background
                    With growing evidence pointing towards the potential of integrative oncology modalities (IOM) in addressing cancer and cancer-treatment related symptoms, research on IOM utilization and implementation is warranted. This study examines global stakeholder perspectives on integrative oncology (IO) utilization for supportive cancer care.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Members of the Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer (MASCC) and the Society for Integrative Oncology (SIO) completed a survey on the utilization of IOM for supportive cancer care. Descriptive statistics were used to assess demographic data, IOM usage patterns, IOM education, and financial considerations for utilizing IOM.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Among 344 participants representing eight geographical regions, 70% reported having utilized or recommended IOM and 79% perceived IOM to be underutilized in cancer supportive care. Acupuncture (48%), exercise classes (39%), nutrition (38%), breathing/yoga (38%) and personalized exercise (38%) were among the most utilized IOM across regions. Relatedly, the symptoms for which IOM were most recommended for persons with a diagnosis of cancer in active treatment [AT] or completed treatment [CT] respectively were emotional (AT 23%; CT 26%), pain (AT 22%; CT 20%), gastrointestinal (AT 21%; CT 12%) and fatigue (AT 15%; CT 16%). The perceived availability of integrative medicine training was highest in North America (69%). Across regions, self-pay (20%-67%), private insurance (0%-26%) and government insurance (7%-40%) were the most common forms of payment for IOM. The IOM most recommended in high-income countries (acupuncture, exercise, massage, individual exercise) varied from the IOM most recommended in low-middle income countries (nutrition counseling, exercise classes, breathing, acupuncture).
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    This study provides valuable insights into global utilization patterns of IOM in supportive cancer care, highlighting that while most respondents have utilized IOM, there is a perceived underutilization overall. Our results show significant regional differences in the availability of integrative oncology education and hint to financial barriers impacting IOM use. Further research is necessary to explore these aspects and inform strategies for supporting IOM implementation efforts.
                  
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05157-6
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05157-6-2025-11-23-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>East Asian traditional medicine for attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder in children and adolescents: a scoping review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05119-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 20
Autoren: Jihong Lee, Hyun-Kyung Sung
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-24
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05119-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-23</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05119-y-2025-11-23-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>