<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 01:08:32 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 01:08:32 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>A multimodal sleep foundation model for disease prediction</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-04133-4</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 989
Autoren: Rahul Thapa, Magnus Ruud Kjaer, Bryan He, Ian Covert, Hyatt Moore IV, Umaer Hanif, Gauri Ganjoo, M. Brandon Westover, Poul Jennum, Andreas Brink-Kjaer, Emmanuel Mignot, James Zou
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-06
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Sleep is a fundamental biological process with broad implications for physical and mental health, yet its complex relationship with disease remains poorly understood. Polysomnography (PSG)—the gold standard for sleep analysis—captures rich physiological signals but is underutilized due to challenges in standardization, generalizability and multimodal integration. To address these challenges, we developed SleepFM, a multimodal sleep foundation model trained with a new contrastive learning approach that accommodates multiple PSG configurations. Trained on a curated dataset of over 585,000 hours of PSG recordings from approximately 65,000 participants across several cohorts, SleepFM produces latent sleep representations that capture the physiological and temporal structure of sleep and enable accurate prediction of future disease risk. From one night of sleep, SleepFM accurately predicts 130 conditions with a C-Index of at least 0.75 (Bonferroni-corrected
                    P
                     &amp;lt; 0.01), including all-cause mortality (C-Index, 0.84), dementia (0.85), myocardial infarction (0.81), heart failure (0.80), chronic kidney disease (0.79), stroke (0.78) and atrial fibrillation (0.78). Moreover, the model demonstrates strong transfer learning performance on a dataset from the Sleep Heart Health Study—a dataset that was excluded from pretraining—and performs competitively with specialized sleep-staging models such as U-Sleep and YASA on common sleep analysis tasks, achieving mean
                    F
                    1
                    scores of 0.70–0.78 for sleep staging and accuracies of 0.69 and 0.87 for classifying sleep apnea severity and presence. This work shows that foundation models can learn the language of sleep from multimodal sleep recordings, enabling scalable, label-efficient analysis and disease prediction.
                  
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-04133-4
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-04133-4-2026-01-13-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Nitrous oxide for the treatment of depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.106023</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 532
Autoren: Kiranpreet Gill, Angharad N. de Cates, Chantelle Wiseman, Susannah E. Murphy, Ella Williams, Catherine J. Harmer, Isabel Morales-Muñoz, Steven Marwaha
Journal: eBioMedicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.106023
ISSN: 2352-3964
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.106023-2026-01-13-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A circadian checkpoint relocates neutrophils to minimize injury</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1084/jem.20250240</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 463
Autoren: Alejandra Aroca-Crevillén, Sandra Martín-Salamanca, Lidiane S. Torres, Georgiana Crainiciuc, Jon Sicilia, Eduardo Peñaloza-Martínez, Nicolás Rosillo, Miguel Molina-Moreno, Jose M. Adrover, Andrea Rubio-Ponce, Tommaso Vicanolo, Xiaosong Liu, Kanin Wichapong, Vanessa Núñez, Karl Balabanian, Françoise Bachelerie, David Sancho, María Casanova-Acebes, José T. Ortiz-Pérez, María Ángeles Moro, Héctor Bueno, Gerry A.F. Nicolaes, Andrés Hidalgo
Journal: Journal of Experimental Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-12
Abstract: Inflammation-driven injury, a significant source of morbidity and mortality worldwide, is largely mediated by the cytotoxic activities of neutrophils, which extend the initial lesion and jeopardize organ function. Intriguingly, inflammatory injury naturally declines at specific times of day, suggesting that circadian mechanisms exist that mitigate the destructive activity of neutrophils and protect the host. Here, we show that the periods of diurnal protection coincide with peaks in plasma CXCL12, a chemokine that inhibits the neutrophil-intrinsic circadian clock by signaling through CXCR4. Genetic deletion of this clock, or a hyperactive form of CXCR4, prevented the diurnal spikes of injury, and treatment with a synthetic CXCR4 agonist conferred protection from myocardial and vascular injury. In tissues, this protection was mediated by repositioning neutrophils in the wound core, which spared neighboring host cells from apoptotic death. Thus, a circadian neutrophil checkpoint protects from exuberant inflammation and can be activated to protect the host.
DOI: 10.1084/jem.20250240
ISSN: 0022-1007
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1084/jem.20250240-2026-01-13-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Neurobehavioural links from infant screen time to anxiety</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.106093</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 462
Autoren: Pei Huang, Shi Yu Chan, Kathy Xinzhuo Zhou, Jasmine Chuah, Aisleen Mariz Arellano Manahan, Evelyn Chung Ning Law, Shefaly Shorey, Helen Juan Zhou, Marielle Valerie Fortier, Yap-Seng Chong, Michael Joseph Meaney, Ai Peng Tan
Journal: eBioMedicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.106093
ISSN: 2352-3964
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ebiom.2025.106093-2026-01-13-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Eleven clinical trials that will shape medicine in 2026</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-04083-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 430
Autoren: Mike May
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-04083-x
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-04083-x-2026-01-13-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>