<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 01:11:12 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 01:11:12 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>The Influence of Ultraprocessed Food Consumption on Energy Intake in Emerging Adulthood: A Controlled Feeding Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.70086</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 346
Autoren: Maria L. M. Rego, Emma Leslie, Emily Schmall, Bailey Capra, Summer Hudson, Monica L. Ahrens, Benjamin Katz, Kevin P. Davy, Valisa E. Hedrick, Alexandra G. DiFeliceantonio, Brenda M. Davy
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-19
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    Objective
                    This study examined the impact of a 2‐week eucaloric diet high in ultraprocessed foods (UPF) compared to a diet without UPF (non‐UPF) on ad libitum energy intake (EI) and food selection in individuals aged 18–25.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    In a randomized, crossover, proof‐of‐concept trial, participants completed two 14‐day controlled feeding periods (81% UPF vs. 0% UPF), with a 4‐week washout. Diets were matched for macronutrients, fiber, added sugar, diet quality, and energy density. Following each condition, participants consumed an ad libitum buffet meal including UPF and non‐UPF. Energy and food grams consumed were quantified. Statistical analyses were conducted for the full sample, late adolescents (aged 18–21), and young adults (aged 22–25).
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Twenty‐seven individuals aged 22 ± 2 years (mean BMI = 24 ± 3 kg/m
                      2
                      ) were included. Diet compliance was ~99% overall. There was no effect of diet condition on meal total kcal or grams consumed or UPF or non‐UPF consumption in the full sample (all
                      p
                       &amp;gt; 0.05). In the exploratory age subgroup analysis, an interaction between diet and age was observed for total EI (
                      p
                       &amp;lt; 0.001), where total EI increased among adolescents following the UPF diet (
                      p
                       = 0.03,
                      d
                       = 0.79), but not in young adults.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    Late adolescents may be susceptible to increased EI following a UPF diet. Future trials are warranted to evaluate this possibility.
                    
                      Trial Registration:
                      ClinicalTrials.gov
                      : NCT05550818.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/oby.70086
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.70086-2025-12-02-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Fingernail Mineral Profiling as a Non‐Invasive Tool to Assess Dietary and Lifestyle Factors: Results From the Cross‐Sectional Fulda
                    NutriNAIL
                    Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/biof.70056</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 206
Autoren: Nina Sonntag, Lina Müller, Katja Plendl, Dustin Dewald, Jan‐Torsten Milde, Heike Hollenbach, Alexander Maxones, Tilman Kühn, Marc Birringer
Journal: BioFactors
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    In the past, fingernail and toenail analyses were mainly used for toxicological investigations on heavy metals and only a few studies used mineral content as a biomarker for assessing lifestyle or dietary habits. The Fulda NutriNAIL study examined associations between lifestyle, dietary habits, supplement use, and fingernail mineral composition in 184 participants (18–81 years) from Fulda, Germany. Mineral concentrations were quantified via Inductively Coupled Plasma Mass Spectrometry (ICP‐MS), and questionnaire data were analyzed for lifestyle correlations. Positive mineral‐to‐mineral correlations were observed between sodium (Na) and potassium (K) (
                    r
                     = 0.89), calcium (Ca) and magnesium (Mg) (
                    r
                     = 0.57), and iron (Fe) and cobalt (Co) (
                    r
                     = 0.66). We detected 21% higher selenium levels in the fingernails of selenium supplement users than for non‐users. Omnivores showed higher Se levels than vegans and slightly higher levels than vegetarians and participants with thyroid disorders had significantly higher nail selenium levels. In addition, nail surface features were linked to specific mineral differences: potassium in brittle nails, reduced sodium and potassium in longitudinal ridges, and reduced chromium (Cr) in white spots. These findings demonstrate that fingernail mineral profiling is a non‐invasive method for assessing lifestyle‐ and diet‐related micronutrient status.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/biof.70056
ISSN: 0951-6433
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/biof.70056-2025-12-02-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mitochondrial complex III-derived ROS amplify immunometabolic changes in astrocytes and promote dementia pathology</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s42255-025-01390-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 181
Autoren: Daniel Barnett, Till S. Zimmer, Caroline Booraem, Fernando Palaguachi, Samantha M. Meadows, Haopeng Xiao, Man Ying Wong, Wenjie Luo, Li Gan, Edward T. Chouchani, Anna G. Orr, Adam L. Orr
Journal: Nature Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-04
DOI: 10.1038/s42255-025-01390-y
ISSN: 2522-5812
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s42255-025-01390-y-2025-12-02-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Adipose Tissue in
                    SARS
                    ‐
                    CoV
                    ‐2 Viral Tropism, Viral Replication, and the Concept of a Viral Reservoir: An Update</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.70093</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 163
Autoren: Liam Charles Maher, Paul M. Ryan, Noel M. Caplice
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-24
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  Since the onset of the COVID‐19 pandemic, obesity has been consistently associated with worse clinical outcomes. In 2020, we hypothesized that adipose tissue (AT) might serve as a viral reservoir and amplifier of immune responses in SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Five years on, accumulating evidence supports this hypothesis. Recent autopsy and in vitro studies support that SARS‐CoV‐2 disseminates to and may replicate within human adipocytes. While several studies have detected SARS‐CoV‐2 RNA and proteins in AT, the recovery of infectious virus from this tissue has not yet been demonstrated. This remains a critical gap in our understanding of SARS‐CoV‐2 viral tropism and replication within adipocytes. Viral entry is mediated via angiotensin‐converting enzyme‐2 and neuropilin‐1 receptors. Infected AT exhibits immune cell infiltration and cytokine activation, implicating it in systemic inflammation. Persistent viral RNA in AT correlates with prolonged metabolic dysfunction. These findings highlight the dual role of AT as a potential viral reservoir and immunometabolic organ. Understanding these mechanisms is critical to mitigating the long‐term impact of COVID‐19 and guiding responses to future pandemics involving metabolically active tissues.
                  
                    
                      
                        image
                      
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/oby.70093
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.70093-2025-12-02-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Body-wide multi-omic counteraction of aging with GLP-1R agonism</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.10.014</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 156
Autoren: Junzhe Huang, Andrew J. Kwok, Jason Chak Yan Li, Clement Lek Hin Chiu, Bonaventure Y. Ip, Lok Yi Tung, Roy C.H. Chan, Danny C.W. Chan, Ziyu Wang, Xianyi Zheng, Hoi Tung Chow, Michelle P.S. Lo, Zhongqi Li, Nenghan Lin, Manyu Wang, Leo Y.C. Yan, William K.K. Wu, Kim Hei-Man Chow, Wei-Jye Lin, Yamei Tang, Yun Zhang, Weihong Song, Billy Wai-Lung Ng, Sunny H. Wong, Thomas W. Leung, Vincent C.T. Mok, Ho Ko
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.10.014
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.10.014-2025-12-02-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>