<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 01:06:38 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 01:06:38 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Pitfalls of large language models in medical ethics reasoning</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01792-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 92
Autoren: Shelly Soffer, Vera Sorin, Girish N. Nadkarni, Eyal Klang
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01792-y
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01792-y-2025-08-12-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Synthetic data trained open-source language models are feasible alternatives to proprietary models for radiology reporting</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01658-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 51
Autoren: Aakriti Pandita, Angela Keniston, Nikhil Madhuripan
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-23
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01658-3
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01658-3-2025-08-12-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Sleep Quality as a Mediator of Internet Gaming Disorder and Executive Dysfunction in Adolescents: Cross-Sectional Questionnaire Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/68571</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 23
Autoren: Michoel L Moshel, Wayne Warburton, Rainer Thomasius, Kerstin Paschke
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-09
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Internet gaming disorder (IGD) has been associated with impairments in executive functioning, particularly inattention and impulsivity. Sleep quality has separately been linked to both gaming behavior and cognitive performance, yet its role as a mediating factor in this relationship is underexplored.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aimed to determine whether sleep quality mediates the relationship between IGD symptoms and executive dysfunction in adolescents, specifically focusing on the domains of inattention and hyperactivity or impulsivity. A reverse mediation model was also tested to explore the bidirectional nature of these relationships.
          
          
            Methods
            A representative sample of 1000 adolescents (539/1000, 53.9% males), aged between 12 and 17 years (mean 14.52, SD 1.64), completed validated self-report measures of IGD symptoms, executive dysfunction, and sleep quality. Structural equation modeling was used to test direct and indirect effects with age and gender included as covariates.
          
          
            Results
            Of the sample, 2.4% (24/1000) met criteria for IGD (875/1000, 87.5% males), and 22.6% (226/1000) met criteria for chronic sleep reduction. Among those with IGD, 54.2% (542/1000) also experienced chronic sleep reduction. In model A (IGD → Sleep → Executive Dysfunction), IGD symptoms were associated with poorer sleep quality (a=0.32, 95% CI 0.19-0.44), which in turn were associated with greater executive dysfunction (b=0.05, 95% CI 0.01-0.10). The indirect effect was significant (a×b=0.02, 95% CI 0.01-0.04), and sleep quality was a partial mediator. In the reverse model (model B), executive dysfunction was associated with poorer sleep quality (a=0.15, 95% CI 0.06-0.25), which subsequently was associated with higher IGD symptoms (b=0.11, 95% CI 0.07-0.16); indirect effect a×b=0.02, 95% CI 0.01-0.04. Simple slope analysis showed that IGD symptoms were associated only with executive dysfunction at average or poor levels of sleep quality. At higher levels of sleep quality, this relationship was no longer significant.
          
          
            Conclusions
            The results of this study suggest that sleep quality may be an important intermediary mechanism by which IGD might contribute to executive dysfunction and provide a basis for the development and implementation of strategies that target sleep issues in IGD. Prospective longitudinal research is needed to examine the directionality of the relationships between IGD, sleep quality, and executive dysfunction longitudinally.
          
DOI: 10.2196/68571
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/68571-2025-08-12-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Applying the principle of justice in digital health</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01877-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 17
Autoren: Oriol Yuguero, Pere Ruiz-Trujillo, Montse Esquerda, Nuria Terribas, Marta Aymerich
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-21
Abstract: Abstract
          In an increasingly digital healthcare landscape, it is essential to assess the ethical impact of technology on care practices. We present a conceptual framework on equity in digital health, addressing justice-related concepts and challenges to reducing the digital divide. An ethical approach ensures that digital health respects fundamental rights. We propose goals—such as incorporating digital determinants into public health policy—to promote justice and reduce health inequalities in digital health implementation.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01877-8
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01877-8-2025-08-12-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>One shot at trust: building credible evidence for medical artificial intelligence</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landig.2025.100883</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 15
Autoren: Ramez Kouzy, Julian C. Hong, Danielle S. Bitterman
Journal: The Lancet Digital Health
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.landig.2025.100883
ISSN: 2589-7500
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.landig.2025.100883-2025-08-12-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>