<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 01:04:38 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 01:04:38 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>The impact of population ageing on musculoskeletal disorders in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2021: global burden and healthcare costs</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.002</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 119
Autoren: Shi-Yang Guan, Jin-Xin Zheng, Xin-Yu Feng, Shun-Xian Zhang, Shu-Zhen Xu, Peng Wang, Hong-Yan Cai, Hai-Feng Pan
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.002
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.08.002-2025-10-17-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>STING-driven necroptosis linked to autoinflammatory disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41584-025-01315-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 70
Autoren: Sarah Onuora
Journal: Nature Reviews Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-02
DOI: 10.1038/s41584-025-01315-9
ISSN: 1759-4790
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41584-025-01315-9-2025-10-17-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Comparative efficacy and safety of anakinra and canakinumab in patients with VEXAS syndrome – an international multicenter study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43384</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 37
Autoren: Tali Eviatar, Dafne Capelusnik, Corrado Campochiaro, Valentin Lacombe, Vincent Jachiet, Michael Zisapel, Iftach Sagy, Oshrat E. Tayer‐Shifman, David Ozeri, Shaye Kivity, Alessandro Tomelleri, Benjamin Terrier, Hagit Peleg, Thibault Comont, Karim Sacre, Pascal Woaye‐Hune, Laurent Arnaud, Estibaliz Lazaro, Vincent Grobost, Francois Lifermann, Maxime Samson, Samuel Ardois, Alice Garnier, Alexandre Maria, Alain Cantagrel, Aurore Meyer, Jean‐David Bouaziz, Mael Heiblig, Lorenzo Dagna, Elisa Diral, Olivier Kosmider, Ori Elkayam, Jérôme Hadjadj, Sophie Georgin‐Lavialle, Olivier Fain, Arsene Mekinian
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-22
Abstract: ObjectivesThe aim of this study was to compare differences in clinical response, drug survival, and adverse event rates between anakinra and canakinumab in VEXAS syndrome.MethodsThis multicenter international study includes VEXAS patients from France, Israel, and Italy treated with IL1 inhibition (IL1i). Global response (GR) was defined as the absence of inflammatory symptoms, 50% or greater decrease in steroid dose and C‐reactive protein. Multiple regression analysis was performed to identify associated variables. Drug survival was analyzed using Kaplan‐Meier plots and log‐rank test, with Cox‐regression models for associated factors.ResultsWe included 47 male VEXAS patients; 44 received anakinra, and 9 received canakinumab, with 6 patients using both at different time points. GR at 1 month was 34% for anakinra and 100% for canakinumab (p&amp;lt;0.001), 22% and 78% at 3 months, respectively (p=0.001).Treatment with canakinumab was associated with higher odds ratio (OR) of achieving GR at 3 months (OR 28.8, 95%CI 3·0‐273·9, p=0.004) in a multivariable analysis. Median drug survival was 54 (30‐56) months for canakinumab at 300 mg/month, compared to 7 (4‐8) months for canakinumab 150 mg/month and 1 (1‐2.5) months for anakinra (p=0.01). Injection site reactions were only recorded for the anakinra group (47 vs 0%; p=0.006), whereas infections were more frequent in the anakinra group (31% and 11%; p=0·3).ConclusionsCanakinumab demonstrated superior clinical response and drug survival with fewer adverse events compared to anakinra. Monthly Canakinumab 300 mg may be considered as an effective steroid‐sparing therapeutic option for VEXAS patients.image
DOI: 10.1002/art.43384
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43384-2025-10-17-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Methylprednisolone plus MTX-based regime vs prednisone-based standard of care for GCA: a propensity score study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/rheumatology/keaf499</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 25
Autoren: Adriana Soto-Peleteiro, José Hernández-Rodríguez, Fátima Raad, Borja de Miguel, Leonor Acha, Marina Torio, Halbert Hernandez-Negrin, Verónica Gómez-Caverzaschi, Ioana Ruiz-Arruza, Olga Araujo, Sergio Prieto-González, Georgina Espígol-Frigolé, Maria C Cid, Guillermo Ruiz-Irastorza
Journal: Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-16
Abstract: Abstract
               
                  Objectives
                  Treatment of GCA still requires substantial exposure to glucocorticoids (GCs), which are associated with significant toxicity. This study compares the efficacy and safety of the GC-only standard of care (SOC) with a regimen combining intravenous methylprednisolone (IVMP) pulses, MTX and lower doses of prednisone, in newly diagnosed patients with GCA.
               
               
                  Methods
                  A usual clinical practice study was conducted in three Spanish academic hospitals. One hundred and fifty-one patients diagnosed with GCA were treated with SOC prednisone (40–60 mg/d) or with IVMP (125–500 mg/d ×3) followed by lower-dose prednisone (≤30 mg/d) and MTX (IVMP/MTX), with a follow-up of 2 years. A propensity score was used to adjust for baseline differences in the multivariate analyses.
               
               
                  Results
                  Seventy-nine (52.3%) patients received SOC prednisone and 72 (47.7%) IVMP/MTX. The clinical characteristics at baseline were similar in both the groups. Hundred percent patients achieved remission after a median time of 4 weeks, without differences between the groups. Relapse rates were also similar. Patients receiving IVMP/MTX had significantly lower cumulative GC doses and reached prednisone ≤5 mg/d faster than SOC patients (mean 13.8 vs 56.5 weeks; P &amp;amp;lt; 0.001). Patients in the IVMP/MTX group were less likely to suffer any GC-related adverse effect (adjusted OR 0.35, 95% CI 0.14–0.85; P = 0.021).
               
               
                  Conclusions
                  The combination IVMP/MTX with lower-dose prednisone is as effective as the SOC in inducing remission and preventing relapses in GCA. The IVMP/MTX scheme significantly reduces GC exposure and GC-associated adverse effects. IVMP/MTX could be a potential GC-sparing strategy, especially in patients with GCA at higher risk of GC toxicity.
               
DOI: 10.1093/rheumatology/keaf499
ISSN: 1462-0324
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/rheumatology/keaf499-2025-10-17-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Re‐thinking Strategies for a Pharmaceutical Approach to Pain‐related to Connective Tissue Related Raynaud's Phenomenon in the United States</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25660</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 22
Autoren: Tracy M Frech, Charles G Frech, W David Merryman, Andrew Sternlicht, Justin Baba
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-25
Abstract: IntroductionThere are no Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved therapies for Raynaud's phenomenon (RP) treatment in the United States (U.S.). Clinical trials have been challenged by study design. Important advances in RP patient reported outcome measures and mechanistic quantification allows RP‐related pain characterization. The rationale for this narrative review is current RP treatment guidelines that focus on vasodilation.MethodsThe question of why there are limitations to RP treatment in the US is addressed through a comprehensive search strategy of published RP‐treatment guidelines up until September 1, 2025. Search databases included Medline (PubMed), Embase, and Scopus for index terms, “Raynaud's phenomenon treatment guidelines”. If a society guideline was updated, only the most recent was included. Eligibility, data extraction, risk of bias and quality assessment were subject to review by two independent reviewers with a third reviewer resolving discrepancies. US specific considerations of published guidelines are reviewed.ResultsThere were 118 published articles that were identified by the search terms ‘Raynaud's phenomenon treatment guidelines,’ and 27 abstracts were reviewed. There were 4 articles that were published as RP treatment recommendations or guidelines, which were reviewed for full content. Pain management for RP is not included in guideline‐based care.ConclusionThere are advances in outcome measures for quantifying pain now available for RP clinical trials. Large U.S. based registries for systemic sclerosis (SSc) utilizing patient reported outcomes can allow serial data collection on RP and RP‐related digital lesions to provide real‐world data on medication efficacy for pain relief.image
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25660
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-17</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25660-2025-10-17-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>