<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 01:05:50 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 01:05:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Early meal timing attenuates high polygenic risk of obesity</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.24319</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 245
Autoren: R De la Peña‐Armada, María Rodríguez‐Martín, Hassan S. Dashti, Ana Isabel Cascales, Frank A. J. L. Scheer, Richa Saxena, Marta Garaulet
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-20
Abstract: AbstractObjectiveWe examined whether meal timing is associated with long‐term weight‐loss maintenance and whether meal timing interacts with a genome‐wide polygenic score (PRS‐BMI) on body weight‐related outcomes. We then examined the interaction of meal timing with 97 BMI‐related single‐nucleotide polymorphisms on obesity outcome.MethodsParticipants (N = 1195, mean age 41.07 [SD 12.68] years, female 80.8%, baseline mean BMI 31.32 [SD 5.53] kg/m2) were adults with overweight or obesity from the Obesity, Nutrigenetics, Timing, and Mediterranean (ONTIME) study. We developed a PRS‐BMI to assess the genetic risk for obesity and estimated the timing of the midpoint of meal intake. We also calculated the success in long‐term weight‐loss maintenance after a dietary obesity treatment (at least 3 years). Linear regression analyses were performed for association and interaction assessments.ResultsEach hour of delay in meal timing was associated with 2.2% higher long‐term body weight (β [SE] = 2.177% [1.067%]; p = 0.042) (i.e., with lower weight‐loss maintenance following dietary obesity treatment). There was a significant interaction between meal timing and PRS‐BMI (p = 0.008); BMI increased by more than 2 kg/m2 for every hour of delay in meal timing in individuals with high PRS‐BMI (β [SE] = 2.208 [0.502] kg/m2; p = 1.0E‐5), whereas no associations were evident for those with lower genetic risk.ConclusionsMeal timing is associated with weight‐loss maintenance and may influence the association between obesity genetics and BMI. Findings underscore the importance of personalized obesity management.image
DOI: 10.1002/oby.24319
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.24319-2025-08-19-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Associations between within-day step accumulation pattern and clinical measures of physical function: a change-for-change analysis of longitudinal data in community-dwelling older adults</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-025-01797-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 163
Autoren: Melvyn Hillsdon, Alexander Schoenfelder, Brad Metcalf, Afroditi Stathi, Max J. Western, Joss Langford
Journal: International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-15
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            While daily step count and stepping pace are linked to various health benefits in older adults, less is known about how the pattern of step accumulation affects physical function. For example, the same step count could be accumulated through clusters of frequent, short bouts (e.g., during house cleaning) or fewer, longer bouts (e.g., walking to and from work). This study aimed to explore whether stepping patterns, and trends in these patterns, were associated with physical function in older adults.
          
          
            Methods
            We analysed accelerometer data from wrist-worn GENEActiv devices, from four time points over 24 months in n = 597 older adults (age ≥65 years, 68% female) participating in the REtirement in ACTion intervention. A step counting algorithm was used to create bouts of stepping (at least 10 steps &amp;gt; 20 steps/minute) before counting the steps in each bout and the average cadence. Total daily steps (20–175 steps/minute), slower-paced steps (20–62 steps/minute; below the median cadence), and faster-paced walking steps (63–175 steps/minute; above the median cadence) were then calculated. We used the frequency of stepping bouts, the time between them (mean and standard deviation) and their burstiness (short bursts of stepping bouts clustered together), to examine the daily patterns of step accumulation. Linear mixed-effects models were used to assess trends in stepping variables and their association with changes in objectively measured physical function (short physical performance battery: SPPB) over the two-year period.
          
          
            Results
            Total, slower-paced and faster-paced daily steps declined, along with the average number of stepping bouts. The time between stepping bouts increased. All components of burstiness, but not burstiness itself, were associated with changes in physical function, even when faster and slower steps (total steps) were in the same model (fewer stepping bouts = lower SPPB, greater SD = lower SPPB). Mean time between bouts was the strongest independent predictor, whereby a 10-minute increase in time between bouts was associated with a clinically important 0.46 decline in SPPB score (p &amp;lt; 0.001).
          
          
            Conclusions
            Preventing increases in the time between stepping bouts could help preserve physical function in older adults. Future intervention trials targeting how bouts of stepping are spread throughout the day, rather than just total steps, may provide a more effective approach to promoting healthy physical functioning in older age.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12966-025-01797-6
ISSN: 1479-5868
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12966-025-01797-6-2025-08-19-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Low-fat and Whole Milk Consumption in relation to Cardiovascular and All-Cause Mortality: A prospective cohort study in three Norwegian counties</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 94
Autoren: Erik Kristoffer Arnesen, Jacob Juel Christensen, Ida Laake, Monica H. Carlsen, Marit B. Veierød, Kjetil Retterstøl
Journal: The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035
ISSN: 0002-9165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035-2025-08-19-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association between dairy intake and multiple health outcomes: a scoping review of systematic reviews and meta-analyses</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41430-025-01639-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 77
Autoren: Saskia Akyil, Stefanie Winkler, Dorothy Meyer, Eva Kiesswetter, Martin Kussmann, Lukas Schwingshackl, Hans Hauner
Journal: European Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-26
Abstract: Abstract
          Food-based dietary guidelines acknowledge non-fortified dairy foods as a source of multiple essential vitamins and minerals as well as high-quality protein. Considering the cultural significance of dairy foods in our diet and the increasing prevalence of non-communicable diseases, it is essential to continuously evaluate the entirety of data regarding the impact of dairy consumption on various health-related outcomes. A systematic literature search was performed in three databases: Medline, Embase, and Web of Science. Systematic reviews published between January 2014 and February 2024 based on randomized controlled trials (RCTs), prospective cohort studies, case-control studies, and/or cross-sectional studies in adults, focusing on the consumption of bovine dairy products were evaluated for inclusion. Reports from the World Cancer Research Fund on selected cancer outcomes were also included in this review. We identified 95 reports encompassing five dairy exposure categories on 29 different health outcomes. Out of 281 associations identified, 37.7% linked dairy consumption to a reduced risk, while 48.0% showed no association with disease risk. Inconclusive results were found in 10.0% of the associations, and 4.3% indicated an increased risk of adverse health outcomes. Overall, the evidence suggests that consuming dairy is not associated with an increased risk of non-communicable diseases or mortality. In fact, it may moderately reduce the risk of several health outcomes, including adverse cardiovascular outcomes and certain cancers such as bladder, breast, colorectal, liver, oral, and ovarian. Some studies have also linked dairy consumption to improved body composition, lower rates of type 2 diabetes, and better bone health.
DOI: 10.1038/s41430-025-01639-5
ISSN: 0954-3007
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41430-025-01639-5-2025-08-19-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Nutritional Epidemiology Risk–Survival Paradox</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 74
Autoren: Raphael E Cuomo
Journal: The Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020
ISSN: 0022-3166
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-19</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020-2025-08-19-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>