<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:59:16 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:59:16 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Baseline individual factors associated with clinical outcomes in adults with non-specific low back pain following manual therapy: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Gaetan Barbier, Mathieu Picchiottino, Arnaud Delafontaine, Guillaume Goncalves, André Bussières, François Cottin, Arnaud Lardon
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y-2025-10-02-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Systematic review of clinical practice guidelines on acupuncture for chronic musculoskeletal pain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Leonard Ho, Cyrus Ngo Tin Lai, Haiyong Chen, Sheung Wai Law, Edwin Chau Leung Yu, Fiona Pui Yan Lam, Yi Chung Cheung, Irene Xinyin Wu, Samuel Yeung Shan Wong, Regina Wing Shan Sit
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Introduction
            Acupuncture is increasingly utilised in primary care to manage chronic musculoskeletal pain, supported by a growing body of evidence. This rising adoption has driven demand for clinical practice guidelines (CPGs). We summarised the characteristics of recent acupuncture CPGs for osteoarthritis, low back pain, neck pain, and shoulder pain, and critically appraised their methodological quality.
          
          
            Methods
            We searched nine databases to identify acupuncture CPGs published from January 2014 to November 2024. Eligible CPGs were required to be developed by guideline committees and to include evidence-informed recommendations linked to clearly defined levels of evidence. Two independent reviewers extracted CPG characteristics and assessed methodological quality using the Appraisal of Guidelines for Research and Evaluation II (AGREE II) instrument.
          
          
            Results
            Of the 1,999 records screened, 17 CPGs were included, encompassing 35 recommendations. Shoulder pain was the most addressed condition (n = 14), followed by low back pain (n = 11), osteoarthritis (n = 8), and neck pain (n = 2). Various types of acupuncture were considered, with manual acupuncture featuring in most (n = 26) recommendations. Overall, 60% of the recommendations supported the use of acupuncture, comprising 5.7% strong recommendations and 54.3% weak or conditional recommendations. In contrast, 22.9% of recommendations offered no explicit guidance, while 17.1% advised against its use. Methodological assessment classified 10 CPGs as high quality, while seven were of moderate quality.
          
          
            Conclusions
            Contradictions exist among the included CPGs regarding whether acupuncture should be recommended for routine practice, potentially reflecting differences in clinical and cultural contexts. Local CPGs should be developed using rigorous methodology, ensuring the involvement of local stakeholders. An AGREE II extension should be developed for the methodological quality assessment of acupuncture CPGs.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y-2025-10-02-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Patients’ experiences with acupuncture for diabetic polyneuropathy as part of a randomized controlled trial (ACUDPN) – a qualitative study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05064-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Marie Bolster, Joanna Dietzel, Isabel Valentina Habermann, Sebastian Hörder, Benno Brinkhaus, Barbara Stöckigt
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            This qualitative study aims to analyse the experiences, perceptions, and motivations of patients with Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy (DPN), who received acupuncture treatments for the symptoms of DPN as part of a Randomized-Controlled Trial (RCT).
          
          
            Methods
            Semi-structured interviews were carried out with participants of a two-arm RCT as part of a mixed-methods study. The interviews were conducted fact-to-face or via phone using a semi-structured interview guide with questions on living with DPN, the medical care for DPN prior to the study, the acupuncture treatments and the overall trial participation.
          
          
            Results
            In total, 10 participants participated between January – December 2020 in this study. All but one participant had positive experiences with acupuncture and reported a reduction of DPN symptoms. They had varying experiences and needs and adopted a range of different coping mechanisms to manage their symptoms and condition prior to participating in the RCT. Many felt dissatisfied with the lack of current treatment options and insufficient medical care for DPN and wished to reduce medication. Acceptance of acupuncture was high, particularly among those wishing to reduce medication. The findings of the qualitative study are in line with the results of the RCT.
          
          
            Conclusions
            Results the qualitative study indicate that acupuncture could be an acceptable and perceived effective treatment option for DPN patients. Declarations.
          
          
            Trial registration
            RCT: ClinicalTrials.gov NCT03755960. Registered on 11 August 2018.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05064-w
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05064-w-2025-10-02-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Urinary oxytocin levels in children meeting a Hospital Dog®</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05076-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: A. Risberg, A. Larsson, U. Bodén, A. Edner
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-08
Abstract: 
            Abstract
            There has been growing interest in animal-assisted therapy (AAT) in recent decades due to increasing reports indicating its health benefits for adult patients. These benefits are partly attributed to changes, usually increased levels of the neuropeptide oxytocin. 
          
          
            Aim
            To investigate changes in oxytocin levels in hospitalized children meeting a certified Hospital Dog®.
          
          
            Method
            Urine samples were collected between 25/02/2016 and 24/05/2017 from 35 hospitalized children (3–17 years) before and after each participant had a session with the Hospital Dog®. Oxytocin levels were analysed with an acetylcholinesterase (AChE) competitive enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). Creatinine levels were measured to determine the subject’s fluid intake and then divided by the hormonal concentration (uOT pg/ml).
          
          
            Results
            The mean level of uOT was 186.0 ± 236.7 (51.5–1349.5) pg/ml before and 137.3 ± 121.5 (30.7–591.3) pg/ml after the dog session (p = 0.010).
          
          
            Conclusion
            Decreased levels of uOT were recorded during the study in which hospitalized children met a Hospital Dog®. The decreased OT levels are potentially the result of the intense activity the subject experienced with the dog during the interaction.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05076-6
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05076-6-2025-10-02-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Chitosan nanocarriers loaded with Egyptian Calligonum comosum L'Hér. Extract: an eco-friendly approach for investigating triple-action biological activities</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Yasser I. Khedr, Soliman M. Toto, Salama M. El-Darier, Mostafa K. Hafez, Abdel-Hamid A. Sakr, Magdi A. Ali, Mohamed Zakaria El-Sayed, Aya M. Helal
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-24
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            
              Calligonum comosum L’Hér. is a large perennial shrub that grows in the desert. This plant inhabits much of the Egyptian desert, but has not yet been scientifically validated. Herein, we demonstrate the antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, and anticancer properties of the ethanolic extract of the Egyptian C. comosum (CE) and its novel eco-friendly chitosan nano-formula (CE/CsNPs), which is prepared using citrate as a crosslinker.
          
          
            Methods
            The produced plant ethanolic extract (CE) was chemically analyzed. The eco-friendly CE/CsNPs were successfully developed through the conjugation of CE with different concentrations (200, 350, and 400 mg/100 mL) within the chitosan nanoparticle; then, it was fully characterized for the determination of the optimum formula and followed by the assessment of the antioxidant effects, proinflammatory cytokines, evaluation of cytotoxicity against different types of cancer cell lines, and estimation of antimicrobial effects of CE and CE/CsNPs.
          
          
            Results
            The eco-friendly CE/CsNPs-2 encapsulating 350 mg of CE was selected for the in vitro studies, as it displayed NPs with a small size and a surface charge of 37.7 ± 1.91 mV with the best encapsulation efficiency (70.15 ± 1.58%) within the CsNPs, and it showed a good release profile. Transmission electron microscope (TEM) images confirmed the discrete spherical shape of CE/CsNPs-2, with no aggregations, and revealed a size range of 49.69 to 71.93 nm. FTIR displayed the successful incorporation of CE into the eco-friendly CsNPs. Regarding their biological activity, CE/CsNPs have superior efficacy with high cytotoxicity against cancer cell lines and antioxidant effects. RT-qPCR gene expression assessments displayed that CE/CsNPs resulted in a remarkable downregulation of the inflammatory cytokines’ mRNA transcript levels (p &amp;lt; 0.05). It enhanced the antimicrobial effect, with an inhibition zone of 12.34 ± 0.75 mm for Escherichia coli, 16.41 ± 1.01 mm for Staphylococcus aureus, and 18.74 ± 1.13 mm for Candida albicans.
          
          
            Conclusions
            The CE possesses various biological activities, and the developed CE/CsNPs could serve as an appealing formulation to be further investigated for use in anticancer regimens.
          
          
            Graphical Abstract
            Synthesis of eco-friendly chitosan nanoparticles loaded with ethanolic extract of C. comosum (CE/CsNPs) by using citrate as an organic cross-linker. The optimum CE/CsNPs formulation loaded with 350 mg/100 mL of the extract with the highest entrapment efficiency (EE)% is a promising anticancer candidate, displaying anticancer, antioxidant, and antimicrobial in vitro potencies.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x-2025-10-02-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>