<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:05:13 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:05:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Development of a new treatment for osteoporotic vertebral fractures using adipose-derived stem cell spheroids</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1302/2046-3758.1410.bjr-2025-0092.r1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 488
Autoren: Yuta Sawada, Shinji Takahashi, Kumi Orita, Akito Yabu, Masayoshi Iwamae, Yuki Okamura, Yuto Kobayashi, Hiroshi Taniwaki, Hiroaki Nakamura, Hidetomi Terai
Journal: Bone &amp;amp; Joint Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-28
Abstract: 
                    Aims
                    Osteoporotic vertebral fractures substantially contribute to disability and often require surgical intervention. However, some challenges, such as implant failure and suboptimal bone regeneration, limit current treatments. Adipose-derived stem cells are promising for regenerative therapy because they are easily obtained, highly proliferative, and resistant to osteoporosis-related symptoms. This study aimed to evaluate the combined effects of osteogenic adipose-derived stem cell spheroids and β-tricalcium phosphate on vertebral bone regeneration in a rat osteoporotic vertebral fracture model.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Osteoporosis was induced in 33 rats (11 per group) by ovariectomy, and defects were created in the L4 and L5 vertebrae. Adipose-derived stem cells were spheroidized and mixed with β-tricalcium phosphate scaffolds. Groups included osteogenic spheroids, undifferentiated spheroids, and β-tricalcium phosphate alone. Bone regeneration was assessed using micro-CT, histology, and biomechanical testing at four and eight weeks. Further in vitro analyses were conducted.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      The osteogenic spheroid group showed significantly higher bone mass, fusion score, and mechanical strength than the control group did. Histological analysis revealed enhanced new bone formation and β-tricalcium phosphate integration. Gene expression analysis revealed osteogenic marker (alkaline phosphatase (
                      ALP
                      ), osteocalcin (
                      OCN
                      ), and runt-related transcription factor 2 (
                      Runx2
                      )) and regenerative factor (bone morphogenetic protein 7 (
                      BMP-7
                      ), insulin-like growth factor 1 (
                      IGF-1
                      ), hepatocyte growth factor
                      1
                      (
                      HGF-1
                      ), and octamer-binding transcription factor
                      4
                      (
                      Oct4
                      ) upregulation, along with reduced apoptosis. Further, adipose-derived stem cell survival was confirmed at the repair site. These results indicate that adipose-derived stem cells contribute to both paracrine and direct osteogenesis.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Combining osteogenic adipose-derived stem cell spheroids with β-tricalcium phosphate scaffolds effectively promotes vertebral bone regeneration in osteoporotic vertebral fracture. This approach is a promising strategy for improving osteoporotic fracture repair with potential clinical applications.
                    
                      Cite this article:
                      Bone Joint Res
                       2025;14(10):915–926.
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1302/2046-3758.1410.bjr-2025-0092.r1
ISSN: 2046-3758
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1302/2046-3758.1410.bjr-2025-0092.r1-2025-11-25-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Characterizing Microstructural and Mechanical Properties of Dancer Achilles Tendon Using Ultrashort Echo Time MRI and Shear Wave Elastography Ultrasound</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/jor.70075</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 46
Autoren: Anna M. Horner, Felix M. Gonzalez, Courtney N. Gleason, Amanda Blackmon, Emma Faulkner, Damian Dyckman, Monica B. Umpierrez, Philip K.‐W. Wong, Vahid Khalilzad Sharghi, Pan Su, David A. Reiter
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-22
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    Previous observations of multi‐echo ultrashort echo time (UTE) magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) decay data from the Achilles tendon (AT) report an off‐resonance non‐water signal associated with non‐collagenous extracellular matrix (ECM) constituents. This cross‐sectional study investigates the relationship between this MRI‐derived tissue matrix signal and mechanical stiffness of the AT in professional ballet dancers and non‐dancer adults. Multiexponential analysis of multi‐echo UTE MRI was used to quantify water components and an off‐resonance AT matrix component. To compare AT structure with its functionality, shear wave elastography (SWE) ultrasound US was used to measure tendon stiffness along both longitudinal (V
                    L
                    ) and transverse (V
                    S
                    ) axes. 34 participants, including 15 ballet dancers and 19 non‐dancers, were studied. Dancers exhibited significantly larger V
                    S
                    (
                    p
                     = 0.013) compared to non‐dancers, consistent with prior observations of a training effect in tendon from repeated loading with exercise. UTE‐derived off‐resonance relaxation component amplitude, β
                    3
                    , was positively associated with V
                    L
                    in dancers (
                    p
                     = 0.029) and V
                    S
                    in non‐dancers (
                    p
                     = 0.024), suggesting a microstructural role of this matrix component. While additional work is needed to unambiguously assign this off‐resonance signal, these findings suggest its association with non‐collagenous ECM and show potential for combined use of UTE and SWE imaging to assess tendon structure‐function relationships and adaptations to mechanical loading in vivo.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/jor.70075
ISSN: 0736-0266
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/jor.70075-2025-11-25-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>ASTM biomechanical study comparing the AxioMed lumbar viscoelastic disc to human lumbar disc data</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2025.106686</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 42
Autoren: Kingsley R. Chin, Sukanya Chebrolu, Roger D. Sung, Jeffrey R. Carlson, Mark W. McFarland, Erik Spayde, William M. Costigan, Sandra Thompson, Vito Lore, Kari B. Zimmers, Hope Estevez, Swapnil Pangarkar, Aditya Humad, Chukwunonso C. Ilogu, Jason A. Seale
Journal: Clinical Biomechanics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2025.106686
ISSN: 0268-0033
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2025.106686-2025-11-25-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Agreement between high-quality clinical practice guidelines in their treatment recommendations for low back pain: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.spinee.2025.07.015</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 42
Autoren: Bayden J. McKenzie, Romi Haas, Giovanni E. Ferreira, Alexandra Gorelik, Sheila Cyril, Jia Xi Han, Stephen Gilbert, Liesl Grobler, Chris G. Maher, Rachelle Buchbinder
Journal: The Spine Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.spinee.2025.07.015
ISSN: 1529-9430
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.spinee.2025.07.015-2025-11-25-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Physiotherapy Compared With Shockwave Therapy for the Treatment of Proximal Hamstring Tendinopathy: A Randomized Controlled Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/03635465251391134</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 20
Autoren: Aidan Rich, Jon Ford, Jilliane Cook, Andrew Hahne
Journal: The American Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-16
Abstract: 
                    Background:
                    Proximal hamstring tendinopathy (PHT) presents as localized lower buttock pain with tasks such as running and sitting.
                  
                  
                    Purpose:
                    To investigate the effectiveness of individualized physiotherapy compared with shockwave therapy on pain and function in PHT.
                  
                  
                    Methods:
                    This prospective parallel-group, assessor-blinded randomized controlled trial (RCT) was set in 10 primary care physiotherapy practices in Victoria, Australia. A total of 100 participants with PHT were randomly assigned to receive 6 sessions of either individualized physiotherapy or shockwave therapy, with both groups receiving standardized advice and education. Primary outcomes were global rating of change on a 7-point Likert scale and the Victorian Institute of Sport Assessment Scale for Proximal Hamstring Tendinopathy at 4, 12, 26, and 52 weeks postrandomization. Analyses were by intention-to-treat using linear mixed models.
                  
                  
                    Results:
                    All except 1 patient received the allocated intervention, and the participant follow-up rate was 88% at 12 months. There were no significant differences between groups in primary outcomes at any time point. For secondary outcome measures, participants in the shockwave group had statistically significantly greater satisfaction with treatment at 26 weeks, satisfaction with results of treatment at 4 and 26 weeks, and general health at 52 weeks. Responder analyses of participants achieving clinically significant improvements showed no significant differences between groups at any time point.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion:
                    This RCT found no difference in effectiveness of individualized physiotherapy compared with shockwave therapy on global effect or function in PHT. Future trials on PHT appear feasible but could explore a different sample population or other intervention and/or comparison groups.
                  
                  
                    Registration:
                    ACTRN12621000846820 (Australian New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry).
                  
DOI: 10.1177/03635465251391134
ISSN: 0363-5465
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/03635465251391134-2025-11-25-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>