<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 01:05:47 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 01:05:47 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Acupuncture for patients with mild cognitive impairment: a randomized, patient–assessor-blinded, sham-controlled pilot study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05023-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 22
Autoren: Yujin Choi, Pyung-Wha Kim, In-Chul Jung, Ae-Ran Kim, Hyo-Ju Park, Ojin Kwon, Jun-Hwan Lee, Joo-Hee Kim
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-19
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Mild cognitive impairment (MCI) is the transitional stage between normal aging and early dementia. Although acupuncture is a promising non-pharmacological treatment, higher-quality evidence is needed to confirm its effectiveness.
          
          
            Methods
            A randomized, patient- and assessor-blinded, sham-controlled, pilot clinical trial was conducted to evaluate the feasibility of acupuncture for treating MCI. In total, 30 participants were randomized into acupuncture and sham acupuncture groups. The participants underwent 24 treatment sessions over 12 weeks. The primary outcome was a change in the Alzheimer’s Disease Assessment Scale-Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-cog) score over 12 weeks, whereas the secondary outcomes included the Seoul Neuropsychological Screening Battery (SNSB-II) score. Adverse events and the success of blinding were also assessed.
          
          
            Results
            Of the 30 participants, 28 completed the study. Participants in the acupuncture and sham acupuncture groups exhibited a decrease in ADAS-cog scores from 10.27 ± 4.03 and 11.47 ± 3.85 at baseline to 5.78 ± 3.04 and 6.27 ± 2.83 at week 12, respectively. Both groups exhibited clinically meaningful improvements, with no significant difference between groups (P = 0.6590). The SNSB-II memory domain exhibited a moderate effect size favoring acupuncture (Cohen’s d = 0.57, P = 0.1317). No intervention-related adverse events were reported, and participant blinding was adequate throughout the trial.
          
          
            Conclusions
            The 12-week acupuncture treatment is feasible for patients with MCI and may improve memory. Although the primary outcomes did not reach statistical significance, the secondary outcomes suggested potential benefits. Larger confirmatory trials are warranted to investigate the effectiveness of acupuncture in patients with MCI.
          
          
            Trial registration
            Clinical Research Information Service (cris.nih.go.kr) KCT0001938 (Registered on June 3, 2016).
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05023-5
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05023-5-2025-08-31-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Discovery of pyroptosis-inducing natural products in neuroblastomas: computational studies with experimental validation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05004-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Beni Lestari, Rohmad Yudi Utomo, Faaza Aulia Rahman, Dyaningtyas Dewi Pamungkas Putri, Ummi Maryam Zulfin, Yusuke Suenaga, Edy Meiyanto, Yoshitaka Hippo
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-19
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05004-8
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05004-8-2025-08-31-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Potential clinical relevance of Buchholzia coriacea: in vitro antimicrobial characteristics of the methanol leaf extract</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05057-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Xiyao Feng, Chinonyerem O. Iheanacho
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-19
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05057-9
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05057-9-2025-08-31-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Trends and patterns of complementary and alternative medicine use among cancer patients in Jordan: a decade comparison</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05065-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Nedal Al-Rawashdeh, Mohammad Alqudimat, Ibrahim Alananzeh, Nour Kasasbeh, Khawlah Ammar, Amal Al-Omari
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-26
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05065-9
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05065-9-2025-08-31-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The clinical efficacy of auricular acupuncture in the treatment of frequent episodic tension-type headache: a single-blind randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05063-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Xiaxia Jin, Ziwen Xu, Tao Gao, Gaofeng Wang, Wendi Dong, Junyi Jin, Yongmei Yan
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-21
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Frequent episodic tension-type headache (FETTH) is a significant public-health concern. Scientific research has demonstrated that acupuncture can improve the clinical symptoms of FETTH.
          
          
            Purpose
            This study aimed to compare the efficacy and safety of auricular acupuncture and sham acupuncture in treating FETTH.
          
          
            Methods
            This was a randomized controlled trial. Participants with FETTH were randomly assigned in a 1:1 ratio to receive auricular acupuncture or sham acupuncture for 4 weeks, with follow-up lasting for up to 24 weeks. The primary outcomes were measured using the headache index and visual analog scale (VAS) score. Secondary outcomes included the Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAMA) score, Hamilton Depression Scale (HAMD) score, blood flow velocity in the anterior cerebral artery (ACA), middle cerebral artery (MCA), and posterior cerebral artery (PCA) (VACA, VMCA, and VPCA, respectively), and the usage of acute headache medications. Adverse events were also recorded to assess safety.
          
          
            Results
            Compared with the sham acupuncture group, the auricular acupuncture group showed significant improvements in VAS score (2 (1.25, 2) vs. 3 (2, 3.5) at 24 h, P &amp;lt; 0.001; 2 (1.25, 2) vs. 2 (2, 3) at the 2nd week, P = 0.004; 2 (1, 2) vs. 2 (1.5, 3) at the 4th week, P = 0.015), headache index (4 (2, 7) vs. 7 (4, 9) at the 4th week, P = 0.016), HAMA score (11.69 ± 2.70) vs. (14.24 ± 3.20) at the 4th week, P &amp;lt; 0.001; (9.83 ± 2.71) vs. (11.95 ± 2.59) at the 8th week, P = 0.001; (9.67 ± 2.65) vs. (11.76 ± 3.00) at the 24th week, P = 0.002), HAMD score ((14.25 ± 2.68) vs. (15.89 ± 3.48) at the 4th week, P = 0.027,) VACA (85.5 (85, 86) vs. 83 (83, 84) at the 4th week, P &amp;lt; 0.001), VPCA (82 (81, 83) vs. 78 (77, 79) at the 4th week, P &amp;lt; 0.001), and usage of acute headache medications (8 (7, 10) vs. 9 (8, 11) at the 4th week, P = 0.030). The incidence of adverse events was similar between the two groups (P = 1.000).
          
          
            Conclusion
            This study found that auricular acupuncture effectively improved the clinical symptoms of FETTH and had relatively fewer side effects. Trial registration: The study was retrospectively registered in the International Traditional Medicine Clinical Trial Registry (ITMCTR2025000363) on January 20, 2025.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05063-x
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-31</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05063-x-2025-08-31-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>