<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:06:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:06:43 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Tech neck: the silent pandemic that is reshaping our spine</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00586-025-09444-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 90
Autoren: Andrew Savoia, John Streepy, Catherine Yuh, Arnold Wong, Dino Samartzis
Journal: European Spine Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-10
DOI: 10.1007/s00586-025-09444-1
ISSN: 0940-6719
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00586-025-09444-1-2025-11-04-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Characterizing Microstructural and Mechanical Properties of Dancer Achilles Tendon Using Ultrashort Echo Time MRI and Shear Wave Elastography Ultrasound</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/jor.70075</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 46
Autoren: Anna M. Horner, Felix M. Gonzalez, Courtney N. Gleason, Amanda Blackmon, Emma Faulkner, Damian Dyckman, Monica B. Umpierrez, Philip K.‐W. Wong, Vahid Khalilzad Sharghi, Pan Su, David A. Reiter
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-22
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    Previous observations of multi‐echo ultrashort echo time (UTE) magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) decay data from the Achilles tendon (AT) report an off‐resonance non‐water signal associated with non‐collagenous extracellular matrix (ECM) constituents. This cross‐sectional study investigates the relationship between this MRI‐derived tissue matrix signal and mechanical stiffness of the AT in professional ballet dancers and non‐dancer adults. Multiexponential analysis of multi‐echo UTE MRI was used to quantify water components and an off‐resonance AT matrix component. To compare AT structure with its functionality, shear wave elastography (SWE) ultrasound US was used to measure tendon stiffness along both longitudinal (V
                    L
                    ) and transverse (V
                    S
                    ) axes. 34 participants, including 15 ballet dancers and 19 non‐dancers, were studied. Dancers exhibited significantly larger V
                    S
                    (
                    p
                     = 0.013) compared to non‐dancers, consistent with prior observations of a training effect in tendon from repeated loading with exercise. UTE‐derived off‐resonance relaxation component amplitude, β
                    3
                    , was positively associated with V
                    L
                    in dancers (
                    p
                     = 0.029) and V
                    S
                    in non‐dancers (
                    p
                     = 0.024), suggesting a microstructural role of this matrix component. While additional work is needed to unambiguously assign this off‐resonance signal, these findings suggest its association with non‐collagenous ECM and show potential for combined use of UTE and SWE imaging to assess tendon structure‐function relationships and adaptations to mechanical loading in vivo.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/jor.70075
ISSN: 0736-0266
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/jor.70075-2025-11-04-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Episode of Care Characteristics Following Implementation of a No Co-pay Physical Therapy Program for Musculoskeletal Conditions</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/ptj/pzaf129</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 43
Autoren: Trevor Lentz, Adam Lutz, Uchechukwu Ikeaba, Brooke Alhanti, Steven Z George, Chad Cook, Charles Thigpen
Journal: Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-24
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Importance
                    New care models promoting early access to physical therapy by reducing or eliminating co-pays are emerging. Few studies have compared health care use in these programs to other care pathways across musculoskeletal conditions.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    The objective of this study was to describe episode-level musculoskeletal health care use across different care pathway options, including a no-copay physical therapy program.
                  
                  
                    Design
                    This study was a descriptive retrospective analysis of claims data.
                  
                  
                    Setting and Participants
                    This study included health care beneficiaries of a self-insured employer with approximately 52,000 covered lives.
                  
                  
                    Interventions or Exposures
                    The study included musculoskeletal care episodes from October 2019 to September 2020 categorized as no copay physical therapy, traditional physical therapy, or other management.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcomes
                    Rates of surgery/injection, imaging, inpatient services, physician services, emergency services, physical therapy, and other services by episode type, overall and stratified by body region: upper extremity, lower extremity, and spine.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Of 9696 total episodes, 886 (9.1%) were no copay physical therapy, 1261 (13%) were traditional physical therapy, and 7549 (77.9%) were other management. No copay physical therapy episodes had lower imaging rates (38%) compared to traditional physical therapy (47%) and other management (45%) episodes. Inpatient services were similar for no copay (16%) and traditional (12%) physical therapy, both lower than other management episodes (23%). Physician services were higher in other management (100%) and traditional physical therapy (81%) episodes compared to no copay physical therapy episodes (43%). Surgery/injection rates were similar for no copay (11%) and traditional (8%) physical therapy, both lower than other management episodes (27%). Differences by pathway were more pronounced for extremity conditions than for spine conditions.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    Rates of no copay program use were modest with those who used the program having lower rates of advanced imaging, injection, and surgery.
                  
                  
                    Relevance
                    Findings may be most relevant for employers, health systems, and payors planning resource allocation and benefit design for similar programs.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/ptj/pzaf129
ISSN: 0031-9023
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/ptj/pzaf129-2025-11-04-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The changing face of acute low back pain management by physiotherapists, osteopaths and chiropractors in the UK: a 20-year comparison from 2003 to 2023</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 24
Autoren: David W. Evans, Nadine E. Foster, Alan C. Breen, Tamar Pincus, Martin Underwood, Steven Vogel
Journal: BMC Musculoskeletal Disorders
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-02
DOI: 10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9
ISSN: 1471-2474
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12891-025-09192-9-2025-11-04-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Time‐dependent wound management protocol prevents periprosthetic joint infection in total knee arthroplasty with persistent drainage</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/ksa.70077</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 16
Autoren: Filippo Leggieri, Francesco Ferriani, Enrico Di Benedetto, Enrick Miani, Enrico Festa, Giovanni Balato, Stefano M. P. Rossi, Francesco Benazzo, Andrea Baldini
Journal: Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-29
Abstract: AbstractPurposeThis study aimed to evaluate the success rate of a standardised protocol for managing persistent wound drainage following total knee arthroplasty (TKA).MethodsA prospective observational study was conducted at four institutions between January and June 2022 across primary and revision TKAs. Sixty‐two patients (mean age 71.5 ± 9.3 years; 45.2% male) who experienced postoperative wound drainage after primary (58.1%) or revision (41.9%) TKA were enrolled. The protocol included staged interventions: anticoagulation adjustments and dressing changes during Days 1–3, incisional negative pressure wound therapy during Days 3–5, and wound debridement above the joint capsule if drainage persisted beyond Day 7. Outcomes were evaluated using the ASEPSIS score. The primary outcome was defined as complete wound healing without progression to debridement, antibiotics and implant retention (DAIR) procedure or periprosthetic joint infection (PJI).ResultsThe mean follow‐up was 13.2 months (range, 11.7–15.1 months). The protocol achieved a 91.9% success rate in preventing progression to DAIR. The median number of visits required to achieve wound healing was 3.5 for the cohort. DAIR rate was 8.1% (n = 5), while PJI rate was 1.6% (n = 1). Primary TKA procedures demonstrated more efficient healing trajectories compared to revision cases, requiring fewer clinical visits (median 3 vs. 5, p &amp;lt; 0.001) and shorter hospital stays (mean 4.5 vs. 7.5 days, p = 0.017). Cox proportional hazards model identified intervention type (revision vs. primary, hazard ratio [HR] 0.24, p &amp;lt; 0.001), advanced age (HR: 0.95 per year, p = 0.006), and male gender (HR: 0.45, p = 0.020) as significant independent predictors of increased time required to achieve wound healing.ConclusionOur standardised wound management protocol achieved a high success rate in preventing progression to PJI following TKA. The time‐dependent approach to intervention escalation provides clear clinical decision‐making criteria and suggests that early identification and systematic management of wound complications are critical determinants of successful outcomes, particularly for primary TKA procedures.Level of EvidenceLevel II.
DOI: 10.1002/ksa.70077
ISSN: 0942-2056
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/ksa.70077-2025-11-04-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>