<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 01:06:51 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 01:06:51 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Development and validation of a machine-learning model to reduce futile procurements in donations after circulatory death in liver transplantation in the USA: a multicentre study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landig.2025.100918</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 282
Autoren: Rintaro Yanagawa, Kazuhiro Iwadoh, Toshihiro Nakayama, Daniel J Firl, Chase J Wehrle, Yuki Bekki, Daiki Soma, Jiro Kusakabe, Yuzuru Sambommatsu, Yutaka Endo, Kliment K Bozhilov, Jenny H Pan, Masaru Kubota, Koji Tomiyama, Masato Fujiki, Magdy Attia, Marc L Melcher, Kazunari Sasaki
Journal: The Lancet Digital Health
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.landig.2025.100918
ISSN: 2589-7500
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.landig.2025.100918-2025-11-27-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Automated detection of radiolucent foreign body aspiration on chest CT using deep learning</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-02097-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 92
Autoren: Xiaofan Liu, Zhe Chen, Zhiyong Tang, Xun Yang, Yan Jiang, Dan Zheng, Fangfang Jiang, Fang Ni, Shuang Geng, Qiong Qian, Yan Hao, Junjie Xu, Yin Wang, Mingyuan Zhu, Xiaoqing Wang, Rob M. Ewing, Zehor Belkhatir, Guqin Zhang, Hanxiang Nie, Yi Hu, Weihua Wang, Yihua Wang
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-10
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Radiolucent foreign body aspiration (FBA) remains diagnostically challenging due to its subtle imaging signatures on chest CT scans, often leading to delayed or missed diagnoses. We present a deep learning model integrating MedpSeg, a high-precision airway segmentation method, with a convolutional classifier to detect radiolucent FBA. The model was trained and validated across three independent cohorts, demonstrating consistent performance with accuracies above 90% and balanced recall–precision metrics. In a blinded independent evaluation cohort, the model outperformed expert radiologists in both recall (71.4%
                    vs
                    . 35.7%) and F1 score (74.1%
                    vs
                    . 52.6%), highlighting its potential to reduce missed cases (false negatives) and support clinical decision-making. This study illustrates the translational potential of artificial intelligence for addressing diagnostically complex and high-risk conditions, offering an effective tool to support radiologists in the assessment of suspected radiolucent foreign body aspiration. Code is available at
                    https://github.com/ZheChen1999/FBA_DL
                    .
                  
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-02097-w
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-02097-w-2025-11-27-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A generative AI teaching assistant for personalized learning in medical education</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-02022-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 60
Autoren: Thomas Thesen, Soo Hwan Park
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-04
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-02022-1
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-02022-1-2025-11-27-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Science for Pandemic Preparedness: A Precautionary Framework</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/jep.70309</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 37
Autoren: David Kriebel, Rok Ho Kim, Trisha Greenhalgh
Journal: Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-02
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  In the early weeks of the pandemic year 2020, health agencies were slow to warn of the potential for a global health emergency while scientists waited for ‘sufficient’ evidence of human‐to‐human transmission of the new coronavirus. There were further delays and confusion in issuing guidance because of uncertainty about the most important routes of exposure. A 2021 international expert panel review of COVID‐19 pandemic response concluded: ‘The bias of the current system of pandemic alert is towards inaction—steps may only be taken if the weight of evidence requires them. This bias should be reversed—precautionary action should be taken on a presumptive basis, unless evidence shows it is not necessary’. To implement this recommendation, health agencies should incorporate the concept of precaution into their methods for rapidly and transparently reaching policy decisions. In this article, we summarise the historical development of precautionary policy frameworks, and present 4 key components. First, take action if potential risks are large, even when the science is uncertain. This corresponds to the common sense idea of ‘better safe than sorry’. Second, consider the burden of proof required before choosing among alternative actions. Third, ensure that the full range of potential solutions is considered by broadly defining the problem and consulting all relevant scientific fields. Finally, increase public participation so that all relevant perspectives are included, and the chances of public buy‐in are increased. Drawing lessons from past applications and missed opportunities, we propose steps that health agencies could take to incorporate precaution into a pragmatic approach to using science for pandemic preparedness and response. The risk of another pandemic from the highly pathogenic avian influenza A (H5N1) virus underscores the urgency of this new approach.
DOI: 10.1111/jep.70309
ISSN: 1356-1294
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/jep.70309-2025-11-27-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Lessons Learned Identifying and Controlling Fraudulent Participation in Online Randomized Trials</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/77512</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 36
Autoren: Robert Siebers, Kara M Magane, Hattie Slayton, Skylar Karzhevsky, Tibor P Palfai, Ana M Abrantes, Lisa M Quintiliani, Michael D Stein
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-29
Abstract: Virtually conducted clinical trials have become an important tool for improving access to research. Online research gives rise to new avenues for potentially fraudulent actors to participate in studies to achieve monetary gain. We describe our experience of uncovering and removing fraudulent participants from a virtual research study and our methods to prevent fraudulent participants in the future. Fraudulent participation in the 2 linked online clinical trials was first uncovered in 2023, prompting our investigation and identification of additional fraudulent participants (falsified identity or information to meet eligibility criteria) who successfully enrolled in these trials. Our study team categorized indicators of suspicious activity at prescreening, screening, and baseline stages of study participation and implemented a manual checklist method to prevent fraudulent participation. We evaluate the effectiveness of our fraud prevention methods 6 months after the initial breach of the trials. Before initial detection, 10 fraudulent participants successfully enrolled in our trials. Following the implementation of new fraud prevention measures, 37 individuals were identified as fraudulent at the screening stage, and no new fraudulent participants were enrolled. We provide a comprehensive list of suspicious behaviors that may suggest the virtual research intrusion of persons using fake identities. For online clinical studies, manual methods of fraud prevention, used in conjunction with automated prevention methods, can equip researchers to detect evolving patterns of attempted fraudulent enrollment.
DOI: 10.2196/77512
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/77512-2025-11-27-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>