<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 01:08:13 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 01:08:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Knee Crepitus and Osteoarthritis Features in Young Adults Following Traumatic Knee Injury</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25637</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 176
Autoren: Jamon L. Couch, Brooke E. Patterson, Kay M. Crossley, Ali Guermazi, Matthew G. King, Danilo De Oliveira Silva, Jackie L. Whittaker, Michael A. Girdwood, Adam G. Culvenor
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-25
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    This study explored the association between knee crepitus and the presence, and worsening, of structural osteoarthritis features and self‐reported outcomes in young adults following traumatic knee injury.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    One year following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction (ACLR), 112 participants (41 female participants; median age 28 years old) self‐reported the presence and/or absence of knee crepitus using an item from the Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS). Patellofemoral and tibiofemoral osteoarthritis features (ie, cartilage lesions, osteophytes, and bone marrow lesions) were assessed from magnetic resonance imaging scans at one and five years after ACLR. Self‐reported outcomes were assessed with two KOOS subscales (pain and quality of life [QoL]) and the International Knee Documentation Committee subjective evaluation form (ie, self‐reported function). Poisson regression evaluated the relationship between self‐reported crepitus and the presence/worsening of structural osteoarthritis features. General linear models explored the relationship between crepitus and self‐reported outcomes.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Self‐reported crepitus was associated with full‐thickness patellofemoral cartilage lesions one year after ACLR (prevalence ratio 2.70, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.41–6.39) but not the risk of worsening structural osteoarthritis features between one and five years after ACLR. Those with crepitus reported worse pain (β = −6.42, 95% CI −10.47 to −2.36), QoL (β = −10.39, 95% CI −18.58 to −2.20), and function (β = −5.49, 95% CI −10.92 to −0.06) one year after ACLR but greater improvement in pain and function between one and five years.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Self‐reported knee crepitus was associated with the presence of full‐thickness patellofemoral cartilage defects one year after ACLR but was not associated with a greater risk of worsening structural osteoarthritis features up to five years after ACLR. One year after ACLR, those with crepitus reported worse pain, knee‐related QoL, and function.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25637
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-03</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25637-2025-12-03-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Reduction in Renal Relapse and Preservation of Long‐Term Kidney Function After Lupus Low Disease Activity in Patients With Lupus Nephritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25611</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 37
Autoren: Chak Kwan Cheung, Desmond Y. H. Yap, Ka Lai Lee, Philip H. Li, Iris Y. K. Tang, Chak Sing Lau, Shirley C. W. Chan
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-21
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    Lupus low disease activity state (LLDAS) is a validated treatment target in systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), but limited studies have explored the role of LLDAS in lupus nephritis (LN). This study aims to investigate the frequency and predictors of LLDAS attainment and its benefit on LN relapse and renal function preservation in patients with LN.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Patients with LN during 2010 to 2020 in Queen Mary Hospital and Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital were included in the discovery cohort and validation cohort, respectively. Complete renal response (CRR), partial renal response (PRR), LLDAS, and Definition Of Remission In SLE (DORIS) remission were assessed at 12 months. Regression analysis was performed to identify risk factors of LN relapse. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves were used to evaluate target attainment and long‐term kidney function.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      A total of 245 patients with LN (discovery cohort n = 143 and validation cohort n = 102) were included. At 12 months, 57 of 143 (40%), 14 of 143 (10%), 70 of 143 (49%), and 15 of 143 (10%) patients achieved CRR, PRR, LLDAS, and DORIS remission, respectively. Attainment of both CRR/PRR and LLDAS at 12 months was associated with best relapse‐free survival (
                      P
                      &amp;lt; 0.001). Multivariate analysis showed independent association of CRR/PRR and LLDAS with LN relapse risk reduction (CRR/PRR: hazard ratio [HR] 0.31,
                      P
                      = 0.007; LLDAS: HR 0.38,
                      P
                      = 0.029). LLDAS attainment predicts renal function preservation with satisfactory performance in both the discovery and validation cohorts (area under the curve of the ROC 0.71).
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    LLDAS is an attainable target in LN comparable to CRR/PRR. Attainment of both targets is associated with additional benefits on relapse risk reduction. Early LLDAS attainment is associated with renal function preservation.
                    
                      
                        
                          image
                        
                      
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25611
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-03</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25611-2025-12-03-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>EULAR 2025 classification criteria for haemochromatosis arthropathy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 37
Autoren: Patrick DW Kiely, Stephanie Finzel, Bayram Farisogullari, Graeme J. Carroll, Geraldine McCarthy, John Stack, Simone Parisi, Graça Porto, Pascal Richette, Gyorgy Nagy, Marton Weidl, Ann Rosenthal, Pascal Guggenbuhl, Katarzyna J. Banaszkiewicz, Svenja Engelhardt, Jeremy D. Shearman, David Mitchell, Jane Barker, Valerie Brueton, Barbara Butzeck, Philip Coathup, Howard Don, Jacqueline Dowsett, Marie Duncan, Tracey Dunleavy, Ian Fish, Allin Hoggarth, Mark McKinnon, James Minter, Tim Osborne, Marguerite Smith, Christine Wright, Pedro M. Machado
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-03</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003-2025-12-03-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Validation of a Genetic Risk Score Combined with Clinical Variables for Predicting Pulmonary Fibrosis in early Rheumatoid Arthritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25696</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 34
Autoren: Mikael Brink, Austin Wheeler, Bryant R. England, Solbritt Rantapää‐Dahlqvist
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-14
Abstract: 
                    Objectives
                    Pulmonary fibrosis (PF) is a severe extra‐articular manifestation of rheumatoid arthritis (RA). The study aimed to externally validate a genetic risk score (GRS) and a combined risk score for predicting the risk of RA‐associated PF in an independent cohort of early‐RA patients.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    This study utilized an inception cohort of 1118 patients diagnosed with RA from northern Sweden between 1996 and 2016. Clinical data were systematically collected, and genotyping was performed for 12 single‐nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) associated with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Statistical analyses, including logistic regression and area under the curve (AUC) assessments, were conducted to evaluate the performance of the GRS and in combination with clinical data as combined risk score in predicting RA‐PF development.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Of the 1115 patients with complete data, 60 (5.6%) were diagnosed with PF. PF was significantly associated with age, rheumatoid factor positivity, disease activity, and
                      MUC5B
                      (rs35705950) and
                      FAM13A
                      (rs2609255) SNPs. The GRS demonstrated a significant association with RA‐PF (odds ratio 2.6, (95%CI 1.6, 4.5), while the combined risk score exhibited superior performance (AUC 0.75, p&amp;lt;0.001) compared to the GRS alone (AUC 0.62). The combined risk score outperformed the GRS in discriminating RA‐PF, indicating its potential utility in clinical practice.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    This study provides external validation of the VARA‐ILD‐GRS and VARA‐ILD combined risk score in an RA cohort, demonstrating their generalizability and effectiveness in identifying high‐risk individuals for RA‐ILD. The findings support the integration of genetic and clinical data in risk stratification models, which could significantly improve screening strategies for RA patients at risk of developing PF.
                    
                      
                        
                          image
                        
                      
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25696
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-03</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25696-2025-12-03-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Associations of Specific Pesticides and Incident Rheumatoid Arthritis Among Female Spouses in the Agricultural Health Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43318</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 31
Autoren: Christine G. Parks, Darya Leyzarovich, Ghassan B. Hamra, Karen H. Costenbader, Dazhe Chen, Jonathan N. Hofmann, Laura E. Beane Freeman, Dale P. Sandler
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-20
Abstract: 
                    Objectives
                    Growing evidence suggests farming and agricultural pesticide use may be associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA), but few studies have examined specific pesticides and RA among women living on farms, who may personally use pesticides or may be indirectly exposed. We investigated pesticide use and RA risk among female spouses of licensed pesticide applicators in the Agricultural Health Study.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Participants were enrolled in 1993 to 1997 in North Carolina and Iowa (N = 32,126). Incident RA cases were identified in follow‐up questionnaires (1999–2021) and confirmed by medical records, relevant medication use, or Medicare claims data (1999–2016) or identified from Medicare claims if lacking questionnaire data on RA. Noncases reported no RA and had no RA Medicare claims. Among those with complete covariate data (N = 410 cases and 21,850 noncases), we examined associations with pesticide classes and 32 specific pesticides (personal lifetime use reported at enrollment, updated in 1999–2003). We calculated odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs), adjusting for age, state, education, smoking pack‐years smoking, body mass index, and correlated pesticides (ρ &amp;gt; 0.35).
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Incident RA was associated with use of organochlorine (DDT: OR 1.89, 95% CI 1.30–2.75; lindane: OR 1.97, 95% CI 1.12–3.47) and organophosphate insecticides (coumaphos: OR 2.32, 95% CI 1.29–4.19; malathion: OR 1.21, 95% CI 0.91–1.62), the carbamate insecticide carbofuran (OR 1.87, 95% CI 0.97–3.63), and permethrin and pyrethroid insecticides on crops (OR 1.56, 95% CI 0.92–2.64) and livestock (OR 1.69, 95% CI 1.07–2.68). RA was not associated with using herbicides, except for metribuzin (OR 1.88, 95% CI 0.94–3.79). The fungicides captan (OR 1.78, 95% CI 1.13–2.83) and metalaxyl (OR 2.49, 95% CI 1.41–4.40) were also associated with RA.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    These findings indicate that persistent organochlorine insecticides and some pesticides also used in public health or residential settings may increase RA risk in women.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/art.43318
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-03</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43318-2025-12-03-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>