<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 01:00:18 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 01:00:18 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>All the Colors of the Rainbow: Synthetic Dyes in US Packaged Foods and Beverages in 2020</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 942
Autoren: Elizabeth K. Dunford, Thomas M. Galligan, Lindsey Smith Taillie, Aviva A. Musicus
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.007-2025-09-05-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Healthfulness of Foods Purchased at Dollar Stores: Insights from Household Scanner Data from 2008 to 2020</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 239
Autoren: Wenhui Feng, Elina T. Page, Bangyao Sun, Sean B. Cash
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.07.001-2025-09-05-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Are all ultra-processed foods bad? A critical review of the NOVA classification system</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0029665125100645</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 176
Autoren: Jimmy Chun Yu Louie
Journal: Proceedings of the Nutrition Society
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-04
Abstract: Abstract
	  The NOVA food classification system and its categorisation of ultra-processed foods (UPFs) have significantly influenced dietary guidelines worldwide, yet the assumption that all UPFs are uniformly harmful warrants critical examination. Here, a review of evidence revealed substantial heterogeneity in health outcomes across UPF subtypes, with products like sugar-sweetened beverages consistently associated with adverse outcomes while fortified cereals and certain dairy products demonstrate neutral or protective effects. The binary nature of NOVA’s classification fails to account for nutritional composition, fortification benefits, and cultural food traditions, creating inconsistencies in categorisation across different contexts. Methodological limitations in UPF research include inadequate dietary assessment tools, selective reporting of negative findings, and experimental design flaws that conflate processing with other dietary factors. Implementation challenges extend to socioeconomic accessibility, as UPFs often provide cost-effective nutrients for disadvantaged populations and environmental sustainability, where wholesale reduction could increase resource demands. Future directions should develop more nuanced classification systems that integrate processing methods with nutritional quality to better inform public health strategies rather than categorically rejecting all UPFs.
DOI: 10.1017/s0029665125100645
ISSN: 0029-6651
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1017/s0029665125100645-2025-09-05-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Nutritional Epidemiology Risk–Survival Paradox</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 166
Autoren: Raphael E Cuomo
Journal: The Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020
ISSN: 0022-3166
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.020-2025-09-05-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Low-fat and whole milk consumption in relation to cardiovascular disease–related and all-cause mortality: a prospective cohort study in 3 Norwegian counties</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 131
Autoren: Erik Kristoffer Arnesen, Jacob Juel Christensen, Ida Laake, Monica H Carlsen, Marit B Veierød, Kjetil Retterstøl
Journal: The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035
ISSN: 0002-9165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-05</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.07.035-2025-09-05-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>