<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 01:14:15 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 01:14:15 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Associations between within-day step accumulation pattern and clinical measures of physical function: a change-for-change analysis of longitudinal data in community-dwelling older adults</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-025-01797-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 160
Autoren: Melvyn Hillsdon, Alexander Schoenfelder, Brad Metcalf, Afroditi Stathi, Max J. Western, Joss Langford
Journal: International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-15
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            While daily step count and stepping pace are linked to various health benefits in older adults, less is known about how the pattern of step accumulation affects physical function. For example, the same step count could be accumulated through clusters of frequent, short bouts (e.g., during house cleaning) or fewer, longer bouts (e.g., walking to and from work). This study aimed to explore whether stepping patterns, and trends in these patterns, were associated with physical function in older adults.
          
          
            Methods
            We analysed accelerometer data from wrist-worn GENEActiv devices, from four time points over 24 months in n = 597 older adults (age ≥65 years, 68% female) participating in the REtirement in ACTion intervention. A step counting algorithm was used to create bouts of stepping (at least 10 steps &amp;gt; 20 steps/minute) before counting the steps in each bout and the average cadence. Total daily steps (20–175 steps/minute), slower-paced steps (20–62 steps/minute; below the median cadence), and faster-paced walking steps (63–175 steps/minute; above the median cadence) were then calculated. We used the frequency of stepping bouts, the time between them (mean and standard deviation) and their burstiness (short bursts of stepping bouts clustered together), to examine the daily patterns of step accumulation. Linear mixed-effects models were used to assess trends in stepping variables and their association with changes in objectively measured physical function (short physical performance battery: SPPB) over the two-year period.
          
          
            Results
            Total, slower-paced and faster-paced daily steps declined, along with the average number of stepping bouts. The time between stepping bouts increased. All components of burstiness, but not burstiness itself, were associated with changes in physical function, even when faster and slower steps (total steps) were in the same model (fewer stepping bouts = lower SPPB, greater SD = lower SPPB). Mean time between bouts was the strongest independent predictor, whereby a 10-minute increase in time between bouts was associated with a clinically important 0.46 decline in SPPB score (p &amp;lt; 0.001).
          
          
            Conclusions
            Preventing increases in the time between stepping bouts could help preserve physical function in older adults. Future intervention trials targeting how bouts of stepping are spread throughout the day, rather than just total steps, may provide a more effective approach to promoting healthy physical functioning in older age.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12966-025-01797-6
ISSN: 1479-5868
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-08</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12966-025-01797-6-2025-08-08-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Early meal timing attenuates high polygenic risk of obesity</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.24319</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 110
Autoren: R De la Peña‐Armada, María Rodríguez‐Martín, Hassan S. Dashti, Ana Isabel Cascales, Frank A. J. L. Scheer, Richa Saxena, Marta Garaulet
Journal: Obesity
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-20
Abstract: AbstractObjectiveWe examined whether meal timing is associated with long‐term weight‐loss maintenance and whether meal timing interacts with a genome‐wide polygenic score (PRS‐BMI) on body weight‐related outcomes. We then examined the interaction of meal timing with 97 BMI‐related single‐nucleotide polymorphisms on obesity outcome.MethodsParticipants (N = 1195, mean age 41.07 [SD 12.68] years, female 80.8%, baseline mean BMI 31.32 [SD 5.53] kg/m2) were adults with overweight or obesity from the Obesity, Nutrigenetics, Timing, and Mediterranean (ONTIME) study. We developed a PRS‐BMI to assess the genetic risk for obesity and estimated the timing of the midpoint of meal intake. We also calculated the success in long‐term weight‐loss maintenance after a dietary obesity treatment (at least 3 years). Linear regression analyses were performed for association and interaction assessments.ResultsEach hour of delay in meal timing was associated with 2.2% higher long‐term body weight (β [SE] = 2.177% [1.067%]; p = 0.042) (i.e., with lower weight‐loss maintenance following dietary obesity treatment). There was a significant interaction between meal timing and PRS‐BMI (p = 0.008); BMI increased by more than 2 kg/m2 for every hour of delay in meal timing in individuals with high PRS‐BMI (β [SE] = 2.208 [0.502] kg/m2; p = 1.0E‐5), whereas no associations were evident for those with lower genetic risk.ConclusionsMeal timing is associated with weight‐loss maintenance and may influence the association between obesity genetics and BMI. Findings underscore the importance of personalized obesity management.image
DOI: 10.1002/oby.24319
ISSN: 1930-7381
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-08</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/oby.24319-2025-08-08-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Characterising the diversity of plant-based food and beverage consumption in adults, and exploring associations with cardiometabolic health outcomes: A cross-sectional study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clnu.2025.07.011</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 101
Autoren: Alice C. Creedon, Leah Foyle, Natalie McCall, Mary Gracia Arulpragasam, Rachel Gibson, Eirini Dimidi
Journal: Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.clnu.2025.07.011
ISSN: 0261-5614
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-08</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.clnu.2025.07.011-2025-08-08-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Acute glycaemic response of orange juice consumption with breakfast in individuals with type 2 diabetes: a randomized cross-over trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41387-025-00385-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 56
Autoren: Kenneth Verboven, Lisa Van Ryckeghem, Ralf Schweiggert, Christof B. Steingass, Tin Gojevic, Carrie H. S. Ruxton, Dominique Hansen
Journal: Nutrition &amp;amp; Diabetes
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-09
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background/Objectives
            Sugar-sweetened beverages are associated with an increased risk of obesity and type 2 diabetes (T2DM) and show clear differential metabolic responses compared with 100% fruit juice, which is unsweetened by law. This study investigated whether the postprandial glycaemic response following a standardized breakfast differed when accompanied by 100% orange juice, equivalent whole orange, or a sugar-sweetened control beverage in individuals with well-controlled T2DM.
          
          
            Subjects/Methods
            Fifteen individuals with T2DM (60 ± 6 y; BMI 28.7 ± 5.0 kg/m², HbA1C 49 ± 3 mmol/mol (6.6 ± 0.3%)) participated in this randomized cross-over trial. They consumed a standardized breakfast served with either 250 mL of 100% orange juice, a sugar-sweetened orange-flavoured beverage or whole orange pieces with identical total sugar content. Postprandial glycaemic and insulinaemic responses were checked during 4 h.
          
          
            Results
            Following a single intake, no significant differences were found in acute glucose or insulin responses (expressed as total or incremental area under the curve or peak values; p
              treatment &amp;gt; 0.05, respectively) when either whole orange pieces, orange juice or a sugar-sweetened control beverage were consumed with a standard high carbohydrate meal. Capillary glucose responses did not differ between conditions (p
              treatment &amp;gt; 0.05).
          
          
            Conclusion
            Acute glycaemic control in individuals with well-controlled T2DM is not significantly influenced by serving orange juice, whole orange pieces or a sugar-sweetened beverage with a standard high-carbohydrate meal.
          
DOI: 10.1038/s41387-025-00385-8
ISSN: 2044-4052
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-08</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41387-025-00385-8-2025-08-08-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Food noise: definition, measurement, and future research directions</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41387-025-00382-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 51
Autoren: Emily J. Dhurandhar, Kevin C. Maki, Nikhil V. Dhurandhar, Theodore K. Kyle, Sydney Yurkow, Misty A. W. Hawkins, Jon Agley, Emily H. Ho, Lawrence J. Cheskin, Thorkild I. A. Sørensen, Xi Rita Wang, David B. Allison
Journal: Nutrition &amp;amp; Diabetes
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-08
DOI: 10.1038/s41387-025-00382-x
ISSN: 2044-4052
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-08</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41387-025-00382-x-2025-08-08-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>