<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 01:05:20 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 01:05:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Epstein-Barr virus reprograms autoreactive B cells as antigen-presenting cells in systemic lupus erythematosus</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.ady0210</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 1408
Autoren: Shady Younis, Salvinaz I. Moutusy, Sajede Rasouli, Shaghayegh Jahanbani, Mahesh Pandit, Xiaohao Wu, Suman Acharya, Orr Sharpe, Tilini U. Wijeratne, Marlayna L. Harris, Emily Y. Yang, Yashaar Chaichian, Shima Parsafar, Matthew C. Baker, John B. Harley, Eric Meffre, Lawrence Steinman, Ann Marshak-Rothstein, Judith A. James, Olivia M. Martinez, Paul J. Utz, Dana E. Orange, Tobias V. Lanz, William H. Robinson
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-12
Abstract: 
                    Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a systemic autoimmune disease characterized by antinuclear antibodies (ANAs). Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) infection has been epidemiologically associated with SLE, yet its role in pathogenesis remains incompletely defined. Here, we developed an EBV-specific single-cell RNA-sequencing platform and used it to demonstrate that EBV infection reprograms autoreactive antinuclear antigen B cells to drive autoimmunity in SLE. We demonstrated that, in SLE, EBV
                    +
                    B cells are predominantly CD27
                    +
                    CD21
                    low
                    memory B cells that are present at increased frequencies and express
                    ZEB2
                    ,
                    TBX21
                    (T-bet), and antigen-presenting cell transcriptional pathways. Integrative analysis of chromatin immunoprecipitation sequencing (ChIP-seq), assay for transposase-accessible chromatin sequencing (ATAC-seq), and RNA polymerase II occupancy data revealed EBV nuclear antigen 2 (EBNA2) binding at the transcriptional start sites and regulatory regions of 
                    CD27
                    , 
                    ZEB2
                    , and
                    TBX21
                    , as well as the antigen-presenting cell genes demonstrated to be up-regulated in SLE EBV
                    +
                    B cells. We expressed recombinant antibodies from SLE EBV
                    +
                    B cells and demonstrated that they bind prototypical SLE nuclear autoantigens, whereas those from healthy individuals do not. We further found that SLE EBV
                    +
                    B cells can serve as antigen-presenting cells to drive activation of T peripheral helper cells with concomitant activation of related EBV
                    −
                    antinuclear double-negative 2 B cells and plasmablasts. Our results provide a mechanistic basis for EBV being a driver of SLE through infecting and reprogramming nuclear antigen-reactive B cells to become activated antigen-presenting cells with the potential to promote systemic disease–driving autoimmune responses.
                  
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.ady0210
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.ady0210-2025-11-18-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Physical activity as a modifiable risk factor in preclinical Alzheimer’s disease</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 708
Autoren: Wai-Ying Wendy Yau, Dylan R. Kirn, Jennifer S. Rabin, Michael J. Properzi, Aaron P. Schultz, Zahra Shirzadi, Kailee Palmgren, Paola Matos, Courtney Maa, Jeremy J. Pruzin, Stephanie A. Schultz, Rachel F. Buckley, Dorene M. Rentz, Keith A. Johnson, Reisa A. Sperling, Jasmeer P. Chhatwal
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-03
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03955-6-2025-11-18-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Safety and pharmacokinetics of SARS-CoV-2 DNA-encoded monoclonal antibodies in healthy adults: a phase 1 trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03969-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 327
Autoren: Pablo Tebas, Ami Patel, Joseph T. Agnes, Elizabeth M. Parzych, Amanda Baer, Maria Caturla, Sukanya Ghosh, Mansi Purwar, Nicole Bedanova, Chungdhak Tsang, Knashawn Morales, Dinah Amante, Paul D. Fisher, Joseph R. Francica, Laurent Humeau, Daniel W. Kulp, Jesper Pallesen, Paul Leon, Mark Esser, Trevor R. F. Smith, David B. Weiner
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-21
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03969-0
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03969-0-2025-11-18-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Myelin injury precedes axonal injury and symptomatic onset in multiple sclerosis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-04014-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 324
Autoren: Ahmed Abdelhak, Gabriel Cerono, Fahime Sheikhzadeh, Adil Harroud, Kiarra Ning, Colin R. Zamecnik, Gavin M. Sowa, John Boscardin, Christian Cordano, Asritha Tubati, Camille Fouassier, Eric D. Chow, Refujia Gomez, Adam Santaniello, Kelsey C. Zorn, Jill A. Hollenbach, Jorge R. Oksenberg, Bruce A. C. Cree, Stephen L. Hauser, Jonah R. Chan, Sergio E. Baranzini, Mitchell T. Wallin, Michael R. Wilson, Ari J. Green
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-20
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-04014-w
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-04014-w-2025-11-18-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Plasma proteome adaptations during feminizing gender-affirming hormone therapy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-04023-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 265
Autoren: Nhi N. L. Nguyen, Den Celestra, Lachlan M. Angus, Toby Mansell, Rebecca Shepherd, Bo Won Kim, Bridget Arman, Georgiana Cabau, Tania O. Crișan, Leo A. B. Joosten, Camille Laberthonnière, David Burgner, Gilda Tachedjian, Musa Mhlanga, Rachel A. Davey, Ken C. Pang, Ada S. Cheung, Richard Saffery, Boris Novakovic
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-20
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-04023-9
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-04023-9-2025-11-18-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>