<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 01:06:37 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 01:06:37 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Habitual fluid intake and hydration status influence cortisol reactivity to acute psychosocial stress</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 1311
Autoren: Daniel Sean Kashi, Marianne Hunter, Jason Paul Edwards, Juliane Zemdegs, Jennifer Lourenço, Anne-Cécile Mille, Erica T Perrier, Alberto Dolci, Neil P Walsh
Journal: Journal of Applied Physiology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-13
Abstract:  Shared pathways connect water regulation and cortisol release and exaggerated cortisol reactivity to stress is associated with poor long-term health. This study investigated the unknown influence of habitual fluid intake and hydration status on saliva cortisol reactivity to psychosocial stress. After screening 62 healthy males and females and adopting low and high fluid intake quartiles from a national database, we identified 16 individuals with habitual low (LOW: 1.3 ± 0.4 L/day) and 16 with habitual high fluid intake (HIGH: 4.4 ± 1.2 L/day) who were comparable for factors likely to influence stress reactivity (e.g., trait anxiety). In pairs (one LOW and one HIGH), participants underwent 7 days of monitored habitual fluid intake. The following day, participants individually completed the Trier Social Stress Test (TSST). Hydration status was assessed in the days preceding and on the day of the TSST (urine osmolality and color; UOsm, UCol). Both UOsm and UCol were greater in LOW ( P &amp;lt; 0.001). The TSST evoked similar increases in state anxiety and heart rate in LOW and HIGH, yet saliva cortisol increased significantly post-TSST only in LOW (group*time interaction, P = 0.02). Moreover, cortisol reactivity was greater in LOW (Δ, 6.2 ± 2.9 vs. HIGH: 4.0 ± 1.8 nmol/L; P = 0.03, Cohen’s d = 0.9) and was associated with hydration status assessed as UOsm (Pearson R = 0.7, P &amp;lt; 0.001). These novel findings show greater cortisol reactivity to acute psychosocial stress in adults with habitual low fluid intake and suboptimal hydration, which may influence long-term health. 
DOI: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025
ISSN: 8750-7587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025-2025-08-25-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Exercise based cardiac rehabilitation for atrial fibrillation: Cochrane systematic review, meta-analysis, meta-regression and trial sequential analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2024-109149</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 212
Autoren: Benjamin JR Buckley, Linda Long, Deirdre A Lane, Signe Risom, Charlotte Jane Fitzhugh, Selina K Berg, Pernille Palm, Kirstine L Sibilitz, Jesper H Svendsen, Christian Gluud, Ann-Dorthe Zwisler, Gregory Y H Lip, Lis Neubeck, Rod S Taylor
Journal: British Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-29
Abstract: 
                  Objective
                  To undertake a contemporary review of the impact of exercise based cardiac rehabilitation (ExCR) for patients with atrial fibrillation (AF).
               
               
                  Data sources
                  CENTRAL, MEDLINE, Embase, PsycINFO, CINAHL, WoS Core Collection, LILACS and trial registers were searched from inception up to 24 March 2024.
               
               
                  Eligibility criteria
                  Randomised clinical trials (RCTs) comparing ExCR with any non-exercise control.
               
               
                  Design
                  Random effect meta-analyses presented as effect estimates and 95% CIs. Meta-regression examined study level effect modification. Cochrane risk of bias, GRADE (Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development and Evaluation) and trial sequential analysis (RTSA) were applied.
               
               
                  Results
                  20 RCTs (n=2039) with a mean follow-up of 11 months showed that ExCR did not impact all cause mortality (8.3% vs 6.0%, relative risk (RR) 1.06, 95% CI 0.76 to 1.48) or serious adverse events (2.9% vs 4.1%, RR 1.30, 95% CI 0.66 to 2.56) but did reduce AF symptom severity (mean difference (MD) −1.61, 95% CI −3.06 to −0.16), AF burden (MD −1.61, 95% CI −2.76 to −0.45), episode frequency (MD −0.57, 95% CI −1.07 to −0.07), episode duration (MD −0.58, 95% CI −1.14 to −0.03), AF recurrence (RR 0.68, 95% CI 0.53 to 0.89), and improved exercise capacity (maximal oxygen consumption (VO2 peak) MD 3.18, 95% CI 1.05 to 5.31 mL/kg/min). There was benefit for the mental component but not the physical component of a health related quality of life questionnaire. No differential effects across AF subtype, ExCR dose, or mode of delivery were seen.
               
               
                  Conclusion
                  Meta-analyses of RCT evidence for ExCR in patients with AF demonstrated several clinical benefits without an increase in serious adverse events. GRADE and RTSA assessments indicated further high quality and adequately powered RCTs are needed.
               
DOI: 10.1136/bjsports-2024-109149
ISSN: 0306-3674
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bjsports-2024-109149-2025-08-25-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Role of exercise in atrial fibrillation management</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2025-110191</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 110
Autoren: Sarandeep Marwaha, Sanjay Sharma
Journal: British Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-29
DOI: 10.1136/bjsports-2025-110191
ISSN: 0306-3674
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bjsports-2025-110191-2025-08-25-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Sex Differences in Disc Golf Performance: Implications for Eligibility Criteria for Women's Competitions</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/ejsc.70008</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 49
Autoren: Tommy R. Lundberg, Justin Menickelli
Journal: European Journal of Sport Science
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-25
Abstract: ABSTRACTDisc golf is becoming increasingly popular, but there is no published information on performance differences between males and females. The aim of this study was to investigate sex differences in disc golf performance in recent years and to discuss the implications of these sex differences on eligibility criteria for women's disc golf competitions. We used publicly available data sources from the Professional Disc Golf Association (PDGA) and Disc Golf Pro Tour (DGPT) to compile performance data related to player ratings, throwing distance, throwing accuracy, and putting success at the professional, amateur, and junior levels. In the Pro class (n = 16,843), the median male player rating was 936 compared with 851 for females (P &amp;lt; 0.001). In the amateurs, over 5000 males had a higher rating than the best female player. In throwing for distance, males threw 23%–54% further than females (P &amp;lt; 0.001). Differences in accuracy were smaller but significant, with males outperforming females in measures of throwing accuracy in the Pro class (average 70.9% vs. 63.4% fairway hits; P &amp;lt; 0.001) and putting consistency (median 82% vs. 69%; P &amp;lt; 0.001). In junior competitions, boys showed higher ratings and better performance than girls, with clear differences already observed at age 10 (e.g., median rating 775 vs. 529; P &amp;lt; 0.001). In conclusion, male disc golfers outperformed female players in player rating, throwing distance, and accuracy in the professional, amateur, and junior divisions. Disc golf governing bodies struggling with setting eligibility criteria for women's disc golf competitions may use these results to better inform policy.
DOI: 10.1002/ejsc.70008
ISSN: 1746-1391
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/ejsc.70008-2025-08-25-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Creatine monohydrate supplementation for older adults and clinical populations</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/15502783.2025.2534130</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 38
Autoren: Darren G. Candow, Sergej M. Ostojic, Philip D. Chilibeck, Igor Longobardi, Bruno Gualano, Mark A. Tarnopolsky, Theo Wallimann, Terence Moriarty, Richard B. Kreider, Scott C. Forbes, Uwe Schlattner, Jose Antonio
Journal: Journal of the International Society of Sports Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-17
DOI: 10.1080/15502783.2025.2534130
ISSN: 1550-2783
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/15502783.2025.2534130-2025-08-25-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>