<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 01:07:26 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 01:07:26 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Systematic review of clinical practice guidelines on acupuncture for chronic musculoskeletal pain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Leonard Ho, Cyrus Ngo Tin Lai, Haiyong Chen, Sheung Wai Law, Edwin Chau Leung Yu, Fiona Pui Yan Lam, Yi Chung Cheung, Irene Xinyin Wu, Samuel Yeung Shan Wong, Regina Wing Shan Sit
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Introduction
            Acupuncture is increasingly utilised in primary care to manage chronic musculoskeletal pain, supported by a growing body of evidence. This rising adoption has driven demand for clinical practice guidelines (CPGs). We summarised the characteristics of recent acupuncture CPGs for osteoarthritis, low back pain, neck pain, and shoulder pain, and critically appraised their methodological quality.
          
          
            Methods
            We searched nine databases to identify acupuncture CPGs published from January 2014 to November 2024. Eligible CPGs were required to be developed by guideline committees and to include evidence-informed recommendations linked to clearly defined levels of evidence. Two independent reviewers extracted CPG characteristics and assessed methodological quality using the Appraisal of Guidelines for Research and Evaluation II (AGREE II) instrument.
          
          
            Results
            Of the 1,999 records screened, 17 CPGs were included, encompassing 35 recommendations. Shoulder pain was the most addressed condition (n = 14), followed by low back pain (n = 11), osteoarthritis (n = 8), and neck pain (n = 2). Various types of acupuncture were considered, with manual acupuncture featuring in most (n = 26) recommendations. Overall, 60% of the recommendations supported the use of acupuncture, comprising 5.7% strong recommendations and 54.3% weak or conditional recommendations. In contrast, 22.9% of recommendations offered no explicit guidance, while 17.1% advised against its use. Methodological assessment classified 10 CPGs as high quality, while seven were of moderate quality.
          
          
            Conclusions
            Contradictions exist among the included CPGs regarding whether acupuncture should be recommended for routine practice, potentially reflecting differences in clinical and cultural contexts. Local CPGs should be developed using rigorous methodology, ensuring the involvement of local stakeholders. An AGREE II extension should be developed for the methodological quality assessment of acupuncture CPGs.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05070-y-2025-10-01-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Baseline individual factors associated with clinical outcomes in adults with non-specific low back pain following manual therapy: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Gaetan Barbier, Mathieu Picchiottino, Arnaud Delafontaine, Guillaume Goncalves, André Bussières, François Cottin, Arnaud Lardon
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y-2025-10-01-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>TriCAM (NCT02976558) – a randomized controlled pilot study of complementary medicine in allogeneic stem cell transplantation to improve quality of life</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05058-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Ali Behzad, Stefan W. Krause, Andreas Mackensen, Fabian Müller, Anja Stark, Simon Völkl, Wolf Rösler
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-08
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05058-8
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05058-8-2025-10-01-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Differential placebo effect of sham acupuncture for chronic pain: a network meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05055-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Renhong Wan, Qianhua Zheng, Xiaorui Zeng, Yalan Luo, Luqiang Sun, Shuai Chen, Fangli Luo, Yupeng Zhang, Ziyue Zhu, Xinyun Chen, Yuanyuan Zhao, Ying Li
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05055-x
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05055-x-2025-10-01-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Comprehensive Network pharmacology and in vitro investigation of L-mimosine: unveiling multi-targeted therapeutic potential against breast cancer</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04905-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Jyoti Kumari Yadav, Krupa Shah, Mohammadfesal Ghanchi, Gaurang sindhav, Saumya Patel, Rakesh Rawal
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04905-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-01</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04905-y-2025-10-01-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>