<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 01:04:49 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 01:04:49 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Deaths following illicit ketamine use in England, Wales and Northern Ireland 1999–2024: An update report to inform the reclassification debate</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/02698811251373058</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 377
Autoren: Jade Pullen, John M. Corkery, Rebecca McKnight, Caroline S. Copeland
Journal: Journal of Psychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-29
Abstract: 
            Background:
            Ketamine is increasingly used in the United Kingdom in non-clinical settings for its psychoactive effects, with rising reports of harms including hospital admissions, dependence and deaths. In light of current debates surrounding the reclassification of ketamine under the Misuse of Drugs Act 1971, up-to-date surveillance of associated mortality is warranted.
          
          
            Aims:
            We aimed to quantify trends in deaths following illicit ketamine use in England, Wales and Northern Ireland, and to examine changes in demographic and contextual characteristics since the last national analysis which comprised illicit ketamine deaths up to 2019.
          
          
            Methods:
            Cases where illicit ketamine was detected at post-mortem were extracted from the National Programme on Substance Use Mortality and analysed.
          
          
            Results:
            There were 696 deaths identified with illicit ketamine between 1999 and 2024. Annual deaths increased over 10-fold from 2014 (15 deaths) to 2024 (197 projected deaths). Whilst absolute deaths implicating illicit ketamine rose (2014: 6 deaths; 2023: 123 projected deaths), the proportion of deaths where illicit ketamine was implicated in causing death declined (2014: 60.0% of cases; 2024: 42.6% of cases). Concurrently, polydrug use increased (median number of co-administered substances 1999–2004: 3; 2005–2009: 3, 2010–2014: 4, 2015–2019: 6; 2020–2024: 6), and the demographic profile of decedents shifted towards greater deprivation and dependence-related contexts.
          
          
            Discussion and Conclusions:
            There has been an acceleration in deaths following illicit ketamine in recent years, which are increasingly featuring complex patterns of polydrug use and socio-economic vulnerability. Policy responses must extend beyond single-substance legislative controls to encompass harm reduction, treatment integration, and social support strategies.
          
DOI: 10.1177/02698811251373058
ISSN: 0269-8811
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/02698811251373058-2025-10-22-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mass balance, pharmacokinetics, metabolism, and excretion of radiolabeled acoziborole, a potential novel treatment for human African trypanosomiasis, following single microtracer oral dose to humans</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.00580-25</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 144
Autoren: Jean-Yves Gillon, François Simon, Sharan Sidhu, Mathieu Louis, Delphine Launay, Valérie Wauthier, Marta Pelay-Gimeno, Lotte van Andel, Sabrina Loyau, Sandra Rembry, Estelle Weinling, Antoine Tarral
Journal: Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-22
Abstract: ABSTRACT
          
            
            
              Acoziborole is an oxaborole 6-carboxamide active against
              Trypanosoma brucei gambiense
              and
              rhodesiense
              , the parasites responsible for human African trypanosomiasis. This open-label, phase I study in six healthy male participants evaluated the mass balance, pharmacokinetics, metabolism pathways, and excretion of a single oral 960 mg dose of [
              14
              C]-acoziborole. Blood, plasma, and feces were collected for 120 days and urine for 16 days. The excretion balance and systemic exposure of total circulating radioactivity were determined using accelerator mass spectrometry. Metabolism profiling was performed in pools of plasma, urine, and feces. Liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry quantified acoziborole and its metabolite SCYX-3109 in plasma and urine. By Day 60, 87.3% of the total radioactivity had been recovered (10.9% and 74.2% of the total dose in urine and in feces, respectively), with an excretion increment of &amp;lt;1% between Days 59 and 61. Mean ratios of total radioactivity indicated an equivalent distribution between blood cells and plasma. The concentration-time profiles of total radioactivity and acoziborole in plasma were similar. In plasma, acoziborole accounted for 95.1%, an oxidized form of acoziborole for 2.3% of the total radioactivity, while SCYX-3109 was not detected. Seven metabolites (oxidative deboronation, glucuronidation, and mono-oxidation) were detected in urine with individual abundances relative to the dose of 0.1–2.1%; unchanged acoziborole accounted for 0.6%. In feces, acoziborole, SCYX-3109, and two other oxidized or deboronated forms of acoziborole represented 33.6%, 12.3%, and 2.3% of the dose, respectively. Acoziborole showed good absorption, limited metabolism, minimal urinary elimination, and predominant but slow biliary-fecal elimination.
            
          
DOI: 10.1128/aac.00580-25
ISSN: 0066-4804
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1128/aac.00580-25-2025-10-22-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>In vivo chimeric antigen receptor (CAR)-T cell therapy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41573-025-01291-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 84
Autoren: Adrian Bot, Andrew Scharenberg, Kevin Friedman, Lin Guey, Robert Hofmeister, James I. Andorko, Michael Klichinsky, Frank Neumann, Jagesh V. Shah, Andrew J. Swayer, Kyle Trudeau, Drew Weissman, Matthias T. Stephan, Christian J. Buchholz, Carl H. June
Journal: Nature Reviews Drug Discovery
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-30
DOI: 10.1038/s41573-025-01291-5
ISSN: 1474-1776
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41573-025-01291-5-2025-10-22-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Population Pharmacokinetic Modeling and Pediatric Exposure of Dexamethasone Sodium Phosphate Encapsulated in Erythrocytes (eDSP) Administered Monthly for Treatment of Neurological Symptoms of Patients With Ataxia Telangiectasia</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/psp4.70103</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 64
Autoren: Deniz Ozdin, Leila Kheibarshekan, Giovanni Mambrini, Pierre‐Olivier Tremblay
Journal: CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp;amp; Systems Pharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-22
Abstract: ABSTRACTThe EryDex System (EDS) is a drug/device combination, which has been tested in clinical trials for ataxia telangiectasia (AT). EDS encapsulates dexamethasone sodium phosphate (DSP) solution in autologous erythrocytes at the point of care, and encapsulated DSP (eDSP) is infused back into the patient. Low doses of dexamethasone are released from erythrocytes over a 30‐day period. This study aimed to (1) characterize the pharmacokinetics (PK) of dexamethasone released from intravenously infused eDSP based on data collected in clinical trials of healthy adults and pediatric AT patients, and to (2) simulate and extrapolate exposure measures of dexamethasone following intravenous infusion of eDSP administered once per month over 6 months in a pediatric population. The population PK model was developed using dense PK data from a phase 1 study in healthy adults and sparse PK data from a phase 3 study in pediatric AT patients. Three dose levels were studied, and the overall PK population included 24 healthy adults and 109 AT patients. The PK of dexamethasone released from eDSP was described using a simplified two‐compartment model, adequate for estimating systemic exposure despite not fully capturing RBC release kinetics indicative of a triphasic pattern. The model showed a good fit, and future refinement will include mechanistic release modeling as more in vitro and in vivo data become available. Monte Carlo simulations of eDSP showed a rapid peak at 0.67 h, followed by sustained dexamethasone release; faster in the first 24 h, then slower over 20–30 days. No accumulation occurred with once‐monthly dosing.
DOI: 10.1002/psp4.70103
ISSN: 2163-8306
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/psp4.70103-2025-10-22-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Clinical Efficacy, Safety and Imaging Effects of Oral Valiltramiprosate in APOEε4/ε4 Homozygotes with Early Alzheimer’s Disease: Results of the Phase III, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, 78-Week APOLLOE4 Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s40265-025-02250-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 56
Autoren: Susan Abushakra, Aidan Power, David Watson, Anton Porsteinsson, Marwan Sabbagh, Emer MacSweeney, Sharon Cohen, Mercè Boada Rovira, P. Murali Doraiswamy, Earvin Liang, Susan Flint, J. Patrick Kesslak, Rosalind McLaine, Adem Albayrak, Jean Schaefer, Jeremy Yu, Luke Tolar, Sam Dickson, John A. Hey, Martin Tolar
Journal: Drugs
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-28
DOI: 10.1007/s40265-025-02250-5
ISSN: 0012-6667
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-22</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s40265-025-02250-5-2025-10-22-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>