<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 01:10:04 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 01:10:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Lacto-ovo-vegetarian and vegan diets in children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analysis of nutritional and health outcomes</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2025.2572983</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 333
Autoren: Sofia Lotti, Giona Panizza, Daniela Martini, Wolfgang Marx, Jeannette M. Beasley, Barbara Colombini, Monica Dinu
Journal: Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-11
DOI: 10.1080/10408398.2025.2572983
ISSN: 1040-8398
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/10408398.2025.2572983-2026-01-10-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Vegetarian diet and likelihood of becoming centenarians in Chinese adults aged 80 y or older: a nested case-control study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.101136</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 97
Autoren: Yaqi Li, Kaiyue Wang, Yuebin Lv, Guliyeerke Jigeer, Yilun Huang, Xiuhua Shen, Xiaoming Shi, Xiang Gao
Journal: The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.101136
ISSN: 0002-9165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.101136-2026-01-10-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Carbohydrate Reduction and a Holistic Model of Care in Diabetes Management: Insights from a Retrospective Multi-Year Audit in New Zealand</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17243953</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 65
Autoren: Caryn Zinn, Jessica L. Campbell, Lily Fraser, Glen Davies, Marcus Hawkins, Olivia Currie, Jared Cannons, David Unwin, Catherine Crofts, Tom Stewart, Grant Schofield
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-17
Abstract: Background/Objectives: The global epidemic of type 2 diabetes (T2D) is a critical public health issue, particularly in New Zealand, where prevalence rates are high, especially among Māori and Pacific people. Recent research indicates that dietary interventions, particularly carbohydrate reduction, can lead to the remission or reversal of T2D. However, little is known about how such approaches perform when implemented in routine New Zealand primary care, particularly within high-risk and underserved populations. This study aimed to evaluate changes in HbA1c, diabetes status, and cardiometabolic outcomes among adults with prediabetes and T2D engaged in such a model of care. Methods: This study reports findings from a retrospective, observational, real-world, multi-site clinical audit (service evaluation) of a holistic model of care implemented in three primary care practices in New Zealand. The model of care is characterised by a three-pronged approach: whole food, carbohydrate reduction; a health-coach, behaviour-change-based delivery approach; and community- or peer-based initiatives. Audit data from 106 patients with prediabetes (PD) and T2D were analysed (median follow-up 19 months; IQR 6–32) to assess changes in glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c) levels, diabetes status, and cardiometabolic outcomes. Results: We observed an overall reduction in HbA1c (median change −3 mmol/mol (IQR: −7 to 3), p = 0.004), with 32% of patients with T2D at baseline achieving reversal and 44% of those with PD attaining normoglycaemia at final follow-up. Weight loss was associated with greater HbA1c reduction (0.56 mmol/mol decrease per kg lost) and additional improvements seen in lowered alanine aminotransferase (ALT). HDL cholesterol showed a small decline (r = 0.31), and triglycerides and blood pressure showed no significant change, indicating that these measures remained broadly stable over the evaluation period. Conclusions: Given the retrospective and uncontrolled audit design, findings should be interpreted with appropriate caution. However, the consistent improvements observed across multiple practices suggest that carbohydrate-reduction strategies within holistic models of care can meaningfully improve diabetes outcomes in real-world primary care settings. Future research should evaluate longer-term sustainability, implementation fidelity, and the applicability of this model at scale, particularly for Māori and Pacific communities.
DOI: 10.3390/nu17243953
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu17243953-2026-01-10-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Effects of Kefir on the Human Oral and Gut Microbiome</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17243861</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 61
Autoren: Eleni Grace Black, Andrea Bugarcic, Romy Lauche, Emad El-Omar, Fatima El-Assaad
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-11
Abstract: Kefir, a fermented probiotic drink made from milk, water, or plant-based ingredients, has gained significant attention as a dietary supplement. Originating from the Caucasus Mountains over three thousand years ago, kefir is believed to harbor a range of health benefits through its ability to alter the composition of microbial niches within the human body. These microbial niches are called microbiomes and encompass the collective community of microbial organisms, their genomes and environment. The modern commercialization of kefir has driven the need for high-quality research into its impact on the human microbiome and associated health outcomes; however, there is currently very limited scientific evidence supporting effects of kefir consumption on the human oral and gut microbiome. High-quality human clinical trials are essential to establish the safety and effectiveness of kefir before it can be advised for use in treating conditions linked to the oral and gut microbiota or metabolic health. This literature review aims to critically analyze recent studies investigating the effect of kefir consumption on the oral and gut microbiome, as well as its potential implications for human health. By examining kefir’s effects on these interconnected microbial ecosystems, we can better understand its potential and limitations as a functional food for promoting systemic health.
DOI: 10.3390/nu17243861
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu17243861-2026-01-10-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Ultra-Processed Foods and Inflammatory Bowel Disease: A Narrative Review of Epidemiology, Mechanisms, and Dietary Implications</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17243852</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 56
Autoren: So Yoon Choi, Won Moon
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-10
Abstract: Ultra-processed foods (UPFs), industrial formulations rich in refined substrates and additives, have been increasingly examined as plausible contributors to gut dysbiosis and mucosal inflammation relevant to inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). This narrative review synthesizes epidemiological, mechanistic, and interventional evidence on UPF intake and IBD based on a structured literature search from 2010 to 2025. Large-scale prospective cohorts consistently associate higher UPF intake with increased risk of Crohn’s disease (CD), whereas findings for ulcerative colitis (UC) remain weaker or inconsistent. Among individuals with established IBD, observational data suggest that greater UPF consumption correlates with higher disease activity and relapse, although potential confounding and reverse causation must be considered. Preclinical studies demonstrate that specific UPF constituents—including emulsifiers, carrageenan, maltodextrin, microparticles, and excess dietary salt—can disrupt epithelial barrier integrity, alter the gut microbiota, and activate immune pathways, providing biological plausibility while underscoring translational gaps. Interventional evidence, particularly for exclusive enteral nutrition and the Crohn’s Disease Exclusion Diet, suggests clinical benefit from reducing UPFs or selected additives, mainly in CD, though data in adults and UC remain limited. Overall, current evidence indicates that dietary strategies to limit UPF exposure may represent a promising and modifiable component of IBD management. Future research should prioritize standardized exposure assessment, mechanism-based human trials, and personalized nutrition approaches to refine clinical applicability.
DOI: 10.3390/nu17243852
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu17243852-2026-01-10-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>