<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Sport Sciences) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 01:06:03 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 01:06:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Habitual fluid intake and hydration status influence cortisol reactivity to acute psychosocial stress</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 2084
Autoren: Daniel S. Kashi, Marianne Hunter, Jason P. Edwards, Juliane Zemdegs, Jennifer Lourenço, Anne-Cécile Mille, Erica T. Perrier, Alberto Dolci, Neil P. Walsh
Journal: Journal of Applied Physiology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract:  Cortisol reactivity to acute stress predicts long-term health. Our novel findings show greater cortisol reactivity to acute stress in adults with habitual low fluid intake. Suboptimal hydration (e.g., darker morning urine) was associated with greater cortisol reactivity to acute stress. These findings provide one possible explanation for why habitual low fluid intake and suboptimal hydration are related to poor long-term health. Furthermore, researchers should account for hydration when assessing cortisol reactivity to acute stressors. 
DOI: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025
ISSN: 8750-7587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1152/japplphysiol.00408.2025-2025-10-13-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of exercise snacks on fitness and cardiometabolic health in physically inactive individuals: systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2025-110027</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 539
Autoren: Miguel Ángel Rodríguez, Marcos Quintana-Cepedal, Boris Cheval, Cecilie Thøgersen-Ntoumani, Irene Crespo, Hugo Olmedillas
Journal: British Journal of Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-07
Abstract: 
                  Objectives
                  To evaluate the effects of brief bouts of exercise spread throughout the day, termed ‘exercise snacks’, on cardiorespiratory and muscular fitness, and cardiometabolic health outcomes in physically inactive adults and older adults (aged ≥65 years).
               
               
                  Design
                  Systematic review and meta-analysis.
               
               
                  Data sources
                  Seven databases were searched from inception to April 2025.
               
               
                  Eligibility criteria
                  Randomised controlled trials (RCTs) of adults and older adults, comparing exercise snacks with non-exercising controls.
               
               
                  Results
                  11 RCTs (n=414; 69.1% women, mean age 18.7±0.8 to 74.2±5.6 years) were included. Exercise snacks were defined as structured bouts lasting ≤5 min, performed at least twice daily, ≥3 times/week, for ≥2 weeks. The interventions varied in duration (4–12 weeks), frequency (3–7 days/week) and intensity (moderate-to-vigorous to near-maximal). Exercise snacks significantly improved cardiorespiratory fitness in adults (g=1.37, 95% CI 0.58 to 2.17; p&amp;lt;0.005; I2=71.4 %, k=6) and muscular endurance in older adults (g=0.40, 95% CI 0.06 to 0.75; p=0.02; I2=0 %, k=4), with moderate and very low certainty of evidence, respectively. No significant effects were observed for lower limb muscular strength or cardiometabolic outcomes, including body composition, blood pressure and blood lipid profiles. High compliance (91.1%) and adherence (82.8%) rates were observed.
               
               
                  Conclusions
                  Moderate certainty of evidence indicated that exercise snacks improved cardiorespiratory fitness in physically inactive adults. However, evidence for benefits on muscular endurance in older adults was limited, and the current data do not support their effectiveness for improving other cardiometabolic health markers.
               
               
                  PROSPERO registration number
                  CRD42024616514.
               
DOI: 10.1136/bjsports-2025-110027
ISSN: 0306-3674
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bjsports-2025-110027-2025-10-13-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Trans* Athletes in Sport: Not Ceding to the Sex/Gender Binary of Gender Critical Feminism1</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1123/ssj.2024-0030</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 145
Autoren: Michael Burke, Matthew Klugman
Journal: Sociology of Sport Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
Abstract: Debates over the position(ing) of trans* athletes in sport have been reignited in the last decade because of the confluence of broader political debates over the provision of rights of self-identification for trans* people with the International Olympic Committee’s decision to place responsibility for transgender regulations in the hands of international sporting federations. The effect of this confluence has meant a regressive shift back toward hard essentialism with regard to sex categories in sport. This paper challenges the politically powerful, yet romanticized and historically inaccurate, narrative that so-called gender critical feminists have produced to support this regressive move.
DOI: 10.1123/ssj.2024-0030
ISSN: 0741-1235
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1123/ssj.2024-0030-2025-10-13-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Isolated and Combined Effects of Cold, Heat and Hypoxia Therapies on Muscle Recovery Following Exercise-Induced Muscle Damage</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s40279-025-02300-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 63
Autoren: Yohan Rousse, Benoit Sautillet, Guillaume Costalat, Franck Brocherie, Grégoire P. Millet
Journal: Sports Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-22
Abstract: Abstract
          The optimisation of muscle recovery from exercise-induced muscle damage (EIMD) is a major issue in sports medicine. This comprehensive review examines the effects of four environmental stressors, including cold (cold therapy), heat (heat therapy), hot–cold alternation (contrast therapy) and reduced oxygen availability (hypoxia therapy), on muscle recovery following EIMD. The analysis of related randomised controlled trials assessed the influences of these stressors on five markers of recovery (muscular performance, joint amplitude, muscle pain, swelling and blood biomarkers). Although cold therapy has been widely studied, the lack of consensus on its application modalities leads to controversial debates regarding its effectiveness for muscle recovery. Heat therapy, particularly hot water immersion, appears to be the most effective method for restoring muscle function. However, the use of local heating techniques is less well understood. Moreover, contrast therapy seems to be promising for reducing swelling post-EIMD; however, the lack of studies and the variety of utilised techniques involving contrast therapy limit conclusions. Finally, local hypoxia, which is elicited by intermittent blood flow restriction, demonstrates potential for reducing inflammation and improving the recovery of muscle function, based on the appropriate application of protocols. By synthesising existing data, this comprehensive review shows that most environmental stress-based therapies can be effective, if the modalities of application—such as dose or frequency—are appropriate. It offers practical recommendations for optimising muscle recovery. This review also highlights the need for further research to refine protocols and better understand the potential synergistic effects of these environmental stress-based interventions.
DOI: 10.1007/s40279-025-02300-8
ISSN: 0112-1642
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s40279-025-02300-8-2025-10-13-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Timed Up-and-Go Test with an Obstacle: Evaluating Anticipatory Locomotor Adjustments in Older Adults</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1080/00222895.2025.2559971</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Sport Sciences
Score: 59
Autoren: Juntaro Sakazaki, Takahito Nakamura, Kentaro Kodama, Takahiro Higuchi
Journal: Journal of Motor Behavior
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-25
DOI: 10.1080/00222895.2025.2559971
ISSN: 0022-2895
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1080/00222895.2025.2559971-2025-10-13-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>