<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 01:02:15 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 01:02:15 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Baseline individual factors associated with clinical outcomes in adults with non-specific low back pain following manual therapy: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Gaetan Barbier, Mathieu Picchiottino, Arnaud Delafontaine, Guillaume Goncalves, André Bussières, François Cottin, Arnaud Lardon
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04975-y-2025-10-15-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Antimalarial potential of Matricaria chamomilla-derived MgO nanoparticles against Plasmodium falciparum strains: an experimental study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05081-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Zahra Farzaneh, Haleh Hanifian, Mehdi Nateghpour, Gholamreza Hasanpour, Ahmad Raeisi, Mohammad Shabani, Leila Farivar, Aram Khezri, S. Ahmad Dehdast, Saeed Shahsavari
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-08
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05081-9
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05081-9-2025-10-15-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Chitosan nanocarriers loaded with Egyptian Calligonum comosum L'Hér. Extract: an eco-friendly approach for investigating triple-action biological activities</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Yasser I. Khedr, Soliman M. Toto, Salama M. El-Darier, Mostafa K. Hafez, Abdel-Hamid A. Sakr, Magdi A. Ali, Mohamed Zakaria El-Sayed, Aya M. Helal
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-24
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            
              Calligonum comosum L’Hér. is a large perennial shrub that grows in the desert. This plant inhabits much of the Egyptian desert, but has not yet been scientifically validated. Herein, we demonstrate the antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, and anticancer properties of the ethanolic extract of the Egyptian C. comosum (CE) and its novel eco-friendly chitosan nano-formula (CE/CsNPs), which is prepared using citrate as a crosslinker.
          
          
            Methods
            The produced plant ethanolic extract (CE) was chemically analyzed. The eco-friendly CE/CsNPs were successfully developed through the conjugation of CE with different concentrations (200, 350, and 400 mg/100 mL) within the chitosan nanoparticle; then, it was fully characterized for the determination of the optimum formula and followed by the assessment of the antioxidant effects, proinflammatory cytokines, evaluation of cytotoxicity against different types of cancer cell lines, and estimation of antimicrobial effects of CE and CE/CsNPs.
          
          
            Results
            The eco-friendly CE/CsNPs-2 encapsulating 350 mg of CE was selected for the in vitro studies, as it displayed NPs with a small size and a surface charge of 37.7 ± 1.91 mV with the best encapsulation efficiency (70.15 ± 1.58%) within the CsNPs, and it showed a good release profile. Transmission electron microscope (TEM) images confirmed the discrete spherical shape of CE/CsNPs-2, with no aggregations, and revealed a size range of 49.69 to 71.93 nm. FTIR displayed the successful incorporation of CE into the eco-friendly CsNPs. Regarding their biological activity, CE/CsNPs have superior efficacy with high cytotoxicity against cancer cell lines and antioxidant effects. RT-qPCR gene expression assessments displayed that CE/CsNPs resulted in a remarkable downregulation of the inflammatory cytokines’ mRNA transcript levels (p &amp;lt; 0.05). It enhanced the antimicrobial effect, with an inhibition zone of 12.34 ± 0.75 mm for Escherichia coli, 16.41 ± 1.01 mm for Staphylococcus aureus, and 18.74 ± 1.13 mm for Candida albicans.
          
          
            Conclusions
            The CE possesses various biological activities, and the developed CE/CsNPs could serve as an appealing formulation to be further investigated for use in anticancer regimens.
          
          
            Graphical Abstract
            Synthesis of eco-friendly chitosan nanoparticles loaded with ethanolic extract of C. comosum (CE/CsNPs) by using citrate as an organic cross-linker. The optimum CE/CsNPs formulation loaded with 350 mg/100 mL of the extract with the highest entrapment efficiency (EE)% is a promising anticancer candidate, displaying anticancer, antioxidant, and antimicrobial in vitro potencies.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05047-x-2025-10-15-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effects of manual diaphragm release on pain, disability and diaphragm function in patients with chronic neck pain: a pilot randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05090-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Kai-Chia Cheng, Everlynn Yi Xuan Hii, Yao-Nan Lin, Yi-Liang Kuo, Yi-Ju Tsai
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Chronic neck pain (CNP) is a prevalent musculoskeletal problem associated with impaired cervical functions, faulty breathing patterns, and declined respiratory functions. Diaphragm is a critical respiratory muscle and also connects to cervical spine through different fascial connections. However, the effects of diaphragm manual release (DMR) on CNP remain unknown. Therefore, the present study aimed to investigate the effects of DMR intervention on pain, disability, and diaphragm function in people with CNP.
          
          
            Methods
            A total of 33 participants with CNP were randomized into the DMR and sham release group (SG), and received the allocated intervention twice a week for 2 weeks. The DMR group received a firm pressure release technique at the 7th to 10th subcostal region along with deep breathing, while the SG group received the same technique with light touch instead. Primary outcomes including pain, disability, and diaphragm function, and secondary outcomes including neck range of motions, strength, and chest expansion were performed before and after the intervention for all participants.
          
          
            Results
            After receiving 4 sessions of intervention, the DMR group demonstrated clinically significant improvements in pain and cervical range of motion, along with potential clinically improvements in diaphragm mobility. In the SG group, only pain showed a clinical significant improvement. Cervical strength and chest expansions showed potential clinical improvements in both groups.
          
          
            Conclusion
            The current results provide preliminary evidence that the DMR shows promise as an intervention for improving pain, cervical range of motion, and potentially diaphragm mobility, cervical strength, and chest expansion in patients with CNP. However, its effects may not be clearly superior to sham intervention after 4 sessions. Future studies with larger sample sizes and longer durations are required to confirm its efficacy and establish its role in CNP management.
          
          
            Trial registration
            The study was registered with ClinicalTrial.gov (NCT04664842) on 11/12/2020.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05090-8
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05090-8-2025-10-15-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Synergistic overcoming of cisplatin resistance in ovarian cancer by combined Astragalus Membranaceus and cisplatin treatment: network pharmacology and experimental validation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05066-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Fei Wang, Qing-fang Yue, Yu Zhang, Fang-liang Lei
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-30
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05066-8
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05066-8-2025-10-15-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>