<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 01:08:34 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 01:08:34 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Mobilization with movement plus exercise versus exercise alone for patients with central sensitization associated with chronic subacromial pain syndrome: a sham-controlled randomized clinical trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 13
Autoren: Volkan Deniz, Bayram Kelle
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-28
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05028-0-2025-08-15-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Microbiological Risk Assessment and Safety Evaluation of Widely Used Herbal Pharmaceuticals</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 13
Autoren: Naveen Kumar Ramachandrappa, Kalyan Dola, Vakdevi Validandi, Senthilkumar Balakrishnan, Philip Raj Abraham, Aditi Ashutosh Kaledhonkar, SDG Gauthami, K Srinivasu, Surekha Mullapudi Venkata
Journal: Journal of Herbal Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047
ISSN: 2210-8033
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047-2025-08-15-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Regulatory mechanisms of hepatocyte PCSK9 expression: translating mechanistic insights into potential nutraceuticals</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13020-025-01178-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 8
Autoren: Seon Kyeong Park, Jin-Taek Hwang, Hyo-Kyoung Choi, Jangho Lee
Journal: Chinese Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-05
Abstract: Abstract
          Proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (PCSK9) is a critical regulator of cholesterol metabolism in hepatocytes with profound implications for cardiovascular health. This review explores the intricate regulatory network that controls hepatic PCSK9 expression and explores how these molecular insights can be translated into nutraceutical applications. The precise control of PCSK9 involves complex interactions among transcription factors, signaling pathways, epigenetic modifications, and post-transcriptional mechanisms. Although pharmaceutical PCSK9 inhibitors demonstrated remarkable efficacy, their high cost has stimulated interest in natural alternatives. Bioactive compounds such as berberine, piceatannol, gallic acid, and organosulfur derivatives from garlic have demonstrated the ability to modulate PCSK9 expression through diverse mechanisms, often targeting the same molecular pathways as conventional drugs. These nutraceuticals not only inhibit PCSK9 but also enhance the expression and activity of the low-density lipoprotein receptor, offering a promising approach to reduce cardiovascular risk with potentially fewer side effects and greater accessibility. Understanding the precise mechanisms of these natural compounds advances the development of targeted dietary strategies to complement conventional pharmacotherapy in the treatment of hypercholesterolemia.
DOI: 10.1186/s13020-025-01178-y
ISSN: 1749-8546
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s13020-025-01178-y-2025-08-15-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Facilitating microglial phagocytosis by which Jiawei Xionggui Decoction alleviates cognitive impairment via TREM2-mediated energy metabolic reprogramming</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60927-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 7
Autoren: Wen Wen, Jie Chen, Junbao Xiang, Shiqi Zhang, Jingru Liu, Jie Wang, Ping Wang, Shijun Xu
Journal: Chinese Journal of Natural Medicines
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60927-7
ISSN: 1875-5364
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s1875-5364(25)60927-7-2025-08-15-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Acupuncture for patients with mild cognitive impairment: a randomized, patient–assessor-blinded, sham-controlled pilot study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05023-5</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 7
Autoren: Yujin Choi, Pyung-Wha Kim, In-Chul Jung, Ae-Ran Kim, Hyo-Ju Park, Ojin Kwon, Jun-Hwan Lee, Joo-Hee Kim
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-19
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Mild cognitive impairment (MCI) is the transitional stage between normal aging and early dementia. Although acupuncture is a promising non-pharmacological treatment, higher-quality evidence is needed to confirm its effectiveness.
          
          
            Methods
            A randomized, patient- and assessor-blinded, sham-controlled, pilot clinical trial was conducted to evaluate the feasibility of acupuncture for treating MCI. In total, 30 participants were randomized into acupuncture and sham acupuncture groups. The participants underwent 24 treatment sessions over 12 weeks. The primary outcome was a change in the Alzheimer’s Disease Assessment Scale-Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-cog) score over 12 weeks, whereas the secondary outcomes included the Seoul Neuropsychological Screening Battery (SNSB-II) score. Adverse events and the success of blinding were also assessed.
          
          
            Results
            Of the 30 participants, 28 completed the study. Participants in the acupuncture and sham acupuncture groups exhibited a decrease in ADAS-cog scores from 10.27 ± 4.03 and 11.47 ± 3.85 at baseline to 5.78 ± 3.04 and 6.27 ± 2.83 at week 12, respectively. Both groups exhibited clinically meaningful improvements, with no significant difference between groups (P = 0.6590). The SNSB-II memory domain exhibited a moderate effect size favoring acupuncture (Cohen’s d = 0.57, P = 0.1317). No intervention-related adverse events were reported, and participant blinding was adequate throughout the trial.
          
          
            Conclusions
            The 12-week acupuncture treatment is feasible for patients with MCI and may improve memory. Although the primary outcomes did not reach statistical significance, the secondary outcomes suggested potential benefits. Larger confirmatory trials are warranted to investigate the effectiveness of acupuncture in patients with MCI.
          
          
            Trial registration
            Clinical Research Information Service (cris.nih.go.kr) KCT0001938 (Registered on June 3, 2016).
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05023-5
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-15</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05023-5-2025-08-15-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>