<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Orthopedics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:10:46 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:10:46 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Personalized Spine Surgery in Adult Deformity: Reoperation Rates and Mechanical Complications Following Customized Planning and Interbody Implant Use</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/21925682251409696</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 50
Autoren: Justin S. Smith, Chun-Po Yen, Roland Kent, Sigurd Berven, Gregory M. Mundis, Robert Robinson, Rodrigo J. Nicolau, Joseph A. Osorio, Jahangir Asghar, J. Rush Fisher, Kelli M. Howell, Mark Tantorski, Donald Blaskiewicz, Jeffrey P. Mullin, Joseph Gjolaj, John Small, Christopher P. Ames
Journal: Global Spine Journal
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-20
Abstract: 
                    Study Design
                    Retrospective cohort study.
                  
                  
                    Objectives
                    Prior studies have shown that adult spinal deformity (ASD) patients undergoing revision surgery due to mechanical complications had less radiographic improvement and worsening patient-reported outcomes scores. The combination of customized 3D planning and personalized implants has been shown to contribute to improved achievement of alignment goals. This study aimed to determine whether such improved correction also results in a correspondingly lower revision surgery rate due to mechanical complications.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Pre- and postoperative radiographic alignment measures, including lumbar lordosis (LL), distal lumbar lordosis (DLL), pelvic incidence (PI) – LL mismatch, and L1 pelvic angle (L1PA), as well as data on mechanical complications leading to reoperation were collected on 115 ASD patients with personalized interbody implants and minimum 2-year follow-up. This cohort was statistically compared to a multicenter dataset (ISSG) of 997 ASD patients treated using stock devices and using the same reoperation classifications.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Postoperatively achieved alignment measures correlated significantly with their respective preoperative alignment goals, with the following average offsets from plan: 2.4° LL, −0.2° DLL, −2.4° PI-LL, 0.3° L1PA. Compared to the ISSG cohort that utilized stock interbody implants, the cohort utilizing 3D preoperative planning and personalized interbody implants resulted in significantly fewer revisions for mechanical complications up to 2 years postoperatively: 5/115 (4.3%) vs 166/997 (16.6%),
                      P
                      &amp;lt; 0.001.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    These findings suggest that achieving planned alignment targets with personalized interbody devices is associated with reduced revision surgery for mechanical complications, a result which may have positive implications for improved patient outcomes and reduced cost.
                  
DOI: 10.1177/21925682251409696
ISSN: 2192-5682
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/21925682251409696-2026-01-20-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Four-year outcomes following triplanar tarsometatarsal arthrodesis with early weightbearing for Hallux Valgus: A multicenter prospective study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1053/j.jfas.2025.07.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 47
Autoren: Daniel J. Hatch, Avneesh Chhabra, Mindi Dayton, Paul D. Dayton, Daniel C. Farber, Deidre A. Kile, Jennifer Koay, George T. Liu, Jody P. McAleer, Robert D. Santrock
Journal: The Journal of Foot and Ankle Surgery
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1053/j.jfas.2025.07.007
ISSN: 1067-2516
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1053/j.jfas.2025.07.007-2026-01-20-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Patient Concerns Are Often Overlooked by Low Back Pain (LBP) Guidelines</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2026.9001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 24
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
Abstract: Infographic illustrating the article “People With Acute Low Back Pain Have Concerns That May Not Be Addressed by Guideline-Recommended Advice: A Mixed-Methods Study”, which was published in the September 2024 issue of JOSPT.
                  J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2026;56(1):64. doi:10.2519/jospt.2026.9001
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2026.9001
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2026.9001-2026-01-20-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Metformin and incident osteoarthritis: Causal insights from a co-twin control study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joca.2025.12.014</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 21
Autoren: Karin Magnusson, Aleksandra Turkiewicz, Andrea Dell’Isola, Ali Kiadaliri, Martin Englund
Journal: Osteoarthritis and Cartilage
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.joca.2025.12.014
ISSN: 1063-4584
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.joca.2025.12.014-2026-01-20-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>More Frequent Empathic Communication by Physical Therapists is Associated With Improved Outcomes for Low-Impact Chronic Pain</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/ptj/pzag001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Orthopedics
Score: 15
Autoren: Chelsea R Chapman, Matthew D Stone, Janae Anthony, Marco Patawaran, Julia Sinsay, Cindy R Solomon, Samantha Ungson, Katrina S Monroe
Journal: Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-06
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Importance
                    Empathic communication is recommended in chronic pain management, yet few studies have examined the role of provider communication on treatment outcomes in pain rehabilitation.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    The objective is to quantify associations between the frequency of empathic communication by physical therapists and patient-reported pain outcomes during routine clinical care for patients with chronic musculoskeletal pain.
                  
                  
                    Participants and Design
                    Thirty-one physical therapist-patient dyads participated in a prospective cohort study in an outpatient physical therapy clinic. Evaluation and treatment sessions were audio-recorded over 6 weeks of routine physical therapy management of chronic musculoskeletal pain.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcomes and Measures
                    Empathic communication was quantified as a ratio of the frequency of empathic responses by physical therapists normalized to the frequency of empathic opportunities expressed by patients. Mixed-effects models assessed associations between physical therapist empathic communication and patient-reported pain intensity and interference over time.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Across 99 recorded visits, physical therapists (n = 8) responded empathically 67% of the time. Empathic response rates for individual providers ranged from 27% to 84%. On average, more frequent empathic communication was associated with lower pain intensity (B = −1.29 [95% CI = −2.23 to −0.36) and pain interference (B = −1.07 [95% CI = −2.11 to −0.03]). More frequent empathic communication was also associated with a greater reduction in pain intensity over time (B = −0.78 [95% CI = −1.45 to −0.12]).
                  
                  
                    Conclusions and Relevance
                    More frequent empathic communication is associated with lower patient-reported pain intensity and interference, along with larger and more rapid decreases in pain intensity over time. Future studies should investigate the efficacy of empathic communication skills training to improve outcomes of chronic pain management.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/ptj/pzag001
ISSN: 0031-9023
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-20</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/ptj/pzag001-2026-01-20-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>