<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 01:02:18 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 01:02:18 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Comparative effectiveness of remote perioperative telemonitoring in cancer surgery: a randomized trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01961-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 315
Autoren: Virginia Sun, Yi Xiao, Shanpeng Li, Joycelynne Palmer, Calvin P. Tribby, Tracy E. Crane, Laleh Melstrom, Thanh Dellinger, Bertram Yuh, Dan Raz, Enrique Cota-Robles, Linda Cota-Robles, Margaret Nolde, Betty Ferrell, Yuman Fong
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-28
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01961-z
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01961-z-2025-09-29-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Detecting, Characterizing, and Mitigating Implicit and Explicit Racial Biases in Health Care Datasets With Subgroup Learnability: Algorithm Development and Validation Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/71757</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 77
Autoren: Faris Gulamali, Ashwin Shreekant Sawant, Lora Liharska, Carol Horowitz, Lili Chan, Ira Hofer, Karandeep Singh, Lynne Richardson, Emmanuel Mensah, Alexander Charney, David Reich, Jianying Hu, Girish Nadkarni
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-04
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            The growing adoption of diagnostic and prognostic algorithms in health care has led to concerns about the perpetuation of algorithmic bias against disadvantaged groups of individuals. Deep learning methods to detect and mitigate bias have revolved around modifying models, optimization strategies, and threshold calibration with varying levels of success and tradeoffs. However, there have been limited substantive efforts to address bias at the level of the data used to generate algorithms in health care datasets.
          
          
            Objective
            The aim of this study is to create a simple metric (AEquity) that uses a learning curve approximation to distinguish and mitigate bias via guided dataset collection or relabeling.
          
          
            Methods
            We demonstrate this metric in 2 well-known examples, chest X-rays and health care cost utilization, and detect novel biases in the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey.
          
          
            Results
            We demonstrated that using AEquity to guide data-centric collection for each diagnostic finding in the chest radiograph dataset decreased bias by between 29% and 96.5% when measured by differences in area under the curve. Next, we wanted to examine (1) whether AEquity worked on intersectional populations and (2) if AEquity is invariant to different types of fairness metrics, not just area under the curve. Subsequently, we examined the effect of AEquity on mitigating bias when measured by false negative rate, precision, and false discovery rate for Black patients on Medicaid. When we examined Black patients on Medicaid, at the intersection of race and socioeconomic status, we found that AEquity-based interventions reduced bias across a number of different fairness metrics including overall false negative rate by 33.3% (bias reduction absolute=1.88×10−1, 95% CI 1.4×10−1 to 2.5×10−1; bias reduction of 33.3%, 95% CI 26.6%‐40%; precision bias by 7.50×10−2, 95% CI 7.48×10−2 to 7.51×10−2; bias reduction of 94.6%, 95% CI 94.5%‐94.7%; false discovery rate by 94.5%; absolute bias reduction=3.50×10−2, 95% CI 3.49×10−2 to 3.50×10−2). Similarly, AEquity-guided data collection demonstrated bias reduction of up to 80% on mortality prediction with the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (bias reduction absolute=0.08, 95% CI 0.07-0.09). Then, we wanted to compare AEquity to state-of-the-art data-guided debiasing measures such as balanced empirical risk minimization and calibration. Consequently, we benchmarked against balanced empirical risk minimization and calibration and showed that AEquity-guided data collection outperforms both standard approaches. Moreover, we demonstrated that AEquity works on fully connected networks; convolutional neural networks such as ResNet-50; transformer architectures such as VIT-B-16, a vision transformer with 86 million parameters; and nonparametric methods such as Light Gradient-Boosting Machine.
          
          
            Conclusions
            In short, we demonstrated that AEquity is a robust tool by applying it to different datasets, algorithms, and intersectional analyses and measuring its effectiveness with respect to a range of traditional fairness metrics.
          
DOI: 10.2196/71757
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/71757-2025-09-29-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Culture-free detection of bacteria from blood for rapid sepsis diagnosis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-01948-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 75
Autoren: M. Henar Marino Miguélez, Mohammad Osaid, Erik Hallström, Kerem Kaya, Jimmy Larsson, Vinodh Kandavalli, Carolina Wählby, Johan Elf, Wouter van der Wijngaart
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-25
Abstract: Abstract
          Approximately 50 million people suffer from sepsis yearly, and 13 million die from it. For every hour a patient with septic shock is untreated, their survival rate decreases by 8%. Therefore, rapid detection and antibiotic susceptibility profiling of bacterial agents in the blood of sepsis patients are crucial for determining appropriate treatment. Here, we introduce a method to isolate bacteria from whole blood with high separation efficiency through Smart centrifugation, followed by microfluidic trapping and subsequent detection using deep learning applied to microscopy images. We detected, within 2 h, E. coli, K. pneumoniae, or E. faecalis from spiked samples of healthy human donor blood at clinically relevant concentrations as low as 9, 7 and 32 colony-forming units per ml of blood, respectively. However, the detection of S. aureus remains a challenge. This rapid isolation and detection represents a significant advancement towards culture-free detection of bloodstream infections.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-01948-w
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-01948-w-2025-09-29-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Video and Telephone Telehealth Use and Web-Based Patient Portal Activation Among Rural-Dwelling Patients: Retrospective Medical Record Review and Policy Implications</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/67226</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 41
Autoren: Meghan Rowe Ferrara, Gina Intinarelli-Shuler, Susan A Chapman
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-29
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Telehealth may redress rural health care shortages in the United States and improve related rural health disparities. However, following the expansion of telehealth related to the COVID-19 pandemic, telehealth use has been lower among rural populations compared to urban populations. Certain populations are also more likely to use audio-only telehealth, with implications for care quality.
          
          
            Objective
            The aim of this study is to describe demographic and telehealth use characteristics of a population of rural-dwelling adult patients and explore relationships of these characteristics with patients’ level of rurality and with modality of patients’ most recent telehealth encounter.
          
          
            Methods
            We conducted a retrospective medical record review of adults who lived in rural California zip codes and used telehealth at an urban medical center from December 2021 to December 2022. Rural-Urban Commuting Area codes were used to assign rurality and group patients by 3 levels of rurality. Telehealth visits were defined as video-enabled and telephone encounters. Variables included age, race or ethnicity, preferred language, payer, web-based patient portal activation status (as proxy for digital health literacy), video or telephone modality, and visit provider. Chi-square and Fisher exact tested associations of demographic and encounter characteristics with patient level of rurality and telehealth encounter modality.
          
          
            Results
            A total of 9359 patients were included. Telehealth patients living in the most rural zip codes were older, and a higher proportion were White compared to those in less rural zip codes. Patients who were American Indian, Asian, Black, and Latino together comprised 18.8% (n=1760) of the sample, lower than that in rural California counties. Video visit use was significantly lower among patients who were 65 years of age or older (n=3183, 91.3% vs n=5507, 93.8% for younger than 65 years; χ21=19.3; P&amp;lt;.001), Latino race or ethnicity (n=1229, 90.9% vs n=6078, 93.4% among White patients; χ23=12.0; P=.008), primary Spanish speakers (n=336, 87.7% vs n=8305, 93% among English speakers; Fisher exact, P&amp;lt;.001), and publicly insured (Medicare: n=3843, 91.7%; Medicaid: n=1717, 92.2%; privately insured: n=3130, 94.7%; χ22=27.9; P&amp;lt;.001). Patient portal activation was lower among Latinx patients (n=1183, 87.5% vs n=6099, 93.7% among White patients), Spanish speakers (n=295, 77% vs n=8241, 92.3% among English speakers; Fisher exact: P&amp;lt;.001), and Medicaid patients (n=1635, 87.8%; Medicare: n=3802, 90.7%; privately insured: n=3140, 95%; χ24=106.3; P&amp;lt;.001).
          
          
            Conclusions
            Findings substantiate concerns of rural telehealth access disparities, particularly among patients who are older, of minoritized race or ethnicity, and Spanish-speaking. Ongoing research is needed to understand how underserved rural populations use telehealth. To address telehealth use disparities, policy should address patient-level barriers by supporting measures such as health care navigation resources, culturally tailored telehealth patient outreach, digital access assessment, and patient digital education. Evidence-based telehealth reimbursement policy is essential to support access and address provider-side barriers.
          
DOI: 10.2196/67226
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/67226-2025-09-29-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Demographic and Socioeconomic Disparities in Telemedicine Use Among Individuals With Type 2 Diabetes in Primary Care: Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/73113</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 34
Autoren: Nawwarah Alfarwan, Maria Panagioti, Alexander Hodkinson, Lamiece Hassan, Salwa S Zghebi, Evangelos Kontopantelis
Journal: Journal of Medical Internet Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-09
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Telemedicine has revolutionized the management of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) in primary care by improving access to health care services and enhancing health outcomes. Despite these advancements, it remains unclear whether telemedicine has reduced access inequalities among different demographic and socioeconomic groups.
          
          
            Objective
            This study aimed to investigate the most important demographic and socioeconomic factors associated with telemedicine use among individuals with T2DM in primary care.
          
          
            Methods
            We conducted a systematic review and meta-analysis. Databases including MEDLINE, Embase, PsycINFO, Google Scholar, Scopus, and CINAHL were searched from inception to December 2023. The reference lists of eligible studies and other relevant systematic reviews were also searched. We included observational and cohort studies that assessed the effects of telemedicine interventions on individuals with T2DM in primary care. The core outcomes were the factors associated with telemedicine use, reported as adjusted odds ratios and 95% CIs for each factor, using a random-effects model. Heterogeneity was quantified using the I² statistic, and publication bias was assessed. The protocol for this review was registered with PROSPERO (CRD42024550410).
          
          
            Results
            Of the 3006 records identified, 16 studies involving 71,336 patients were included in the meta-analysis. Female patients had higher odds of using telemedicine than males (pooled adjusted odds ratio [OR] 1.05, 95% CI 1.02-1.09). Older patients were significantly less likely to use telemedicine than younger patients (pooled OR 0.979, 95% CI 0.98-0.98). Compared with White patients, Black patients were less likely to use telemedicine (pooled OR 0.55, 95% CI 0.32-0.94), while no statistically significant differences were observed for Hispanic (pooled OR 1.075, 95% CI 0.36-3.24) or Asian participants (pooled OR 0.56, 95% CI 0.29-1.06). Patients with higher education levels had greater odds of using telemedicine than those with lower education levels (pooled OR 1.681, 95% CI 1.48-1.91).
          
          
            Conclusions
            This systematic review and meta-analysis provide evidence of significant disparities in telemedicine use among men, older adults, Black individuals, and those with lower levels of education who have T2DM in primary care. Given that these groups are among the most vulnerable to T2DM, these disparities highlight the critical need for strategic interventions and robust policies that ensure telemedicine fosters equitable access to health care while preventing further exacerbation of existing health inequalities.
          
DOI: 10.2196/73113
ISSN: 1438-8871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-29</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/73113-2025-09-29-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>