<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, General &amp; Internal) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 01:08:49 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 01:08:49 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Azelastine Nasal Spray for Prevention of SARS-CoV-2 Infections</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.4283</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 2458
Autoren: Thorsten Lehr, Peter Meiser, Dominik Selzer, Torben Rixecker, Frank Holzer, Ralph Mösges, Sigrun Smola, Robert Bals, CONTAIN Study Group, Veronika Alberg, Florian Bub, Nicholas Biwank, Charlotte Dette, Lale Dastgir, Alina Kuntz, Christopher Hale, Johanna Sophie Kapp, Kathrin Litzenburger, Henning Morr, Johanna Wagner, Hacer Sahin, Nelli Schröder, Martina Seibert, Katrin Thieser, Quirin Werthner
Journal: JAMA Internal Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
Abstract: 
                    Importance
                    Limited pharmaceutical options exist for preexposure prophylaxis of COVID-19 beyond vaccination. Azelastine, an antihistamine nasal spray used for decades to treat allergic rhinitis, has in vitro antiviral activity against respiratory viruses, including SARS-CoV-2.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    To determine the efficacy and safety of azelastine nasal spray for prevention of SARS-CoV-2 infections in healthy adults.
                  
                  
                    Design, Setting, and Participants
                    A phase 2, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single-center trial was conducted from March 2023 to July 2024. Healthy adults from the general population were enrolled at the Saarland University Hospital in Germany.
                  
                  
                    Interventions
                    Participants were randomly assigned 1:1 to receive azelastine, 0.1%, nasal spray or placebo 3 times daily for 56 days. SARS-CoV-2 rapid antigen testing (RAT) was conducted twice weekly, with positive results confirmed by polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Symptomatic participants with negative RAT results underwent multiplex PCR testing for respiratory viruses.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcome
                    The primary end point was the number of PCR-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infections during the study.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    A total of 450 participants were randomized, with 227 assigned to azelastine and 223 to placebo; 299 (66.4%) were female, 151 (33.6%) male, with a mean (SD) age of 33.0 (13.3) years. Most were White (417 [92.7%]), with 4 (0.9%) African, 22 (4.9%) Asian, and 7 (1.6%) of other ethnicity. In the intention-to-treat (ITT) population, the incidence of PCR-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection was significantly lower in the azelastine group (n = 5 [2.2%]) compared with the placebo group (n = 15 [6.7%]) (OR, 0.31; 95% CI, 0.11-0.87). As secondary end points, azelastine demonstrated an increase in mean (SD) time to SARS-CoV-2 infection among infected participants (31.2 [9.3] vs 19.5 [14.8] days), a reduction of the overall number of PCR-confirmed symptomatic infections (21 of 227 participants vs 49 of 223 participants), and a lower incidence of PCR-confirmed rhinovirus infections (1.8% vs 6.3%). Adverse events were comparable between the groups.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions and Relevance
                    In this single-center trial, azelastine nasal spray was associated with reduced risk of SARS-CoV-2 respiratory infections. These findings support the potential of azelastine as a safe prophylactic approach warranting confirmation in larger, multicentric trials.
                  
                  
                    Trial registration
                    
                      EudraCT number:
                      2022-003756-13
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.4283
ISSN: 2168-6106
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.4283-2025-12-02-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Caffeinated Coffee Consumption or Abstinence to Reduce Atrial Fibrillation</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2025.21056</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1957
Autoren: Christopher X. Wong, Christopher C. Cheung, Gabrielle Montenegro, Hannah H. Oo, Isabella J. Peña, Janet J. Tang, Samuel J. Tu, Grace Wall, Thomas A. Dewland, Joshua D. Moss, Edward P. Gerstenfeld, Zian H. Tseng, Henry H. Hsia, Randall J. Lee, Jeffrey E. Olgin, Vasanth Vedantham, Melvin M. Scheinman, Catherine Lee, Prashanthan Sanders, Gregory M. Marcus
Journal: JAMA
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-09
Abstract: 
                    Importance
                    Conventional wisdom holds that caffeinated coffee is proarrhythmic. Coffee is the most commonly consumed caffeinated beverage in the US, and a randomized trial assessing caffeinated coffee consumption in patients with atrial fibrillation (AF) has not previously been performed.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    To determine the effect of caffeinated coffee consumption compared with abstinence from coffee and caffeine on recurrent AF.
                  
                  
                    Design, Setting, and Participants
                    This was a prospective, open-label, randomized clinical trial enrolling 200 current or previous (within past 5 years) coffee-drinking adults with persistent AF, or atrial flutter with a history of AF, planned for electrical cardioversion from 5 hospitals in the US, Canada, and Australia between November 2021 and December 2024. The date of final follow-up was June 5, 2025.
                  
                  
                    Intervention
                    Patients were randomized in a 1:1 ratio to regular caffeinated coffee consumption vs coffee and caffeine abstinence for 6 months. Patients in the coffee consumption group were encouraged to drink at least 1 cup of caffeinated coffee daily. Patients in the abstinence group were encouraged to completely abstain from both caffeinated and decaffeinated coffee and other caffeine-containing products.
                  
                  
                    Main Outcomes and Measures
                    The primary end point was clinically detected recurrence of AF or atrial flutter over 6 months.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Two hundred patients (mean [SD] age, 69 [11] years; 71% male) were randomized to caffeinated coffee consumption (n = 100) or coffee abstinence (n = 100). Baseline coffee intake was 7 cups (IQR, 7-18) per week in both groups. During follow-up, coffee intake in the consumption and abstinence groups was 7 (IQR, 6-11) and 0 (IQR, 0-2) cups per week, respectively, resulting in a between-group difference of 7 cups (95% CI, 7-7) per week. In the primary analysis, AF or atrial flutter recurrence was less in the coffee consumption (47%) than the coffee abstinence (64%) group, resulting in a 39% lower hazard of recurrence (hazard ratio, 0.61 [95% CI, 0.42-0.89];
                      P
                       = .01). A comparable benefit of coffee consumption was observed with AF recurrence only. There was no significant difference in adverse events.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusions and Relevance
                    In this clinical trial of coffee drinkers after successful cardioversion, allocation to consumption of caffeinated coffee averaging 1 cup a day was associated with less recurrence of AF or atrial flutter compared with abstinence from coffee and caffeinated products.
                  
                  
                    Trial Registration
                    
                      ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier:
                      NCT05121519
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1001/jama.2025.21056
ISSN: 0098-7484
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jama.2025.21056-2025-12-02-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Beta-Blockers after Myocardial Infarction without Reduced Ejection Fraction</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2504735</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1768
Autoren: Borja Ibanez, Roberto Latini, Xavier Rossello, Alberto Dominguez-Rodriguez, Felipe Fernández-Vazquez, Valentina Pelizzoni, Pedro L. Sánchez, Manuel Anguita, José A. Barrabés, Sergio Raposeiras-Roubín, Stuart Pocock, Noemí Escalera, Lidia Staszewsky, Carlos Nicolás Pérez-García, Pablo Díez-Villanueva, Jose-Angel Pérez-Rivera, Oscar Prada-Delgado, Ruth Owen, Gonzalo Pizarro, Onofre Caldes, Sandra Gómez-Talavera, José Tuñón, Matteo Bianco, Jesus Zarauza, Alfredo Vetrano, Ana Campos, Susana Martínez-Huertas, Héctor Bueno, Miguel Puentes, Giulietta Grigis, Juan L. Bonilla-Palomas, Elvira Marco, José R. González-Juanatey, Roi Bangueses, Carlos González-Juanatey, Ana García-Álvarez, Juan Ruiz-García, Anna Carrasquer, Juan C. García-Rubira, Domingo Pascual-Figal, Carlos Tomás-Querol, J. Alberto San Román, Pasquale Baratta, Jaume Agüero, Roberto Martín-Reyes, Furio Colivicchi, Rosario Ortas-Nadal, Pablo Bazal, Alberto Cordero, Antonio Fernández-Ortiz, Pierangelo Basso, Eva González, Fabrizio Poletti, Giulia Bugani, Marzia Debiasio, Deborah Cosmi, Alessandro Navazio, Javier Bermejo, Giovanni Tortorella, Marco Marini, Javier Botas, José M. de la Torre-Hernández, Filippo Ottani, Valentín Fuster
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-13
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2504735
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2504735-2025-12-02-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Clinical Trials Affected by Research Grant Terminations at the National Institutes of Health</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1394
Autoren: Vishal R. Patel, Michael Liu, Anupam B. Jena
Journal: JAMA Internal Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-17
Abstract: This cross-sectional study summarizes the number of trials with terminated grants from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and calculates the proportion of affected trials among those with previously active NIH funding, by trial status at time of grant termination and by trial characteristics.
DOI: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088
ISSN: 2168-6106
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1001/jamainternmed.2025.6088-2025-12-02-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Orforglipron, an Oral Small-Molecule GLP-1 Receptor Agonist for Obesity Treatment</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa2511774</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, General &amp; Internal
Score: 1317
Autoren: Sean Wharton, Louis J. Aronne, Adam Stefanski, Nasreen F. Alfaris, Andreea Ciudin, Koutaro Yokote, Bruno Halpern, Alpana P. Shukla, Chunmei Zhou, Lisa Macpherson, Sheryl E. Allen, Nadia N. Ahmad, Suzanne R. Klise
Journal: New England Journal of Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-06
DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa2511774
ISSN: 0028-4793
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-12-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1056/nejmoa2511774-2025-12-02-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>