<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 01:07:28 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 01:07:28 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Expanding the rheumatology lens: should we embrace POTS and post-infectious syndromes?</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 65
Autoren: Brittany L Adler
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0-2025-08-12-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of Long‐Term Voclosporin Treatment on Renal Histology in Patients With Active Lupus Nephritis With Repeat Renal Biopsies</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43209</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 21
Autoren: Brad H. Rovin, Clarissa Cassol, Samir V. Parikh, Amit Saxena, Neil Solomons, Vanessa Birardi, Ernie Yap, Clint W. Abner, David R. W. Jayne, Robert B. Huizinga
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-17
Abstract: ObjectiveThis study characterized the impact of voclosporin on kidney histology in patients with lupus nephritis (LN) who had protocolized repeat kidney biopsies in the AURORA clinical trials.MethodsPatients were randomized to voclosporin or placebo treatment for up to 3 years; all patients received mycophenolate mofetil and low‐dose glucocorticoids. Patients had baseline kidney biopsies within 6 months before study start and repeat biopsies after approximately 18 months of study treatment. The revised National Institutes of Health indices for LN activity and chronicity (CI) were calculated in addition to a semiquantitative assessment of vascular and tubular lesions.ResultsSixteen patients in the voclosporin group and 10 patients in the control group had both baseline and repeat kidney biopsies. Patient clinical characteristics were similar at baseline. In the voclosporin group, most (n = 13) patients had pure class IV lesions (pure class V, n = 1; mixed, n = 2). In the control group, three patients had pure class IV (pure class III, n = 3; pure class V, n = 1; mixed, n = 3). Most of the voclosporin‐treated patients had no change in CI (n = 8) or a change no greater than 2 (n = 6); control‐treated patients also had no change in CI (n = 3) or a change no greater than 2 (n = 6). No trends in vascular lesions or tubular compartment changes were observed.ConclusionOutcomes from this small subgroup show that exposure to study treatment was not associated with nephrotoxicity based on histopathologic evaluation after 18 months. These data are reassuring and further contribute to the safety profile of voclosporin for the treatment of adults with active LN.
DOI: 10.1002/art.43209
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43209-2025-08-12-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Real‐World Cost‐Effectiveness of a Standardized Education and Exercise Therapy Program for Hip and Knee Osteoarthritis Compared to Usual Care</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25555</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 19
Autoren: Darren R. Mazzei, Jackie L. Whittaker, Peter Faris, Tracy Wasylak, Deborah A. Marshall
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-12
Abstract: ObjectiveWe estimated the real‐world cost‐effectiveness of a standardized education and exercise therapy program (GLA:D) compared to usual care (UC) for people managing hip and/or knee osteoarthritis (HKOA).MethodsWe used a prospective matched cohort design to recruit people (aged &amp;gt;45 years) diagnosed with HKOA who used GLA:D or UC (not on a surgical waitlist) throughout Alberta, Canada. Demographics, pain, function, quality of life, and an HKOA‐related cost questionnaire were administered over 12 months. The primary Ministry of Health (MOH) perspective used administrative data to estimate all public health care costs. The secondary health care perspective included MOH, private insurance, and out‐of‐pocket costs. We calculated our cost‐effectiveness measure, incremental net monetary benefit (INMB) in Canadian dollars, over 12 months with a $30,000/quality‐adjusted life years (QALY) willingness to pay threshold and adjusted for the differences between cohorts. A Markov model was used to extend INMB over a lifetime time horizon (3% discounting). Model uncertainty was explored by probabilistic sensitivity analyses.ResultsA total of 254 participants (GLA:D n = 127, UC n = 127; 72% female), with a mean age of 64.3 years (95% confidence interval [CI]: 63.1–65.5), diagnosed with knee osteoarthritis (63%), hip osteoarthritis (24%), or both (13%) were observed for a mean of 5.5 years (95% CI: 4.8–6.3). The adjusted INMB of GLA:D compared to UC was $6,065 (95% CI: $3,648–$8,482) and $499 (95% CI: −$2,913 to $3,912) from an MOH and health care perspective over 12 months and $6,574 and $1,775 over a lifetime with 54% and 51% probability of being cost‐effective using a threshold of willingness to pay of $30,000 per QALY.ConclusionsGLA:D had a positive INMB compared to UC from the MOH perspective over 12 months. The INMB remained positive but was less certain over a lifetime or when out‐of‐pocket and private insurance costs were considered.
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25555
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25555-2025-08-12-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association of Abatacept with Lower Mortality Risk Compared to Rituximab in Rheumatoid Arthritis‐Associated Interstitial Lung Disease: An Emulated Target Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43332</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 18
Autoren: Po‐Cheng Shih, Shiow‐Ing Wang, Qing‐Wen Wang, James Cheng Chung Wei
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
Abstract: BackgroundThe optimal treatment strategy for rheumatoid arthritis‐associated interstitial lung disease (RA‐ILD) remains uncertain, and direct comparative data between biologics is limited. This study aimed to evaluate the effectiveness and safety of abatacept compared with rituximab in patients with RA‐ILD.MethodsAn emulated target trial was designed using the TriNetX US Collaborative Network database, including patients with RA‐ILD, diagnosed between 2007 and 2024. Propensity score matching (PSM) was used to balance baseline characteristics between the two treatment groups (abatacept and rituximab). The primary outcome was all‐cause mortality, while secondary outcomes included respiratory events, medical utilization, and infection‐related adverse events. Hazard ratios (HRs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were estimated to use Cox proportional hazards models.Results1,615 patients per group were identified after matching for analysis. Abatacept was associated with a significantly lower risk of all‐cause mortality compared with rituximab (HR 0.689, 95% CI 0.581–0.818) and a reduced risk of mechanical ventilation (HR 0.698, 95% CI 0.521–0.934). The subgroup analyses yielded consistent findings. Sensitivity analyses excluding patients with concomitant connective tissue diseases also demonstrated consistent results (mortality, HR 0.679, 95% CI 0.570–0.810), reinforcing the robustness of the findings.ConclusionAbatacept was associated with a lower risk of mortality compared with rituximab in patients with RA‐ILD. Because clinicians may preferentially reserve abatacept for less aggressive RA‐ILD, residual confounding by indication cannot be excluded; thus, the association should not be interpreted as proof of causality. Prospective randomized trials are needed to confirm whether abatacept confers a true survival advantage.image
DOI: 10.1002/art.43332
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43332-2025-08-12-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Gastrointestinal manifestations of systemic sclerosis: current approaches and emerging therapies</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1097/bor.0000000000001110</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 17
Autoren: Luis G. Alcala-Gonzalez, Monique Hinchcliff, Zsuzsanna H. McMahan
Journal: Current Opinion in Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-15
Abstract: 
            Purpose of review
            This review highlights recent advances in the understanding and management of gastrointestinal manifestations in systemic sclerosis (SSc). It is intended for clinicians and researchers aiming to improve diagnostic accuracy and therapeutic strategies in managing SSc-related gastrointestinal disease.
          
          
            Recent findings
            Gastrointestinal involvement in SSc is highly variable in terms of clinical presentation, symptom severity, progression, timing of onset, and response to treatment. Emerging research highlights early immune-mediated damage to neural and muscular gastrointestinal tissues, microbiome alterations, and vascular dysfunction – particularly in patients with late-onset gastrointestinal disease – as key factors guiding the development of personalized, precision-based approaches for well defined patient subgroups. Recent studies underscore the value of early, objective assessment of gastrointestinal motility using tools like whole-gut transit scintigraphy and abdominal vascular ultrasound. New treatment strategies are also being explored for severe manifestations, including investigating mechanisms behind acid-suppressive therapy-resistant gastroesophageal reflux disease and implementing adjunctive therapies for gastrointestinal dysmotility.
          
          
            Summary
            Gastrointestinal involvement in SSc poses a complex clinical challenge, particularly in patients with severe dysmotility and symptoms refractory to standard management strategies. This review offers timely, evidence-based insights to support clinicians in delivering more personalized and effective patient care and highlights critical gaps to address in future research.
          
DOI: 10.1097/bor.0000000000001110
ISSN: 1040-8711
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-12</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1097/bor.0000000000001110-2025-08-12-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>