<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:59:27 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:59:27 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Global, regional, and national cascades of diabetes care, 2000–23: a systematic review and modelling analysis using findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00217-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 1050
Autoren: Lauryn K Stafford, Anna Gage, Yvonne Yiru Xu, Madeleine Conrad, Ismael Barreras Beltran, Edward J Boyko, Bruce B Duncan, Simon I Hay, Hailey Lenox, Rafael Lozano, Dianna J Magliano, Carlos A Aguilar Salinas, Nikhil Tandon, Pedro Zitko, Christopher J L Murray, Theo Vos, Annie Haakenstad, Kanyin Liane Ong
Journal: The Lancet Diabetes &amp;amp; Endocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00217-7
ISSN: 2213-8587
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2213-8587(25)00217-7-2025-09-16-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association of metformin treatment with changes in metal dynamics in individuals with type 2 diabetes</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 336
Autoren: Natsu Otowa-Suematsu, Kazuhiko Sakaguchi, Tomoko Yamada, Marika Nishisaka, Yasuko Morita, Hayato Fukumitsu, Yukari Katsura, Yuko Okada, Yushi Hirota, Kenji Sugawara, Wataru Ogawa
Journal: BMJ Open Diabetes Research &amp;amp; Care
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-31
Abstract: 
                  Introduction
                  The metal-chelating activity of metformin, which has long been known but of unclear clinical relevance, has recently been implicated in the pleiotropic effects, including antitumorigenic and anti-inflammatory actions, of the drug. However, whether metformin actually influences metal dynamics in humans has remained unknown. We here investigate whether metformin influences serum metal levels in individuals with type 2 diabetes.
               
               
                  Research design and methods
                  In this cross-sectional study, individuals with type 2 diabetes treated or not treated with metformin for at least 6 months were recruited. The primary outcome was the difference in serum copper concentration between metformin users and non-users. Secondary outcomes included differences in serum levels of iron, zinc, and vitamin B12 as well as in copper-related and iron-related parameters between the two groups.
               
               
                  Results
                  A total of 189 individuals (93 metformin users and 96 non-users) were analyzed. Metformin users showed significantly lower serum copper (16.0 vs 17.8 µmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) and iron levels (16.3 vs 17.3 µmol/L, p=0.02) and higher zinc levels (13.3 vs 12.5 µmol/L, p=0.01) compared with non-users. Copper-related and iron-related parameters for metformin users were consistent with latent deficiencies of these metals. Serum homocysteine levels (12.2 vs 11.2 µmol/L, p=0.03) were significantly higher, whereas vitamin B12 levels (338.7 vs 412.8 pmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) were significantly lower, in metformin users. Multiple regression analysis including variables that potentially influence metal dynamics identified metformin use as an independent predictor of serum copper (B = –1.54 µmol/L, p&amp;lt;0.001) and iron levels (B = –2.49 µmol/L, p=0.004).
               
               
                  Conclusions
                  Metformin use was associated with reduced serum levels of copper and iron, as well as with increased serum zinc levels. These changes in metal dynamics may be related to the pharmacological effects of this widely administered drug.
               
DOI: 10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255
ISSN: 2052-4897
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1136/bmjdrc-2025-005255-2025-09-16-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide receptor signaling in oligodendrocytes increases the weight-loss action of GLP-1R agonism</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.009</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 149
Autoren: Robert Hansford, Sophie Buller, Anthony H. Tsang, Simon Benoit, Anna G. Roberts, Emmy Erskine, Thomas Brown, Valentina Pirro, Frank Reimann, Norio Harada, Nobuya Inagaki, Ricardo J. Samms, Johannes Broichhagen, David J. Hodson, Alice Adriaenssens, Soyoung Park, Clemence Blouet
Journal: Cell Metabolism
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.009
ISSN: 1550-4131
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.cmet.2025.07.009-2025-09-16-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The effect of turmeric/curcumin supplementation on anthropometric indices in subjects with prediabetes and type 2 diabetes mellitus: A GRADE-assessed systematic review and dose-response meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41387-025-00386-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 149
Autoren: Mohammadreza Moradi Baniasadi, Pishva Arzhang, Azin Setayesh, Maedeh Moradi, Ensieh Nasli-Esfahani, Leila Azadbakht
Journal: Nutrition &amp;amp; Diabetes
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-14
DOI: 10.1038/s41387-025-00386-7
ISSN: 2044-4052
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41387-025-00386-7-2025-09-16-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Too stressed for sex? Associations between stress and sex in daily life</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psyneuen.2025.107583</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism
Score: 107
Autoren: Hanna M. Mües, Charlotte Markert, Anja C. Feneberg, Urs M. Nater
Journal: Psychoneuroendocrinology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2025.107583
ISSN: 0306-4530
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-16</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.psyneuen.2025.107583-2025-09-16-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>