<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 14:17:21 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 14:17:21 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>British Dietetic Association Guidelines for the Dietary Management of Chronic Constipation in Adults</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1111/jhn.70133</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 1205
Autoren: Eirini Dimidi, Alice van der Schoot, Kevin Barrett, Adam D. Farmer, Miranda C. Lomer, S. Mark Scott, Kevin Whelan
Journal: Journal of Human Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
Abstract: ABSTRACT
                  
                    Background
                    Current clinical guidelines for chronic constipation offer limited dietary recommendations. The aim of this project was to develop the first comprehensive evidence‐based dietary guidelines for the management of chronic constipation in adults.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Four systematic reviews and meta‐analyses were performed to identify eligible randomised controlled trials (RCTs). The findings generated from the meta‐analyses were then used to develop guideline statements using the Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development and Evaluation (GRADE) approach and a Delphi consensus survey among a multi‐disciplinary expert Guideline Steering Committee. Recommendation statements were produced for treatment response, stool output, gut symptoms, adverse events, and quality of life, and only based on the findings where ≥ 2 RCTs contributed to the meta‐analysis. The strength of recommendation was assessed using the GRADE approach. Consensus voting amongst the Guideline Steering Committee was performed using a modified Delphi survey approach.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    The four systematic reviews included a total of 75 RCTs. Fifty‐nine dietary recommendation statements were generated and accepted through the Delphi survey. For dietary supplements, 15 recommendation statements relate to fibre supplements, 20 relate to probiotics, 2 to synbiotics, 5 to magnesium oxide, 2 to senna, and 3 to kiwifruit supplements. For foods, three recommendation statements related to kiwifruits, two to prunes, and two to rye bread. For drinks, five recommendation statements related to high mineral‐containing water. No recommendations were made for whole diet approaches due to a lack of evidence. Twelve statements had a very low level of evidence, 39 had a low level of evidence, and 8 had moderate evidence. Twenty‐seven statements were strong recommendations, and 32 were qualified recommendations.
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    These are the first comprehensive evidence‐based dietary guidelines for the management of constipation based upon a robust systematic review and GRADE processes. Recommendations were made for dietary supplements, foods and drinks that have never been previously included in clinical guidelines, and can now be rapidly implemented into clinical practice, thereby improving clinical care and patient outcomes.
                  
DOI: 10.1111/jhn.70133
ISSN: 0952-3871
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1111/jhn.70133-2025-11-11-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Development and validation of a brief Nutrition Security Screener (NSS) for clinical and public health settings</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.08.017</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 200
Autoren: Hope C Craig, Julia Reedy Sharib, Ronit Ridberg, Julia Caldwell, Dipa Shah-Patel, Kelly Warner, Kayla de la Haye, Michelle Livings, Meagan C Brown, Ceping Chao, Mina Habib, Kara Cushing-Haugen, Claudia Nau, Pamela Schwartz, Dariush Mozaffarian
Journal: The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.08.017
ISSN: 0002-9165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.08.017-2025-11-11-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Understanding Dietary Protein Quality: Digestible Indispensable Amino Acid Scores and Beyond</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.005</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 171
Autoren: Joseph J Matthews, Emily J Arentson-Lantz, Paul J Moughan, Robert R Wolfe, Arny A Ferrando, David D Church
Journal: The Journal of Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.005
ISSN: 0022-3166
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tjnut.2025.07.005-2025-11-11-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cheese Consumption and Incidence of Dementia in Community-Dwelling Older Japanese Adults: The JAGES 2019–2022 Cohort Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17213363</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 151
Autoren: Seungwon Jeong, Takao Suzuki, Yusuke Inoue, Eunji Bang, Kentaro Nakamura, Mayuki Sasaki, Katsunori Kondo
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-25
Abstract: Background/Objectives: Dementia is a growing public health concern in rapidly aging Japan. Dietary factors, including dairy products, have been proposed as modifiable influences on cognitive health, although findings across studies remain inconsistent. This study aimed to examine the association between habitual cheese consumption and incident dementia in a large, population-based cohort of older Japanese adults, and to provide epidemiological evidence regarding its potential preventive role in populations with low baseline dairy intake. Methods: We analyzed data from the Japan Gerontological Evaluation Study (JAGES) 2019–2022 cohort, linking survey responses to long-term care insurance (LTCI) certification records. Participants aged ≥65 years without prior LTCI certification were included. Cheese consumption was assessed at baseline and categorized as ≥1 time/week vs. non-consumers. Propensity score matching (PSM) was applied on sociodemographic and health-related covariates. Cox proportional hazards models estimated hazard ratios (HRs) for incident dementia over three years. Results: After PSM, 7914 participants were analyzed (3957 consumers; 3957 non-consumers). Baseline covariates were well-balanced. Over 3 years, 134 consumers (3.4%) and 176 non-consumers (4.5%) developed dementia, corresponding to an absolute risk difference of 1.06 percentage points. Cheese consumption was associated with a lower hazard of dementia (HR = 0.76, 95% CI 0.60–0.95, p = 0.015). Conclusions: Habitual cheese consumption (≥1 time/week) was modestly associated with a reduced 3-year incidence of dementia in older Japanese adults. While the absolute risk reduction was small, these findings are consistent with prior observational evidence linking dairy intake to cognitive health. Further research is warranted to clarify dose–response relationships, cheese subtypes, and underlying mechanisms.
DOI: 10.3390/nu17213363
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu17213363-2025-11-11-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Gut Microbiota α- and β-Diversity, but Not Dietary Patterns, Differ Between Underweight and Normal-Weight Japanese Women Aged 20–39 Years</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17203265</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 105
Autoren: Risako Yamamoto-Wada, Eri Hiraiwa, Kana Okuma, Masako Yamada, Chihiro Ushiroda, Kanako Deguchi, Hiroyuki Naruse, Hiroaki Masuyama, Katsumi Iizuka
Journal: Nutrients
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-17
Abstract: Background and Aim: Underweight young adult women are vulnerable to health risks such as menstrual disorders and vitamin deficiencies. Because few seek medical care for low body weight, the underlying causes remain unclear. This study aimed to examine the associations of body type with dietary patterns and gut microbiota diversity in young women. Methods: We enrolled 40 women aged 20–39 years who visited a nutrition evaluation clinic with a BMI &amp;lt; 17.5 at their first consultation (underweight group) and 40 age-matched women with 18.5 ≤ BMI &amp;lt; 25 (control group). Some women in the underweight group were no longer underweight at the time of analysis but were classified based on their initial BMI. Dietary patterns were assessed based on ten major food categories (meat, fish, eggs, dairy products, soybeans, green and yellow vegetables, seaweed, fruit, tubers, and fats and oil) based on the Food Frequency Questionnaire based on Food Groups. Gut microbiota α-diversity was evaluated using the Shannon, Simpson, and Pielou indices, while β-diversity was analyzed by nonmetric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) and redundancy analysis (RDA). Genera contributing to group differences were identified by RDA and ANOVA-Like Differential Expression tool (ALDEx2). Results: Underweight women had significantly lower gut microbiota α-diversity, while no difference was observed in dietary patterns. NMDS revealed significant β-diversity differences in gut microbiota (PERMANOVA: R2 = 0.064, F = 5.31, p = 0.0001) but not in dietary patterns (p = 0.99). RDA showed that body type explained 4.5% of variance (adjusted R2 = 0.032, F = 3.65, p = 0.0005). Bacteroides, Bifidobacterium, Enterocloster, and Erysipelatoclostridium were enriched in underweight women, whereas Fusicatenibacter, Agathobacter, Dorea, and Prevotella were enriched in controls. AldEx2 confirmed increases in Bacteroides, Enterocloster, and Erysipelatoclostridium and a decrease in Dorea. Conclusions: Underweight women demonstrated reduced gut microbiota diversity and enrichment of taxa associated with inflammatory tendencies. Dietary therapies involving not only prebiotics but also probiotics may beneficially modulate gut microbiota and contribute to the management of low body weight.
DOI: 10.3390/nu17203265
ISSN: 2072-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-11</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3390/nu17203265-2025-11-11-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>