<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 01:08:33 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 01:08:33 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Expanding the rheumatology lens: should we embrace POTS and post-infectious syndromes?</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 65
Autoren: Brittany L Adler
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00190-0-2025-08-13-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Associations of specific pesticides and incident rheumatoid arthritis among female spouses in the Agricultural Health Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43318</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 31
Autoren: Christine G. Parks, Darya Leyzarovich, Ghassan B. Hamra, Karen H. Costenbader, Dazhe Chen, Jonathan N. Hofmann, Laura E. Beane Freeman, Dale P. Sandler
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-16
Abstract: ObjectivesGrowing evidence suggests farming and agricultural pesticide use may be associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA), but few studies have examined specific pesticides and RA among farm women, who may personally use pesticides or be indirectly exposed. We investigated pesticide use and RA risk among female spouses of licensed pesticide applicators in the Agricultural Health Study.MethodsParticipants enrolled in 1993‐1997 in North Carolina and Iowa (N=32,126). Incident RA cases were identified in follow‐up questionnaires (1999‐2021) and confirmed by medical records, relevant medication use, or Medicare claims data (1999‐2016), or from Medicare claims if lacking questionnaire data on RA. Non‐cases reported no RA and had no RA Medicare claims. Among those with complete covariate data (N=410 cases and 21,850 non‐cases), we examined associations with pesticide classes and 32 specific pesticides (personal lifetime use reported at enrollment, updated in 1999‐2003). We calculated odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI), adjusting for age, state, education, smoking pack‐years smoking, body mass index, and correlated pesticides (rho&amp;gt;0.35).ResultsIncident RA was associated with use of organochlorine [DDT (1.89;1.30‐2.75), lindane (1.97;1.12‐3.47)] and organophosphate insecticides [coumaphos (2.32;1.29‐4.19), malathion (1.21;0.91‐1.62)], the carbamate insecticide carbofuran (1.87;0.97‐3.63), and permethrin or pyrethroid insecticides use on crops (1.56;0.92‐2.64) or livestock (1.69;1.07‐2.68). RA was not associated with using herbicides, except for metribuzin (1.88;0.94‐3.79). The fungicides captan (1.78;1.13‐2.83) and metalaxyl (2.49;1.41‐4.40) were also associated with RA.DiscussionThese findings indicate that persistent organochlorine insecticides and some pesticides also used in public health or residential settings may increase RA risk in women.
DOI: 10.1002/art.43318
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43318-2025-08-13-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Hand Swelling and Other Non–Raynaud Phenomenon Symptoms as the Initial Presentation of Systemic Sclerosis: Prevalence and Clinical Associations in Two US Cohorts</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43237</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 22
Autoren: Iqtidar Hanif, Shervin Assassi, Maureen D. Mayes, Zsuzsanna H. McMahan, Meng Zhang, Julio Charles, John M. VanBuren, Jessica S. Alvey, Kimia Ghaffari, Elana J. Bernstein, Flavia V. Castelino, Lorinda Chung, Luke Evnin, Tracy M. Frech, Jessica K. Gordon, Faye N. Hant, Laura K. Hummers, Dinesh Khanna, Kimberly S. Lakin, Dorota Lebiedz‐Odrobina, Yiming Luo, Ashima Makol, Jerry A. Molitor, Duncan F. Moore, Carrie Richardson, Nora Sandorfi, Ami A. Shah, Ankoor Shah, Victoria K. Shanmugam, Virginia D. Steen, Elizabeth R. Volkmann, Carleigh Zahn, Brian Skaug
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
Abstract: ObjectiveRaynaud phenomenon (RP) is often the initial clinical manifestation of systemic sclerosis (SSc), but some patients develop other manifestations first. To help elucidate the diversity of SSc presentation in its early stages, we describe the initial clinical manifestations and antinuclear antibody (ANA) profiles of patients in two early SSc cohorts.MethodsAll patient data in the Genetics vs Environment in Scleroderma Outcomes Study (GENISOS) and Collaborative National Quality and Efficacy Registry (CONQUER) cohorts were reviewed. Both studies enrolled patients within five years of the first non‐RP symptom.ResultsIn GENISOS and CONQUER, respectively, 194 (44.2%) of 439 and 292 (31.1%) of 938 patients had a non‐RP initial symptom, most commonly puffy fingers/hands. Black patients had a non‐RP symptom before RP more commonly than patients in other race and ethnicity categories. Non‐RP first patients were more likely than RP first patients to have diffuse cutaneous involvement and joint contractures at enrollment and had a higher prevalence of RNA polymerase III antibody positivity.ConclusionIn two large US cohorts, &amp;gt;30% of patients began to manifest SSc with puffy fingers/hands or other symptoms, without the “warning sign” of RP as their initial symptom. These patients presented with more severe skin and musculoskeletal disease on average, highlighting the importance of early recognition. The most common autoantibody associated with this presentation was RNA polymerase III. These results should be considered in efforts to recognize SSc in its earliest stages. Puffy fingers/hands, even in the absence of RP, should prompt consideration of early SSc and testing for ANA and SSc‐associated autoantibodies, including RNA polymerase III.
DOI: 10.1002/art.43237
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43237-2025-08-13-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of Long‐Term Voclosporin Treatment on Renal Histology in Patients With Active Lupus Nephritis With Repeat Renal Biopsies</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43209</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 21
Autoren: Brad H. Rovin, Clarissa Cassol, Samir V. Parikh, Amit Saxena, Neil Solomons, Vanessa Birardi, Ernie Yap, Clint W. Abner, David R. W. Jayne, Robert B. Huizinga
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-17
Abstract: ObjectiveThis study characterized the impact of voclosporin on kidney histology in patients with lupus nephritis (LN) who had protocolized repeat kidney biopsies in the AURORA clinical trials.MethodsPatients were randomized to voclosporin or placebo treatment for up to 3 years; all patients received mycophenolate mofetil and low‐dose glucocorticoids. Patients had baseline kidney biopsies within 6 months before study start and repeat biopsies after approximately 18 months of study treatment. The revised National Institutes of Health indices for LN activity and chronicity (CI) were calculated in addition to a semiquantitative assessment of vascular and tubular lesions.ResultsSixteen patients in the voclosporin group and 10 patients in the control group had both baseline and repeat kidney biopsies. Patient clinical characteristics were similar at baseline. In the voclosporin group, most (n = 13) patients had pure class IV lesions (pure class V, n = 1; mixed, n = 2). In the control group, three patients had pure class IV (pure class III, n = 3; pure class V, n = 1; mixed, n = 3). Most of the voclosporin‐treated patients had no change in CI (n = 8) or a change no greater than 2 (n = 6); control‐treated patients also had no change in CI (n = 3) or a change no greater than 2 (n = 6). No trends in vascular lesions or tubular compartment changes were observed.ConclusionOutcomes from this small subgroup show that exposure to study treatment was not associated with nephrotoxicity based on histopathologic evaluation after 18 months. These data are reassuring and further contribute to the safety profile of voclosporin for the treatment of adults with active LN.
DOI: 10.1002/art.43209
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43209-2025-08-13-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association of Abatacept with Lower Mortality Risk Compared to Rituximab in Rheumatoid Arthritis‐Associated Interstitial Lung Disease: An Emulated Target Trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43332</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 19
Autoren: Po‐Cheng Shih, Shiow‐Ing Wang, Qing‐Wen Wang, James Cheng Chung Wei
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
Abstract: BackgroundThe optimal treatment strategy for rheumatoid arthritis‐associated interstitial lung disease (RA‐ILD) remains uncertain, and direct comparative data between biologics is limited. This study aimed to evaluate the effectiveness and safety of abatacept compared with rituximab in patients with RA‐ILD.MethodsAn emulated target trial was designed using the TriNetX US Collaborative Network database, including patients with RA‐ILD, diagnosed between 2007 and 2024. Propensity score matching (PSM) was used to balance baseline characteristics between the two treatment groups (abatacept and rituximab). The primary outcome was all‐cause mortality, while secondary outcomes included respiratory events, medical utilization, and infection‐related adverse events. Hazard ratios (HRs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were estimated to use Cox proportional hazards models.Results1,615 patients per group were identified after matching for analysis. Abatacept was associated with a significantly lower risk of all‐cause mortality compared with rituximab (HR 0.689, 95% CI 0.581–0.818) and a reduced risk of mechanical ventilation (HR 0.698, 95% CI 0.521–0.934). The subgroup analyses yielded consistent findings. Sensitivity analyses excluding patients with concomitant connective tissue diseases also demonstrated consistent results (mortality, HR 0.679, 95% CI 0.570–0.810), reinforcing the robustness of the findings.ConclusionAbatacept was associated with a lower risk of mortality compared with rituximab in patients with RA‐ILD. Because clinicians may preferentially reserve abatacept for less aggressive RA‐ILD, residual confounding by indication cannot be excluded; thus, the association should not be interpreted as proof of causality. Prospective randomized trials are needed to confirm whether abatacept confers a true survival advantage.image
DOI: 10.1002/art.43332
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43332-2025-08-13-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>