<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:17:13 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:17:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Unlocking the potential: Cannabidiol (CBD) as a promising anti-tumor agent</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phymed.2025.157737</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 21
Autoren: Shuqin Duan, Mingyu Liu, Zhechao An, Ziyun Zhong, Xin Guan, Xin Liu, Zheng Zhang, Fan Yang
Journal: Phytomedicine
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.phymed.2025.157737
ISSN: 0944-7113
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.phymed.2025.157737-2026-01-18-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Prevalence and factors associated with the use of complementary and alternative medicine among PCOS patients</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05084-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 19
Autoren: Dahira Sani Ya’u, Habibah binti Abdul Hamid, Siti Farhana binti Md Pauzi, Siti Nawwal Ahmad Nasfy, Norhasmah Sulaiman
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-16
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05084-6
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05084-6-2026-01-18-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy of phospholipid-bound omega-3 versus standard omega-3 in patients with hypertriglyceridemia: a randomized clinical trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-026-05245-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Miguel Urina-Triana, David Gabriel David-Pardo, Manuel Urina-Triana, Jhesua Valencia, Anthony Bernal-Martínez, Daniela Urina-Jassir, Erick Orozco-Acosta, Tarec K. Elajami
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-10
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-026-05245-1
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-026-05245-1-2026-01-18-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of aromatic stimulation on CPAP adherence and sleep quality in patients with obstructive sleep apnea: a pilot study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05243-9</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Erina Ishimizu, Ayako Inoshita, Yo Suzuki, Masahiro Nakamura, Takatoshi Kasai, Fumihiko Matsumoto
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-09
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Purpose
                    Continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy remains the cornerstone of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) treatment, considerably reducing the risk of cardiovascular complications and improving patient outcomes. However, adherence to CPAP therapy is a major challenge and poor compliance limits its efficacy. This study investigated the potential of aromatherapy, a noninvasive, cost-effective intervention, to improve CPAP adherence and enhance sleep quality in patients with OSA.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    
                      A prospective observational pilot study was conducted in patients with obstructive sleep apnea who demonstrated poor CPAP adherence (&amp;lt; 70% usage and &amp;lt; 4 h/night). Participants were exposed to lavender or cypress aroma oil during sleep. Pre- and post-intervention subjective sleep measures Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) and Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS), and objective CPAP usage metrics were collected. Normally distributed variables were analyzed using paired t-tests, and non-normally distributed variables were analyzed using the Wilcoxon signed-rank test. Statistical significance was set at
                      p
                       &amp;lt; 0.05. A post hoc power analysis was performed based on observed effect sizes for the primary outcomes.
                    
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      Eight patients with OSA (mean age 53.5 years; 4 males, 4 females) participated in the study. Following 67 days of treatment, the median PSQI score significantly improved from 9.0 to 6.5 (
                      p
                       = 0.006), and the median ESS score decreased from 9.0 to 6.5 (
                      p
                       = 0.034). Additionally, CPAP for more than 4 h increased from 5.0% to 25.7% (
                      p
                       = 0.028). The median usage duration improved from 149 to 231 min (
                      p
                       = 0.018). No significant change in apnea hypopnea index (AHI) was observed during CPAP use, decreasing from 3.2 events/h to 1.3 events/h (
                      p
                       = 0.226), which is consistent with the understanding that appropriately applied CPAP maintains effective control of respiratory events.
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Aromatic stimulation with essential oils shows promise in improving both CPAP adherence and sleep quality, offering a novel approach to enhance OSA treatment efficacy.
                  
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05243-9
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05243-9-2026-01-18-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Inhibition of the PI3K signaling pathway in cancer cells by Agrimonia eupatoria L. ethanolic extract: identification of tricoumaroyl spermidine as a potential PI3K inhibitor</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05231-z</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 18
Autoren: Mikayel Ginovyan, Smbat Gevorgyan, Hayarpi Javrushyan, Barbara Kusznierewicz, Izabela Koss-Mikołajczyk, Naira Sahakyan, Agnieszka Bartoszek, Nikolay Avtandilyan
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-06
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05231-z
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-18</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05231-z-2026-01-18-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>