<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 01:04:47 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 01:04:47 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Evenamide reverses schizophrenia-related dysfunction in a neurodevelopmental animal model</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-025-02188-y</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 218
Autoren: Daniela L. Uliana, Rachel A. Walsh, Debora Fabris, Anthony A. Grace
Journal: Neuropsychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-05
DOI: 10.1038/s41386-025-02188-y
ISSN: 0893-133X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-26</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41386-025-02188-y-2025-08-26-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A timeline of reckoning: Tracking the historical rise of antimicrobial resistance across HIV, TB, and malaria</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jgar.2025.07.014</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 174
Autoren: Tayla Williamson, Jack Adderley, Kylie Quinn, Taane G. Clark, Sharon R. Lewin, Christian Doerig
Journal: Journal of Global Antimicrobial Resistance
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jgar.2025.07.014
ISSN: 2213-7165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-26</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jgar.2025.07.014-2025-08-26-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Methylphenidate (Ritalin) does not improve exam performance in an experimental setting</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00213-025-06864-1</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 102
Autoren: Anke Sambeth, Monika Toth, Arjan Blokland
Journal: Psychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-05
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Rationale
            Surveys indicate that about 10–20% of students use medicinal drugs to improve their exam performance. Whether these drugs really improve exam performance has not been examined in an experimental setting yet. This study tested the effects of methylphenidate (MPH; 20 mg) on exam performance either by giving the drug before studying for an exam (day 1, acquiring new information) or before the exam was taken (day 2, retrieving the information).
          
          
            Method
            For this study, a double-blind placebo controlled between-subjects design was applied. The participants were randomly assigned to three groups that were given treatment on the two days: Placebo-Placebo (n = 25), MPH (n = 24), Placebo-MPH (n = 26). The exam contained multiple-choice questions (factual knowledge and inference questions) and open questions (inference).
          
          
            Results
            The data showed that MPH did not improve the exam performance on the three types of questions. In addition, the average grade did not differ between the three groups and the number of participants failing or passing the exam did not differ.
          
          
            Conclusion
            This is a first experimental study showing that MPH does not improve exam performance and should discourage students to take MPH during exam periods.
          
DOI: 10.1007/s00213-025-06864-1
ISSN: 0033-3158
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-26</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s00213-025-06864-1-2025-08-26-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>FDA grants first US approval for decades-old eye drug</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41573-025-00138-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 70
Autoren: Asher Mullard
Journal: Nature Reviews Drug Discovery
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-07
DOI: 10.1038/d41573-025-00138-3
ISSN: 1474-1776
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-26</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/d41573-025-00138-3-2025-08-26-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Investigating Zinc Migration from Rigid Needle Shield to Drug Formulation in Needle Tip of Pre-filled Syringe</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11095-025-03888-2</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 60
Autoren: Guangli Hu, Chengbei Li, Kaitlin Wang, Yongchao Su, William Forrest, Jeffrey Givand, Dario Ferreira Sanchez, Margie Olbinado, Matthias Wagner, Christian Grünzweig, Vladimir Novak
Journal: Pharmaceutical Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-29
DOI: 10.1007/s11095-025-03888-2
ISSN: 0724-8741
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-26</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1007/s11095-025-03888-2-2025-08-26-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>