<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Nutrition &amp; Dietetics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 01:00:44 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 01:00:44 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Day/night fluctuations of breast milk bioactive factors and microbiome</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1618784</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 412
Autoren: Melissa A. Woortman, Haipeng Sun, Jincheng Wang, Filipa Godoy-Vitorino, Angeliz J. Rivera Meléndez, Maribel Campos Rivera, Edna E. Aquino Piñero, Krystin Engelhardt, Lawrence C. Kleinman, Maria G. Dominguez-Bello
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-05
Abstract: IntroductionHuman breast milk is a sophisticated and complex biological fluid that provides crucial nutritional, immunological, and microbial benefits to infants. Hormones exhibit circadian variations in maternal serum, and understanding these fluctuations in breast milk is crucial for assessing infant maturation. This is particularly relevant when expressed breast milk is fed at a different time from when it was originally produced.MethodsThis study examined 24-h variations in breast milk composition by analyzing samples from 38 lactating mothers at four distinct times of the day. Levels of cortisol, melatonin, immunoglobulin A (IgA), lactoferrin, and oxytocin were quantified using ELISA, and microbiome composition was assessed through 16S rRNA sequencing.ResultsSignificant 24-h fluctuations in melatonin and cortisol concentrations were noted, whereas lactoferrin and IgA levels only varied when separating by infant age, maternal BMI, or infant sex. Breast milk microbial composition shifted, with a nocturnal increase in skin-associated bacteria and a diurnal increase in environmental bacteria depending on maternal BMI and infant age. Additionally, milk microbiota alpha diversity increased due to age, but not consistently over all the time points.DiscussionThese differences in 24-h breast milk composition underscore the physiological relevance of maintaining the natural temporal dynamics of breast milk, which may be disrupted when expressed breast milk is fed asynchronously from its time of expression.
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1618784
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1618784-2025-10-10-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Introducing blueberry powder as one of the first complementary foods changes the gut microbiota composition and diversity in U.S. human milk-fed infants: a double-blind, randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2025.1623521</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 242
Autoren: Gabrielle N. E. Glime, Kinzie L. Matzeller, Daniel N. Frank, Cassandra Kotter, Jennifer M. Kofonow, Charles E. Robertson, Carina Venter, Wayne W. Campbell, Nancy F. Krebs, Minghua Tang
Journal: Frontiers in Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-04
Abstract: IntroductionComplementary feeding is a critical period marked by rapid changes in the infant’s diet, nutrient needs, and gut microbiota. However, the effects of specific foods introduced during complementary feeding, such as blueberries, on the developing infant gut microbiota remain unclear. Our primary aim was to evaluate the effect of daily consumption of freeze-dried blueberry powder during complementary feeding on gut microbiota development in U. S. human-milk-fed infants.MethodsIn a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled feeding trial, infants from the Denver metro area (Colorado, United States) were randomly assigned to consume up to 10 g of freeze-dried blueberry powder or an isocaloric placebo powder, combined with liquid or semi-liquid and served as a puree, daily from 5 to 12 months of age. Stool samples were collected bimonthly to assess gut microbial diversity and composition. Novel taxa were identified through parsimony insertion into the SILVA reference phylogenetic tree. Infant length, weight and dietary intakes were also assessed.ResultsSeventy-six caregiver-infant pairs consented and enrolled in the study and 61 completed the study (blueberry group n = 30, placebo group n = 31). There were no differences between groups in energy or macronutrient intakes from complementary foods. Growth z-scores were comparable between groups. Gut microbiota alpha diversity increased over time in both groups (effect of time p &amp;amp;lt; 0.001). Several taxa, including Veillonaceae, Flavonifractor, Subdoligranulum, and Butryicicoccus (all more abundant in the blueberry group), and Actinomyces, Escherichia, Streptococcus, and Romboutsia (more abundant in the placebo group) had group-by-time interactions that trended toward significance.ConclusionIntroducing blueberries as one of the first complementary foods, in the form of freeze-dried powder served as a puree, exerts potential benefits in gut microbiota development and maturation in this cohort of human-milk-fed infants.Systematic review registrationhttps://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT05006989.
DOI: 10.3389/fnut.2025.1623521
ISSN: 2296-861X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.3389/fnut.2025.1623521-2025-10-10-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of Vitamin D2 Supplementation on 25-Hydroxyvitamin D3 Status: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/nutrit/nuaf166</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 237
Autoren: Emily I G Brown, Andrea L Darling, Tracey M Robertson, Kathryn H Hart, Jie Li, Cathie Martin, Martin J Warren, Colin P Smith, Susan A Lanham-New, Ruan M Elliott
Journal: Nutrition Reviews
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-18
Abstract: Abstract
               
                  Context
                  Researchers have identified differences in metabolic activity between vitamins D2 and D3. Moreover, it is suspected from randomized controlled trial data that vitamin D2 supplementation increases the metabolic clearance of 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 [25(OH)D3], but this effect has yet to be quantified.
               
               
                  Objective
                  This study sought to undertake a systematic review and meta-analysis of the effect of vitamin D2 supplementation on serum 25(OH)D3 concentrations.
               
               
                  Data Sources
                  PUBMED was searched for articles published from January 1, 1975, to February 1, 2023. Of the 202 articles retrieved, 20 were included in this review, and of those, 11 were suitable for meta-analysis.
               
               
                  Data Extraction
                  Randomized controlled trials reporting either baseline and postintervention serum 25(OH)D3 concentrations (nmol/L) or absolute changes in concentrations were included. Random-effects meta-analyses were calculated using Review Manager (version 5.3; The Cochrane Collaboration). Mean differences were reported with 95% CIs.
               
               
                  Data Analysis
                  In meta-analyses there was a reduction in serum 25(OH)D3 after vitamin D2 supplementation compared with control for end-of-trial between-groups data (random weighted mean difference [WMD] = −17.99 nmol/L; 95% CI, −25.86 to −10.12; P &amp;amp;lt; .00001) and absolute change over the trial (random WMD = −9.25 nmol/L; 95% CI, −14.40 to −4.10; P = .0004).
               
               
                  Conclusions
                  Study participants who received vitamin D2 supplementation showed statistically significant reductions in serum 25(OH)D3 concentrations, compared to controls without supplementation. An inverse relationship between vitamin D2 and D3 concentrations has been proposed in the literature. A regulatory mechanism that increases the disposal rate of 25(OH)D after an increase in vitamin D concentrations could explain these results. However, further research is needed to establish whether vitamins D2 and D3 elicit different changes in overall vitamin D metabolism that might influence clinical advice to recommend vitamin D3 supplements over vitamin D2 supplements, where appropriate.
               
DOI: 10.1093/nutrit/nuaf166
ISSN: 0029-6643
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/nutrit/nuaf166-2025-10-10-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Young Children’s (Aged 3 to 8 Years) Food and Beverage Brand Exposure on YouTube and YouTube Kids: An Observational Study and Content Analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.010</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 228
Autoren: Frances Fleming-Milici, Haley Gershman, Hanako O. Agresta, Melissa McCann, Jennifer Harris
Journal: Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.010
ISSN: 2212-2672
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.jand.2025.05.010-2025-10-10-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Ingestion of a lipid-rich meat matrix blunts the postexercise increase of myofibrillar protein synthesis rates in healthy adults: a randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.09.001</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Score: 139
Autoren: Žan Zupančič, Andrew T Askow, Takeshi M Barnes, Max T Deutz, Alexander V Ulanov, Ryan N Dilger, Anna C Dilger, Jared W Willard, Richard WA Mackenzie, Jocelyn E Harseim, Diego Hernández-Saavedra, Nicholas A Burd
Journal: The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.09.001
ISSN: 0002-9165
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-10</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ajcnut.2025.09.001-2025-10-10-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>