<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:07:37 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:07:37 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Reduction in Renal Relapse and Preservation of Long‐Term Kidney Function After Lupus Low Disease Activity in Patients With Lupus Nephritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/acr.25611</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 37
Autoren: Chak Kwan Cheung, Desmond Y. H. Yap, Ka Lai Lee, Philip H. Li, Iris Y. K. Tang, Chak Sing Lau, Shirley C. W. Chan
Journal: Arthritis Care &amp;amp; Research
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-21
Abstract: 
                    Objective
                    Lupus low disease activity state (LLDAS) is a validated treatment target in systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), but limited studies have explored the role of LLDAS in lupus nephritis (LN). This study aims to investigate the frequency and predictors of LLDAS attainment and its benefit on LN relapse and renal function preservation in patients with LN.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Patients with LN during 2010 to 2020 in Queen Mary Hospital and Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital were included in the discovery cohort and validation cohort, respectively. Complete renal response (CRR), partial renal response (PRR), LLDAS, and Definition Of Remission In SLE (DORIS) remission were assessed at 12 months. Regression analysis was performed to identify risk factors of LN relapse. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves were used to evaluate target attainment and long‐term kidney function.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    
                      A total of 245 patients with LN (discovery cohort n = 143 and validation cohort n = 102) were included. At 12 months, 57 of 143 (40%), 14 of 143 (10%), 70 of 143 (49%), and 15 of 143 (10%) patients achieved CRR, PRR, LLDAS, and DORIS remission, respectively. Attainment of both CRR/PRR and LLDAS at 12 months was associated with best relapse‐free survival (
                      P
                      &amp;lt; 0.001). Multivariate analysis showed independent association of CRR/PRR and LLDAS with LN relapse risk reduction (CRR/PRR: hazard ratio [HR] 0.31,
                      P
                      = 0.007; LLDAS: HR 0.38,
                      P
                      = 0.029). LLDAS attainment predicts renal function preservation with satisfactory performance in both the discovery and validation cohorts (area under the curve of the ROC 0.71).
                    
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    LLDAS is an attainable target in LN comparable to CRR/PRR. Attainment of both targets is associated with additional benefits on relapse risk reduction. Early LLDAS attainment is associated with renal function preservation.
                    
                      
                        
                          image
                        
                      
                    
                  
DOI: 10.1002/acr.25611
ISSN: 2151-464X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/acr.25611-2025-11-25-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>EULAR 2025 classification criteria for haemochromatosis arthropathy</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 36
Autoren: Patrick DW Kiely, Stephanie Finzel, Bayram Farisogullari, Graeme J. Carroll, Geraldine McCarthy, John Stack, Simone Parisi, Graça Porto, Pascal Richette, Gyorgy Nagy, Marton Weidl, Ann Rosenthal, Pascal Guggenbuhl, Katarzyna J. Banaszkiewicz, Svenja Engelhardt, Jeremy D. Shearman, David Mitchell, Jane Barker, Valerie Brueton, Barbara Butzeck, Philip Coathup, Howard Don, Jacqueline Dowsett, Marie Duncan, Tracey Dunleavy, Ian Fish, Allin Hoggarth, Mark McKinnon, James Minter, Tim Osborne, Marguerite Smith, Christine Wright, Pedro M. Machado
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.10.003-2025-11-25-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Associations of Specific Pesticides and Incident Rheumatoid Arthritis Among Female Spouses in the Agricultural Health Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/art.43318</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 31
Autoren: Christine G. Parks, Darya Leyzarovich, Ghassan B. Hamra, Karen H. Costenbader, Dazhe Chen, Jonathan N. Hofmann, Laura E. Beane Freeman, Dale P. Sandler
Journal: Arthritis &amp;amp; Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-20
Abstract: 
                    Objectives
                    Growing evidence suggests farming and agricultural pesticide use may be associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA), but few studies have examined specific pesticides and RA among women living on farms, who may personally use pesticides or may be indirectly exposed. We investigated pesticide use and RA risk among female spouses of licensed pesticide applicators in the Agricultural Health Study.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    Participants were enrolled in 1993 to 1997 in North Carolina and Iowa (N = 32,126). Incident RA cases were identified in follow‐up questionnaires (1999–2021) and confirmed by medical records, relevant medication use, or Medicare claims data (1999–2016) or identified from Medicare claims if lacking questionnaire data on RA. Noncases reported no RA and had no RA Medicare claims. Among those with complete covariate data (N = 410 cases and 21,850 noncases), we examined associations with pesticide classes and 32 specific pesticides (personal lifetime use reported at enrollment, updated in 1999–2003). We calculated odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs), adjusting for age, state, education, smoking pack‐years smoking, body mass index, and correlated pesticides (ρ &amp;gt; 0.35).
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Incident RA was associated with use of organochlorine (DDT: OR 1.89, 95% CI 1.30–2.75; lindane: OR 1.97, 95% CI 1.12–3.47) and organophosphate insecticides (coumaphos: OR 2.32, 95% CI 1.29–4.19; malathion: OR 1.21, 95% CI 0.91–1.62), the carbamate insecticide carbofuran (OR 1.87, 95% CI 0.97–3.63), and permethrin and pyrethroid insecticides on crops (OR 1.56, 95% CI 0.92–2.64) and livestock (OR 1.69, 95% CI 1.07–2.68). RA was not associated with using herbicides, except for metribuzin (OR 1.88, 95% CI 0.94–3.79). The fungicides captan (OR 1.78, 95% CI 1.13–2.83) and metalaxyl (OR 2.49, 95% CI 1.41–4.40) were also associated with RA.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    These findings indicate that persistent organochlorine insecticides and some pesticides also used in public health or residential settings may increase RA risk in women.
                  
DOI: 10.1002/art.43318
ISSN: 2326-5191
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1002/art.43318-2025-11-25-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Advances in the pathophysiology, diagnosis and treatment of Takayasu arteritis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41584-025-01309-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 23
Autoren: Amr H. Sawalha, Durga P. Misra, Ruchika Goel, Fatma Alibaz-Oner, Kaitlin A. Quinn, Peter C. Grayson, Haner Direskeneli
Journal: Nature Reviews Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-06
DOI: 10.1038/s41584-025-01309-7
ISSN: 1759-4790
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41584-025-01309-7-2025-11-25-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Methotrexate use in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis associated-interstitial lung disease: a systematic review</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/rheumatology/keaf538</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 19
Autoren: Ines Mahmoud, Fatma Majdoub, Selma Bouden, Leila Rouached, Olfa Saidane, Raoudha Tekaya, Aicha Ben Tekaya, Leila Abdelmoula
Journal: Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-24
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Objectives
                    To assess the progression of the interstitial lung disease related to rheumatoid arthritis (RA-ILD) with Methotrexate (MTX) exposure, and to evaluate the lung involvement in RA non-ILD patients with MTX exposure.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    A systematic review was performed including studies of RA patients reporting the effect of MTX on ILD, as a primary or secondary end point.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Sixteen studies were included in the systematic review. The total number of patients was 36 444, of which 18 548 (50.8%) were declared on MTX. Patients on MTX were classified into two groups, based on whether they were experiencing ILD. Comparison with control groups was performed to assess the development and/or the progression of ILD in MTX users. Non exposed MTX subjects (N-MTX) were considered as the control group in 14 studies. To evaluate the pulmonary state, studies carried out different evaluation methods: High-Resolution Computed Tomography (10 studies), pulmonary function tests (8 studies), arterial blood gas analysis (one study) and survival (5 studies). MTX was not associated with a risk of developing ILD (9 studies). Five studies suggested that MTX was not associated with the progression of RA-ILD. An accelerated decline in lung function was observed with low-dose MTX (one study). Better survival was shown in MTX patients compared with the N-MTX group (one study). In one study, MTX use was significantly associated with the development of acute exacerbations.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    MTX appears to have no association with an increased risk of ILD and/or its progression in RA patients.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/rheumatology/keaf538
ISSN: 1462-0324
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/rheumatology/keaf538-2025-11-25-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>