<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 01:01:17 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 01:01:17 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Deaths following illicit ketamine use in England, Wales and Northern Ireland 1999–2024: An update report to inform the reclassification debate</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1177/02698811251373058</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 377
Autoren: Jade Pullen, John M. Corkery, Rebecca McKnight, Caroline S. Copeland
Journal: Journal of Psychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-29
Abstract: 
            Background:
            Ketamine is increasingly used in the United Kingdom in non-clinical settings for its psychoactive effects, with rising reports of harms including hospital admissions, dependence and deaths. In light of current debates surrounding the reclassification of ketamine under the Misuse of Drugs Act 1971, up-to-date surveillance of associated mortality is warranted.
          
          
            Aims:
            We aimed to quantify trends in deaths following illicit ketamine use in England, Wales and Northern Ireland, and to examine changes in demographic and contextual characteristics since the last national analysis which comprised illicit ketamine deaths up to 2019.
          
          
            Methods:
            Cases where illicit ketamine was detected at post-mortem were extracted from the National Programme on Substance Use Mortality and analysed.
          
          
            Results:
            There were 696 deaths identified with illicit ketamine between 1999 and 2024. Annual deaths increased over 10-fold from 2014 (15 deaths) to 2024 (197 projected deaths). Whilst absolute deaths implicating illicit ketamine rose (2014: 6 deaths; 2023: 123 projected deaths), the proportion of deaths where illicit ketamine was implicated in causing death declined (2014: 60.0% of cases; 2024: 42.6% of cases). Concurrently, polydrug use increased (median number of co-administered substances 1999–2004: 3; 2005–2009: 3, 2010–2014: 4, 2015–2019: 6; 2020–2024: 6), and the demographic profile of decedents shifted towards greater deprivation and dependence-related contexts.
          
          
            Discussion and Conclusions:
            There has been an acceleration in deaths following illicit ketamine in recent years, which are increasingly featuring complex patterns of polydrug use and socio-economic vulnerability. Policy responses must extend beyond single-substance legislative controls to encompass harm reduction, treatment integration, and social support strategies.
          
DOI: 10.1177/02698811251373058
ISSN: 0269-8811
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1177/02698811251373058-2025-10-09-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mass balance, pharmacokinetics, metabolism, and excretion of radiolabeled acoziborole, a potential novel treatment for human African trypanosomiasis, following single microtracer oral dose to humans</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.00580-25</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 145
Autoren: Jean-Yves Gillon, François Simon, Sharan Sidhu, Mathieu Louis, Delphine Launay, Valérie Wauthier, Marta Pelay-Gimeno, Lotte van Andel, Sabrina Loyau, Sandra Rembry, Estelle Weinling, Antoine Tarral
Journal: Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-22
Abstract: ABSTRACT
          
            
            
              Acoziborole is an oxaborole 6-carboxamide active against
              Trypanosoma brucei gambiense
              and
              rhodesiense
              , the parasites responsible for human African trypanosomiasis. This open-label, phase I study in six healthy male participants evaluated the mass balance, pharmacokinetics, metabolism pathways, and excretion of a single oral 960 mg dose of [
              14
              C]-acoziborole. Blood, plasma, and feces were collected for 120 days and urine for 16 days. The excretion balance and systemic exposure of total circulating radioactivity were determined using accelerator mass spectrometry. Metabolism profiling was performed in pools of plasma, urine, and feces. Liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry quantified acoziborole and its metabolite SCYX-3109 in plasma and urine. By Day 60, 87.3% of the total radioactivity had been recovered (10.9% and 74.2% of the total dose in urine and in feces, respectively), with an excretion increment of &amp;lt;1% between Days 59 and 61. Mean ratios of total radioactivity indicated an equivalent distribution between blood cells and plasma. The concentration-time profiles of total radioactivity and acoziborole in plasma were similar. In plasma, acoziborole accounted for 95.1%, an oxidized form of acoziborole for 2.3% of the total radioactivity, while SCYX-3109 was not detected. Seven metabolites (oxidative deboronation, glucuronidation, and mono-oxidation) were detected in urine with individual abundances relative to the dose of 0.1–2.1%; unchanged acoziborole accounted for 0.6%. In feces, acoziborole, SCYX-3109, and two other oxidized or deboronated forms of acoziborole represented 33.6%, 12.3%, and 2.3% of the dose, respectively. Acoziborole showed good absorption, limited metabolism, minimal urinary elimination, and predominant but slow biliary-fecal elimination.
            
          
DOI: 10.1128/aac.00580-25
ISSN: 0066-4804
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1128/aac.00580-25-2025-10-09-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Targeting Tregs in T1DM: bridging heterogeneity, mechanisms, and clinical progress</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2025.08.004</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 96
Autoren: Yutong Li, Eyad Elkord
Journal: Trends in Pharmacological Sciences
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.tips.2025.08.004
ISSN: 0165-6147
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.tips.2025.08.004-2025-10-09-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Coffee for the liver: a mechanistic approach</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2025.117338</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 95
Autoren: Eduardo E. Vargas-Pozada, Erika Ramos-Tovar, Linda Vanessa Márquez-Quiroga, Karla Jocelyn Ortega-Carballo, Pablo Muriel
Journal: Biochemical Pharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bcp.2025.117338
ISSN: 0006-2952
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bcp.2025.117338-2025-10-09-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Chronic treatment with fluoxetine regulates mitochondrial features and plasticity-associated transcriptomic pathways in parvalbumin-positive interneurons of prefrontal cortex</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-025-02219-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacy
Score: 74
Autoren: Elias Jetsonen, Giuliano Didio, Ilida Suleymanova, Indrek Teino, Eero Castrén, Juzoh Umemori
Journal: Neuropsychopharmacology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-08
Abstract: Abstract
          Chronic treatment with fluoxetine, a widely prescribed selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI), is known to promote neural plasticity. The role of fluoxetine in plasticity has been particularly tied to parvalbumin-positive interneurons, a key population of GABAergic neurons that regulate inhibitory tone and network stability. While our previous studies have highlighted fluoxetine-induced plasticity in the visual cortex and hippocampus, its cell-type-specific effects in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) remain unclear. This study aims to investigate the effects of chronic fluoxetine treatment on PV-positive (PV+) cells, identified using PV-IRES-Cre-driven reporter expression in the PFC. Using Translating Ribosome Affinity Purification (TRAP), we found that fluoxetine treatment altered the expression of 50 distinct biological pathways. Downregulated pathways are involved in mitochondrial ATP production, including components of the electron transport chain, and ribosomes. Upregulated pathways were associated with phosphatase activity, ion channel function, and cytoskeletal remodeling —molecules broadly implicated in synaptic signaling and plasticity-related processes. In FACS-sorted cells, mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) expression was significantly increased in PV+ cells of the PFC, while intracellular ATP levels remained unchanged. Immunohistochemical analyses demonstrated reduced PV expression and weakened perineuronal nets in specific PFC subregions, suggesting a plasticity-permissive state in PV+ cells. TOMM22 signal intensity in PV+ cells showed a slight but significant increase in the prelimbic region, suggesting potential compensatory mitochondrial biogenesis despite transcriptomic downregulation of mitochondrial genes. Our findings reveal that chronic fluoxetine induces coordinated transcriptional, structural alterations in PV+ cells of the PFC, including shifts in mitochondrial-related gene expression and plasticity-associated pathways. These changes may contribute to region-specific shifts in cortical inhibition and plasticity, complementing previous reports of fluoxetine-mediated behavioral modulation.
DOI: 10.1038/s41386-025-02219-8
ISSN: 0893-133X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-10-09</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41386-025-02219-8-2025-10-09-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>