<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 01:05:47 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 01:05:47 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Korean medicine registry for allergic rhinitis in real-world settings (KOREA-R): a multicenter registry protocol</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05030-6</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Boram Lee, Gyu Tae Chang, Hyelim Lee, Sun Haeng Lee, Tae Hwan Kim, Mi Mi Ko, Sumin Seo, Bok-Nam Seo, Su Eun Lim, Mi Ju Son
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05030-6
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05030-6-2025-08-25-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Nanoparticles from grape seed extract inhibit inflammatory cytokines and ameliorate CCl4-induced hepatotoxicity</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05005-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Neveen Adel Madbouly, Doaa Mohammad Ali, Alyaa Ahmed Farid
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-19
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Xenobiotic-induced liver injury is a clinically reverent condition which may influence the development of steatohepatitis via affecting numerous pathways such as oxidative stress, inflammation, mitochondorial functioning and fatty acid biosynthesis. The current study was conducted to survey the antioxidant effect of grape seeds extract nanoparticles (GS extract NPs) against CCl4-induced oxidative stress, hepatic dysfunction and inflammatory changes.
          
          
            Methods
            Hydroethanolic Grape seed (GS) extract was prepared and characterized using high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), inductively coupled plasma–mass spectrometry (ICP-MS) and gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC-MS). Then, GS extract NPs were synthesized and in vitro antioxidant, anticoagulant, cytotoxicity and anti-inflammatory testes confirmed biological activity. Finally, Twenty-five male Sprague-Dawley rats were divided into five groups (n = 5/group). Either GS extract (200 mg/kg/day) or GS extract NPs (100 mg/kg/day) were orally administrated independently to CCL4-intoxicated (0.5 ml/kg twice a week for 3 weeks) rats. Four weeks after the treatment, serum levels of alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALP) were monitored. In addition, hepatic Malondialdehyde (MDA), Superoxide dismutases (SOD), Glutathione (GSH) and catalase (CAT) and hepatic inflammatory cytokines were assessed.
          
          
            Results
            GS extract NPs were spherical-shaped and regular particles (size: 16.5 to 22.5 nm and zeta potential: -39.42 mv). CCL4 -intoxicated rats showed increase of serum ALT, AST, ALP, elevation in MDA level accompanied by a decline in SOD, GSH and CAT levels in liver, compared with CCL4-untreated rats. Immunologically, serum C-Reactive Protein (CRP) and hepatic interleukin 1β (IL-1β), IL-4, IL-6 and Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha (TNF-α) showed significant elevation, compared with CCL4 -untreated rats. Conversely, GS extract NPs supplementation potentially ameliorate hepatic functions by normalization of serum ALT, AST and ALP, reduced MDA level, improved antioxidant CAT, regulated liver inflammatory cytokines via maximal reduction of hepatic IL-1β, IL-4, IL-6 and TNF-α. 
          
          
            Conclusion
            GS extract NPs augmented the antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties of GS extract thereby protecting the liver against oxidative stress induced by CCl4 as hepatic xenobiotic.
          
          
            Clinical trial number
            Not applicable.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05005-7
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05005-7-2025-08-25-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The effects of Cissus quadrangularis on bone-related biomarkers in humans: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-04995-8</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Mingkwan Na Takuathung, Jakkrit Aisara, Suphunwadee Sawong, Nut Koonrungsesomboon
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-24
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Maintaining bone health is vital, particularly for aging populations prone to bone disorders. Cissus quadrangularis (CQ), a traditional medicinal plant, is increasingly recognized for its potential benefits in promoting bone health, including the effects on bone-related biomarkers promoting bone healing and bone density improvement. This study aimed to evaluate the effects of CQ on bone-related biomarkers in humans as the primary objective and to assess its impact on other clinical outcomes as a secondary objective.
          
          
            Methods
            A systematic search of PubMed, Embase, Scopus, and the Cochrane Library databases was conducted up to April 2025. This systematic review included studies with participants receiving Cissus quadrangularis, those reporting bone biomarkers, and those with a randomized controlled design involving human participants. No restrictions were placed on age, sex, disease severity, or administration route. The quality of the studies included was assessed using the revised Cochrane risk-of-bias tool (RoB-2), while the overall strength of evidence was appraised using the GRADE approach. The summary effect measure was the standardized mean difference (SMD) with 95% confidence intervals (95% CI).
          
          
            Results
            Seven studies, comprising a total of 354 participants, met the inclusion criteria for meta-analysis. The analysis revealed that CQ intervention significantly elevated serum parathyroid hormone levels (SMD = 1.23; 95% CI = 0.79 to 1.67; p &amp;lt; 0.0001). However, the CQ intervention did not result in significant changes in other bone-related biomarkers, including calcium, phosphorus, and serum alkaline phosphatase. The RoB-2 revealed that most studies had some concerns about bias, with two evaluated as having a high risk. The certainty of evidence was very low for all four parameters assessed by GRADE.
          
          
            Conclusion
            The CQ intervention was significantly associated with increased serum parathyroid hormone levels, with no significant effects on other bone-related biomarkers. Although there were a limited number of studies, these findings suggest its potential for modulating bone health; however, further research is needed to confirm these results and explore its clinical applications.
          
          
            Trial registration
            The study protocol was prospectively registered with PROSPERO, and the registration number is CRD42023435351.
          
          
            Clinical trial number
            Not applicable.
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-04995-8
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-04995-8-2025-08-25-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Efficacy and safety of YQFM (YiQiFuMai lyophilized injection) on acute ischemic stroke (FAST): rationale and design for a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-025-05036-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 15
Autoren: Yingzhi Xu, Li Sun, Zhaoyou Meng, Xinxing Lai, Dayong Ma, Yuqiu An, Boxuan Du, Qiaosheng Ren, Ying Gao, Kegang Cao
Journal: BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-22
Abstract: Abstract
          
            Background
            Low blood pressure at acute ischemic stroke onset is associated with both short- and long-term adverse outcomes. Studies have shown that YQFM (YiQiFuMai lyophilized injection) can ameliorate neurological deficits in ischemic stroke.However, all of these studies are all small-sample clinical observations lacking rigorous study design for AIS with inappropriate blood pressure.
          
          
            Aims
            To describe the design of the YQFM aimed at reducing the disability rate in AIS patients with inappropriate blood pressure.
          
          
            Methods
            This trial is a prospective, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, superiority trial aimed at evaluating the efficacy and safety of YQFM in reducing the disability rate in patients with acute hypoperfusion stroke within 90 days. We will recruit 480 patients with AIS within 48 h of symptom onset from 24 hospitals, who have large atherosclerosis, systolic pressure ≤ 155 mmHg, and an NIHSS score of 4–18. Eligible patients will be randomly assigned to receive either YQFM or 0.9% NaCl injection once daily for 10 days and will be followed up until the 90th day after stroke onset.The primary outcome will be the proportion of patients with mRS ≤ 2 at 90 days after patient recruitment. Secondary outcomes will include the proportion of early neurological deterioration at 7 days, patient self-reported outcomes and the syndrome score at 10 days, MMSE scale and BI scale at 90 days.During the trial, adverse events will be recorded. These data will be analyzed according to the predetermined statistical analysis plan.
          
          
            Conclusion
            This study is the first randomized controlled double-blind trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of YQFM in patients with AIS. This trial will provide evidence-based data for YQFM application in AIS with inappropriate blood pressure.
          
          
            Clinical trial registration
            ChiCTR2300074125 was registered on 31 July, 2023. For more information, please visit Clinical Trials.gov at https://www.chictr.org.cn/showproj.html?Proj=200686.
          
          
            Graphical Abstract
          
DOI: 10.1186/s12906-025-05036-0
ISSN: 2662-7671
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12906-025-05036-0-2025-08-25-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Microbiological Risk Assessment and Safety Evaluation of Widely Used Herbal Pharmaceuticals</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Integrative &amp; Complementary Medicine
Score: 13
Autoren: Naveen Kumar Ramachandrappa, Kalyan Dola, Vakdevi Validandi, Senthilkumar Balakrishnan, Philip Raj Abraham, Aditi Ashutosh Kaledhonkar, SDG Gauthami, K Srinivasu, Surekha Mullapudi Venkata
Journal: Journal of Herbal Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047
ISSN: 2210-8033
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-25</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.hermed.2025.101047-2025-08-25-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>