<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rehabilitation) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 01:11:00 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 01:11:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>The content of diagnostic information has an immediate effect on pain with loading in people with midportion Achilles tendinopathy: a randomized clinical experiment</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101244</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 23
Autoren: Nigel J Travers, Mervyn J Travers, William Gibson, James R Debenham, Dana A Hince, Benedict M Wand
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101244
ISSN: 1413-3555
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.bjpt.2025.101244-2025-08-02-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effect of astaxanthin supplementation on cycling performance, muscle damage biomarkers and oxidative stress in young adults: a randomized controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13102-025-01221-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 22
Autoren: Jung-Piao Tsao, Pei-Yu Wu, Hsu-Tung Kuo, Wei-Hsien Hong, Chih-Chieh Chen, Min-Yu Wang, Mallikarjuna Korivi, I-Shiung Cheng
Journal: BMC Sports Science, Medicine and Rehabilitation
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-04
DOI: 10.1186/s13102-025-01221-3
ISSN: 2052-1847
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s13102-025-01221-3-2025-08-02-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Hip muscle strength in patients with chronic ankle instability: A systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ptsp.2025.07.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 21
Autoren: Jiawei Zheng, Bing Xu, Xinxin Xiong, Jian Chen
Journal: Physical Therapy in Sport
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ptsp.2025.07.007
ISSN: 1466-853X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ptsp.2025.07.007-2025-08-02-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Effectiveness of Painful Versus Nonpainful Exercise on Pain Intensity, Disability, and Other Patient-Reported Outcomes in Adults With Chronic Musculoskeletal Pain: An Updated Systematic Review With Meta-Analysis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13253</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 16
Autoren: Ivy Tran, Mitchell T. Gibbs, Nathan Yu, Jared K. Powell, Benjamin E. Smith, Matthew D. Jones
Journal: Journal of Orthopaedic &amp;amp; Sports Physical Therapy
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-01
Abstract:  OBJECTIVE: The purpose of this study was to determine the effect of painful versus nonpainful exercise on pain, disability, and other patient-reported outcomes in adults with chronic musculoskeletal pain.  DESIGN: This study is an intervention systematic review with meta-analysis.  LITERATURE SEARCH: Electronic databases (CENTRAL, EMBASE, CINAHL, PubMed, and PsycINFO) and trial registers ( ClinicalTrials.gov , ANZCTR, World Health Organization International Clinical Trials Registry Platform) were searched from October 2016 to May 2024.  STUDY SELECTION CRITERIA: We included randomized controlled trials that compared painful exercise to nonpainful exercise in adults with chronic musculoskeletal pain.  DATA SYNTHESIS: Data were analyzed using random-effects meta-analysis and narrative synthesis. We assessed risk of bias using the Cochrane RoB2 tool and certainty of evidence using the Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluations framework.  RESULTS: We included 16 trials (reported across 18 studies). There was no difference in the effect of painful versus nonpainful exercise on pain intensity or disability in the short, medium, or long term or pain catastrophizing or fear avoidance in the short term. The confidence intervals were wide. Narrative synthesis found similar results for quality of life, self-efficacy, mood, and adverse events. All trials were at high risk of bias, and certainty of evidence was very low to low.  CONCLUSION: The effect of painful versus nonpainful exercise on patient-reported outcomes in adults with chronic musculoskeletal pain was unclear. Pain during exercise may not need to be avoided to allow for symptomatic and functional improvement. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 2025;55(8):527-537. Epub 10 June 2025. https://doi.org/10.2519/jospt.2025.13253 
DOI: 10.2519/jospt.2025.13253
ISSN: 0190-6011
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2519/jospt.2025.13253-2025-08-02-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>No drugs, more sex? And Rock’n Roll: effective non-operative treatments and practical management strategies for older adults with lumbar spinal stenosis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12998-025-00590-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rehabilitation
Score: 15
Autoren: Carlo Ammendolia
Journal: Chiropractic &amp;amp; Manual Therapies
Veröffentlicht: 2025-07-21
Abstract: Abstract
          Lumbar spinal stenosis is a growing problem among older adults, associated with significant disability and socio-economic burden. Neurogenic claudication is the most common clinical syndrome caused by LSS with pain being the predominant symptom and limited walking the main impairment. Lumbar spinal stenosis can also impact sexual function in older adults, necessitating greater awareness of this association. Pain and impaired function can lead to psychosocial distress, including hopelessness, anxiety, and isolation, further compounding disability. Recent clinical practice guidelines recommend non-operative treatment as the first-line approach, including manual therapy, exercise, and education. However, these guidelines lack details on the practical application of these interventions in clinical practice. This narrative review explores the epidemiology of lumbar spinal stenosis, the evidence supporting non-operative care, and practical management strategies. It also highlights the relationship between sexual dysfunction and lumbar spinal stenosis.
DOI: 10.1186/s12998-025-00590-3
ISSN: 2045-709X
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-08-02</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1186/s12998-025-00590-3-2025-08-02-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>