<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:58:18 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:58:18 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Heat-related mortality in Europe during 2024 and health emergency forecasting to reduce preventable deaths</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03954-7</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 822
Autoren: Tomáš Janoš, Marcos Quijal-Zamorano, Natalia Shartova, Elisa Gallo, Raúl Fernando Méndez Turrubiates, Nadia Denisse Beltrán Barrón, Fabien Peyrusse, Joan Ballester
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-22
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03954-7
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03954-7-2025-09-27-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Dietary saturated fatty acids promote lung myeloid cell inflammasome activation and IL-1β–mediated inflammation in mice and humans</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 454
Autoren: Sam J. McCright, Olivia Harding, Julia Chini, Nicole DeMarco, Li-Yin Hung, Christopher F. Pastore, Wenyun Lu, Joshua Rabinowitz, Jorge Henao-Mejia, De’Broski R. Herbert, Lisa R. Young, David A. Hill
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-08-27
Abstract: Resident tissue macrophages and monocytes (RTMs) integrate local and systemic signals to coordinate immune cell function at homeostasis and in response to inflammatory stimuli. Obesity-associated metabolic dysfunction drives the development of RTM populations that contribute to disease states in multiple tissues. However, the contribution of specific dietary components to innate immune cell activation and function, as opposed to the direct effects of obesity, is largely unknown. Here, we studied the mechanisms by which high-fat (HF) diets shape lung RTM phenotype and function at steady state and influence responses to inflammatory insults. We found that, during HF diet feeding, lung RTMs accumulate saturated long-chain fatty acids, specifically stearic acid (SA), and demonstrate features of NLRP3 inflammasome priming and activation. In vivo, increased dietary SA was sufficient to cause neutrophil-predominant lung inflammation in the steady state and exacerbate a model of innate airway inflammation, whereas increased dietary oleic acid, the monounsaturated counterpart of SA, was sufficient to reduce inflammasome activation in the steady state and attenuate airway inflammation. Depletion of interleukin-1β (IL-1β) or pharmacologic inhibition of the endonuclease inositol requiring enzyme 1α (IRE1α) protected against SA-induced exacerbated lung inflammation. Last, we identified a population of lung monocytes with hallmarks of HF diet–induced RTM activation that were present in samples from obese humans with asthma. Together, these results identify a class of dietary lipids that regulate lung RTM phenotype and function in the steady state and modulate the severity of inflammation in the lung.
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.adp5653-2025-09-27-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Targeting dormant tumor cells to prevent recurrent breast cancer: a randomized phase 2 trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03877-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 372
Autoren: Angela DeMichele, Amy S. Clark, Emily Shea, Lauren J. Bayne, Christopher J. Sterner, Killian Rohn, Samantha Dwyer, Tien-chi Pan, Isoris Nivar, Yan Chen, Paul Wileyto, Lindsay R. Berry, Shannon Deluca, Jessica Savage, Igor Makhlin, Dhruv K. Pant, Heather Martin, Adetutu Egunsola, Nathan Mears, Brooke L. Goodspeed, Elizabeth M. Chislock, Jewell Graves, Jianping Wang, Natalie Shih, George K. Belka, Don Berry, Anupma Nayak, Michael Feldman, Lewis A. Chodosh
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-02
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03877-3
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03877-3-2025-09-27-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Macrovascular and microvascular outcomes of metabolic surgery versus GLP-1 receptor agonists in patients with diabetes and obesity</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-025-03893-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 358
Autoren: Hamlet Gasoyan, Mohammad Hesam Alavi, Alexander Zajichek, Nicholas J. Casacchia, Abdullah Al Jabri, James Bena, Xiaoxi Feng, Rickesha Wilson, Ricard Corcelles, W. Scott Butsch, Rishi P. Singh, Nikhil Das, Hejin Jeong, Amgad Mentias, W. H. Wilson Tang, Bartolome Burguera, Raul J. Rosenthal, Steven E. Nissen, Michael B. Rothberg, Ali Aminian
Journal: Nature Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-16
DOI: 10.1038/s41591-025-03893-3
ISSN: 1078-8956
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41591-025-03893-3-2025-09-27-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Longitudinal antibody titers measured after COVID-19 mRNA vaccination can identify individuals at risk for subsequent infection</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.adv4214</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medicine, Research &amp; Experimental
Score: 301
Autoren: Hyeongki Park, Naotoshi Nakamura, Sho Miyamoto, Yoshitaka Sato, Kwang Su Kim, Kosaku Kitagawa, Yurie Kobashi, Yuta Tani, Yuzo Shimazu, Tianchen Zhao, Yoshitaka Nishikawa, Fumiya Omata, Moe Kawashima, Toshiki Abe, Yoshika Saito, Saori Nonaka, Morihito Takita, Chika Yamamoto, Hiroshi Morioka, Katsuhiro Kato, Ken Sagou, Tetsuya Yagi, Takeshi Kawamura, Akira Sugiyama, Aya Nakayama, Yudai Kaneko, Risa Yokokawa Shibata, Kazuyuki Aihara, Tatsuhiko Kodama, Akifumi Kamiyama, Tomokazu Tamura, Takasuke Fukuhara, Kenji Shibuya, Tadaki Suzuki, Shingo Iwami, Masaharu Tsubokura
Journal: Science Translational Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-09-17
Abstract: A key issue in the post–COVID-19 pandemic era is the ongoing administration of COVID-19 vaccines. Repeated vaccination is essential for preparing against currently circulating and newly emerging severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) variants. However, optimizing vaccination strategies is crucial to efficiently manage medical resources and establish an effective vaccination framework. Therefore, a strategy to identify poor responders with lower sustained antibody titers would be beneficial because these individuals should be considered high priority for revaccination. We investigated longitudinal antibody titer data in a cohort of 2526 people in Fukushima, Japan, collected between April 2021 and November 2022. Using mathematical modeling and machine learning, we stratified the time-course patterns of antibody titers after two primary doses and one booster dose of COVID-19 messenger RNA vaccines. We identified three populations, which we refer to as the durable, the vulnerable, and the rapid-decliner populations, and approximately half of the participants remained in the same population after the booster dose. The rapid-decliner population experienced earlier infections than the others. Furthermore, when comparing spike protein–specific immunoglobulin G (IgG) titers, spike protein–specific IgA titers, and SARS-CoV-2–specific T cell responses between participants who experienced subsequent infections after booster vaccination and those who did not, we found that spike protein–specific IgA titers were lower during the early stage after booster vaccination in participants who went on to become infected with SARS-CoV-2. This approach could be used to inform policy decisions on vaccine distribution to maximize population-level immunity both in future pandemics and in the post–COVID-19 pandemic era.
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.adv4214
ISSN: 1946-6234
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-09-27</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1126/scitranslmed.adv4214-2025-09-27-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>