<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Rheumatology) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:08:00 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:08:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Injury and local injection and the risk of foot/ankle osteoarthritis: a case–control study in retired UK male professional footballers</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1093/rheumatology/keaf518</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 342
Autoren: Ahmed Ali Thanoon, Shima Espahbodi, Monirah Ali Shuaib, Bonnie Millar, Ashley Duncan, Catherine J Bowen, Terence W O’Neill, Richard J Wakefield, Fiona E Watt, David A Walsh, Gordon Fuller, Mark E Batt, Sanjay M Parekh, Gwen Sascha Fernandes, Michael Doherty, Weiya Zhang
Journal: Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-22
Abstract: Abstract
                  
                    Objective
                    The objective of this study was to examine whether foot/ankle injury and injection contribute to the risk of foot/ankle OA in retired UK male professional footballers.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    This was a case–control study among retired UK male footballers, in which cases reported General Practitioner–diagnosed foot/ankle OA or forefoot/ankle surgery after retirement, and controls reported neither. Injury was defined as significant foot/ankle injury with pain for most days over 3 months during their career. Injection was defined as injection of corticosteroids or other agents into foot/ankle joints during their career. Adjusted odds ratios (aORs) with 95% confidence interval (CIs) were calculated using logistic regression. Areas Under the Curve (AUCs) and 95% CIs were estimated to examine the contribution of injury and/or injection in the context of other available risk factors.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Of 424 footballers studied, 63 had foot/ankle OA and 361 had neither. Cases had similar mean age (63.2 vs 63.0, P = 0.457) and BMI (27.7 vs 27.0, P = 0.240) to those of controls, but more foot/ankle injury (73.3% vs 42.5%, P &amp;amp;lt; 0.001) and injections (75.0% vs 48.4%, P &amp;amp;lt; 0.001), with aORs of 4.23 (95% CI 1.88–9.48) and 2.62 (95% CI 1.19–5.78), respectively. The AUC was 0.69 (95% CI 0.62–0.77) for injury, 0.74 (95% CI 0.66–0.81) for injury and injection, and 0.78 (95% CI 0.70–0.85) for all risk factors. Similar results were observed in footballers with ankle OA only.
                  
                  
                    Conclusion
                    Injury was a major risk factor for foot/ankle OA in retired UK male professional footballers. The role of injection needs cautious interpretation due to potential confounding by indication.
                  
DOI: 10.1093/rheumatology/keaf518
ISSN: 1462-0324
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1093/rheumatology/keaf518-2025-11-04-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Clinical and cost-effectiveness of a cycling and education intervention versus usual physiotherapy care for the treatment of hip osteoarthritis in the UK (CLEAT): a pragmatic, randomised, controlled trial</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00102-x</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 140
Autoren: Thomas W Wainwright, Tikki Immins, Sharon Docherty, Geoff Saunders, Annie Hawton, Elizabeth Goodwin, Tim Rees, Matthew Low, Jo Samways, Fran Webley, Nikki Howard, Paul H Lee, Robert G Middleton
Journal: The Lancet Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-11-01
DOI: 10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00102-x
ISSN: 2665-9913
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/s2665-9913(25)00102-x-2025-11-04-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Blocking the neonatal Fc receptor as a novel approach to prevent cardiac neonatal lupus: a proof-of-concept study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.09.011</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 120
Autoren: Philip M. Carlucci, Mala Masson, Bettina F. Cuneo, Justin S. Brandt, Angus B. Worthing, Peter Izmirly, Nicola Fraser, Nalani Sachan, Mary T. Donofrio, Robert Clancy, Jill P. Buyon
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.09.011
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.09.011-2025-11-04-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Challenges in the diagnosis, classification and prognosis of ANCA-associated vasculitis</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41584-025-01306-w</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 109
Autoren: Marta Casal Moura, Peter A. Merkel, David Jayne, Maria C. Cid, Neil Basu, Bernhard Hellmich, Benjamin Terrier, Abraham Rutgers, Jennifer Gordon, Peter Verhoeven, Joyce Kullman, Carol A. Langford, Ingeborg M. Bajema, Duvuru Geetha, Fernando C. Fervenza, A. Richard Kitching, John H. Stone, Ulrich Specks, Andreas Kronbichler
Journal: Nature Reviews Rheumatology
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-16
DOI: 10.1038/s41584-025-01306-w
ISSN: 1759-4790
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41584-025-01306-w-2025-11-04-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>EULAR recommendations for the management of systemic lupus erythematosus with kidney involvement: 2025 update</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ard.2025.09.007</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Rheumatology
Score: 85
Autoren: Antonis Fanouriakis, Myrto Kostopoulou, Hans-Joachim Anders, Jeanette Andersen, Martin Aringer, Michael W. Beresford, Andrea Doria, Eleni Frangou, Richard Furie, Dafna D. Gladman, Frederic Houssiau, Alexandre Karras, Marios Kouloumas, Anastasia-Vasiliki Madenidou, Ana Malvar, Smaragdi Marinaki, Chi Chiu Mok, Gabriella Moroni, Ioannis Parodis, Simona Rednic, Cristiana Sieiro Santos, Carlo Alberto Scire, Josef S. Smolen, Farah Tamirou, Yoshiya Tanaka, Y. K. Onno Teng, Elisabet Welin, George Bertsias, Dimitrios T. Boumpas
Journal: Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases
Veröffentlicht: 2025-10-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.ard.2025.09.007
ISSN: 0003-4967
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2025-11-04</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.ard.2025.09.007-2025-11-04-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>