<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>OOIR Trends: Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics)</title>
		<description>Aktuelle Paper-Trends im Bereich Clinical Medicine (Medical Informatics) von OOIR (mit Titel und Metadaten von Crossref)</description>
		<link>https://ooir.org</link>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 01:08:22 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 01:08:22 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi Games’ Affordance of Childlike Wonder and Reduced Burnout Risk in Young Adults: In-Depth Mixed Methods Cross-Sectional Study</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.2196/84219</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 503
Autoren: Winze Tam, Congcong Hou, Andreas Benedikt Eisingerich
Journal: JMIR Serious Games
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-19
Abstract: 
                    Background
                    Unrelenting pressure and an “always-on” culture can leave no time for genuine rest among young adults. While playing video games has been noted to afford cognitive escapism and relaxation, critical questions remain about the influence of popular video games, such as Super Mario Bros., and their potential effects on young adults’ burnout risk.
                  
                  
                    Objective
                    This study examined the extent to which, if at all, popular video games such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi could foster childlike wonder. It also investigated the potential of these games to reduce burnout risk among young adults.
                  
                  
                    Methods
                    We used a mixed methods approach. First, qualitative data were collected through 41 exploratory, in-depth interviews (women: n=19, 46.3%; men: n=21, 51.2%; prefer not to disclose sex: n=11, 2.4%; mean age 22.51, SD 1.52 years) with university students who had experience playing Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi. Second, quantitative data were collected in a cross-sectional survey (N=336) of players of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi to examine the games’ affordance of childlike wonder, overall happiness in life, and burnout risk.
                  
                  
                    Results
                    Insights from in-depth interviews showed that players appreciated the ability of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games to instill childlike wonder, enhance happiness in life, and reduce burnout risk. Quantitative analyses showed that the games’ affordance of childlike wonder positively affected young adults’ happiness (b=0.30, SE=0.04, t=6.80, 95% CI 0.21-0.38; P&amp;lt;.001). In turn, overall happiness significantly reduced the risk of burnout (b=–0.48, SE=0.05, t=–9.55, 95% CI –0.572 to –0.377). Results showed that happiness fully mediated the impact of childlike wonder on burnout, as the direct effect of childlike wonder on burnout risk became insignificant (b=–0.08, SE=0.04, t=–1.88, 95% CI –0.16 to 0.01; P=.06), while the indirect effect of childlike wonder on burnout risk was significant (b=–0.14, bootstrapped SE=0.03, 95% CI –0.20 to –0.09).
                  
                  
                    Conclusions
                    The findings showed the significant positive effect of popular video games such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi on fostering players’ childlike wonder, increasing happiness, and reducing burnout risk. This study was among the first to identify childlike wonder as an emotional pathway through which mainstream video games could enhance well-being and reduce burnout. By moving beyond escapism and nostalgia, it offers a new perspective on how well-designed, globally familiar games can function as accessible, resilience-building digital microenvironments. These findings contributed to research bridging gaming and mental health and have practical implications for game designers, educators, and health professionals interested in promoting mental wellness through everyday play.
                  
DOI: 10.2196/84219
ISSN: 2291-9279
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.2196/84219-2026-01-13-1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Association of sleep patterns assessed by a smartphone application with work productivity loss among Japanese employees</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-02155-3</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 201
Autoren: Jaehoon Seol, Masao Iwagami, Masashi Yanagisawa
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-11
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-02155-3
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-02155-3-2026-01-13-2</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Personalizing prostate cancer education for patients using an EHR-Integrated LLM agent</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-025-02166-0</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 52
Autoren: Yuexing Hao, Jason Holmes, Mark R. Waddle, Brian J. Davis, Nathan Y. Yu, Kristin S. Vickers, Heather Preston, Drew Margolin, Corinna E. Löckenhoff, Aditya Vashistha, Saleh Kalantari, Marzyeh Ghassemi, Wei Liu
Journal: npj Digital Medicine
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-18
Abstract: Abstract
                  Cancer patients often lack timely education and personalized support due to clinician workload. This quality improvement study develops and evaluates a Large Language Model (LLM) agent, MedEduChat, which is integrated with the clinic’s electronic health records (EHR) and designed to enhance prostate cancer patient education. Fifteen non-metastatic prostate cancer patients and three clinicians recruited from the Mayo Clinic interacted with the agent between May 2024 and April 2025. Findings showed that MedEduChat has a high usability score (UMUX = 83.7/100) and improves patients’ health confidence (Health Confidence Score rose from 9.9 to 13.9). Clinicians evaluated the patient-chat interaction history and rated MedEduChat as highly correct (2.9/3), complete (2.7/3), and safe (2.7/3), with moderate personalization (2.3/3). This study highlights the potential of LLM agents to improve patient engagement and health education.
DOI: 10.1038/s41746-025-02166-0
ISSN: 2398-6352
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1038/s41746-025-02166-0-2026-01-13-3</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Evaluation of performance measures in predictive artificial intelligence models to support medical decisions: overview and guidance</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landig.2025.100916</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 51
Autoren: Ben Van Calster, Gary S Collins, Andrew J Vickers, Laure Wynants, Kathleen F Kerr, Lasai Barreñada, Gael Varoquaux, Karandeep Singh, Karel GM Moons, Tina Hernandez-Boussard, Dirk Timmerman, David J McLernon, Maarten van Smeden, Ewout W Steyerberg
Journal: The Lancet Digital Health
Veröffentlicht: 2025-12-01
DOI: 10.1016/j.landig.2025.100916
ISSN: 2589-7500
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1016/j.landig.2025.100916-2026-01-13-4</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A Feature-Augmented Transformer Model to Recognize Functional Activities From in-the-Wild Smartwatch Data</title>
			<link>https://doi.org/10.1109/jbhi.2025.3586074</link>
			<description>Feld: Clinical Medicine
Kategorie: Medical Informatics
Score: 40
Autoren: Bryan Minor, Colin Greeley, Ryan Holder, Brian Thomas, Lawrence B. Holder, Diane J. Cook
Journal: IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics
Veröffentlicht: 2026-01-01
DOI: 10.1109/jbhi.2025.3586074
ISSN: 2168-2194
Tag der Erhebung (OOIR): 2026-01-13</description>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">ooir-trend-10.1109/jbhi.2025.3586074-2026-01-13-5</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>